<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Conscience satisfied. That there is no warrant for the armes now taken up by subjects. By way of reply unto severall answers made to a treatise formerly published for the resolving of conscience upon the case. Especially unto that which is entituled A fuller answer. By H. Ferne, D.D. &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Ferne, H. (Henry), 1602-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 241 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85229</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F791</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E97_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212790</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871360</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871360</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155829</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85229)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155829)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 17:E97[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Conscience satisfied. That there is no warrant for the armes now taken up by subjects. By way of reply unto severall answers made to a treatise formerly published for the resolving of conscience upon the case. Especially unto that which is entituled A fuller answer. By H. Ferne, D.D. &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Ferne, H. (Henry), 1602-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 85, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Leonard Lichfield Printer to the Vniversity,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford [i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In part a reply to: Herle, Charles.  A fuller answer to a treatise written by Doctor Ferne, entituled The resolving of conscience upon this question.</note>
                  <note>The imprint is false. "This is a paginatim and almost lineatim reprint of the true Oxford edition, done in London. On page 85 are four "Errata", not in the original. On page 2 line 9 begins 'stake is in him', not as in the original 'him that coplains'"--Madan.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>In this edition, line 13 of title page has "fuller" (lowercased).</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 18th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Herle, Charles, 1598-1659. --  Fuller answer to a treatise written by Doctor Ferne, entituled The resolving of conscience upon this question.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155829:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CONSCIENCE SATISFIED.</p>
            <p>That there is no warrant for the Armes now taken up by SUBjECTS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY WAY OF REPLY</hi> unto ſeverall Anſwers made to a Treatiſe formerly publiſhed for the Reſolving of Conſcience upon <hi>the</hi> CASE.</p>
            <p>ESPECIALLY Unto that which is entituled <hi>A fuller Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By H. FERNE, D. D. &amp;c.</p>
            <q>Speake unto the Elders of <hi>Iudah,</hi> ſaying, what? are yee the laſt to bring the King back to His Houſe? ſeeing the ſpeech of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> is come to the <hi>King.</hi>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Sam. 19.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Let your Moderation be known unto all men; the Lord is at hand,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Phil. 4.5</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by LEONARD LICHFIELD <hi>Printer to the Vniverſity,</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:155829:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155829:2"/>
            <head>To the Conſcientious Readers among the People.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O you eſpecially this is intended, who profeſſing to make a Conſcience of your wayes have hitherto been led on in the dangerous and perverſe way of Reſiſtance and diſloyaltie; to give you ſome check, and call you at leaſt to a thought of the violent Courſe you were in purſuit of, there was a <hi>Treatiſe</hi> formerly directed to you, for your better help in the examination of your <hi>Way,</hi> and the <hi>Reſolving</hi> of your <hi>Conſciences,</hi> for it was marvailous to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, how men pretending Religion and Conſcience, ſhould be ſo ſecurely carryed on without all warrant, ſo hood winckt with an implicite faith, againſt the cleere light of the Law of God and this Land meeting them in the face, which faith as by reaſon of its blindneſſe, it is moſt contrary to a Conſcience deſirous to be informed, ſo the blinder it is, the ſtronger it is, and leaves a man miſerably deceived with the conceipt of a Conſcience well fatisfied.</p>
            <p>To hold you on in this blinde devotion, Foure Anſwerers have appeared for you againſt the aforeſaid Treatiſe, that you may at leaſt ſay, you have foure for one; but if you take them all and <hi>bray them in a Mortar</hi> together you ſhall not beate out of them any true and reall Cauſes of theſe your Armes, but Pretences onely, nor any warrant from the Law of God, or of
<pb facs="tcp:155829:3"/>this Land to juſtifie your taking Armes upon ſuch Cauſes, were they never ſo true and reall. That you may more eaſily diſcern what is in them, &amp; thereby the truth, I have take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them in peices for you, and by this <hi>Reply</hi> ſhewen you what is adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate. It is chiefly directed againſt M. <hi>Bridge</hi> his book, and the <hi>Fuller Anſwer;</hi> againſt that, becauſe it appeares under the Licence and Authority of Them he pleads for, and is framed more to the capacity of the Vulgar; againſt This, becauſe it is cryed up among the more Intelligent of the Party, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries an appearing depth of Reaſon, though indeed no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then ſtained waters doe, which ſeem deep through the darkneſſe of their Colour. What is materiall in M. <hi>Burrowes</hi> you ſhall finde repeated in Theirs, or his own words, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving anſwer. With that other Anſwer, which appeares with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out name, but with a Margin full of Greek and Latin, I dare truſt you, ſo that you will beware of one thing, that dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous diſcourſe he has for the ſuppreſſing and taking away of Tyrants, and will promiſe me another thing, that you will not proceed in this unjuſtifiable way without direct and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive warrant for Conſcience to reſt on; Yet ſhall you have ſomething in particular to this Anſwerer in the 12. <hi>Section.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before that <hi>Fuller Anſwer</hi> came to my hands, I was told by one, that had reaſon to know, I ſhould receive anſwer from a grave Divine; but having peruſed it, I found little of the Divine, leſſe of his Gravity: but a phanſy both ridiculous and dangerous. He has ſet before his book a Premonition (wherein he has painted out the <hi>Reſolver</hi> under the ſeverall ſhapes of birds and beaſts, as his flitting phanſy led him) a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry peice of Pictured Tapeſtry, fitter to hang before the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of a Stage, then of a Treatiſe concerning Conſcience: but which is worſt of all, concern's not me onely but eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Subject, in his book he has phanſied ſuch a frame of Government here in this Land, that he has marr'd it in the
<pb facs="tcp:155829:3"/>Making, for by an unheard of Coordination he has contrived it into a plain Popular State.</p>
            <p>I held my ſelfe many wayes (though this Age has had books enough to teach it duty) engaged to anſwer, for my own, for yours, for Truths ſake; I found my ſelfe much abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by miſtakes, and odious imputations, eſpecially of the <hi>Full Anſwerer,</hi> but you worſe by deceiving pretences, &amp; Truth worſt of all by falſe Principles, and Doctrines given out under its name.</p>
            <p>I deſire you would underſtand, what was ſpoken by me in the former Treatiſe, by way of Aſſertion, Concluſion, or ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Rule concerning the two Houſes, was but a ſacrificing to Truth from a Conſcience not ſimply devoted to man; what was related as matter of Fact, did either not concern them, or not touch them with any ſuch foule aſperſion, as the <hi>Fuller Anſwerer</hi> would make you beleeve; My Conſcience is clear, and my paper was not ſtained with ſuch blots.</p>
            <p>For diſaffection to Parliaments (wherewith I am charged) I will not ſay how far my heart went along with This in the way of approbation, but thus much I will ſay, I alwayes had, and ſtill have to Parliaments affection enough (though not to make me a Rebell to the light of Reaſon, and Rules of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or diſloyall to His Majeſty, yet enough) to ground a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny due obedience upon. My heart would faile me (as hers did upon the <hi>departure of glory from Iſrael,</hi> 1 Sam. 4.) to think, how the Name of Religion and Authority of Parliament would ſuffer in after Times, could they juſtly be entitled to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry of theſe.</p>
            <p>But I take it to be the deſire of all good men and Loyall Subjects, yea of the King himſelfe, That Parliaments ſhould flouriſh in their due power and freedom, knowing that neither he nor they can ſuffer by ſuch; &amp; I preſume that many of the Thouſands which follow his Majeſty, have engaged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb facs="tcp:155829:4"/>in the Cauſe, not only out of meer duty of Allegiance, but alſo out of a ſenſe of that very deſire, they are Confident is in Him, to the continuance of Parliaments; being ſuch for the moſt part, as have no other hope of advantage by the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, then peaceably to enjoy what by the Law of the Land they may call their own; ſuch <hi>whoſe hearts God hath touched</hi> as he did theirs, that went with <hi>Saul,</hi> when ſome children of <hi>Belial</hi> deſpiſed him, ſaying, <hi>how ſhall this man ſave us?</hi> 1 Sam. 10.</p>
            <p>Should I bring in the Kingdome (as <hi>Ioab</hi> did the ſuborned Widdow of <hi>Tekoah</hi>) like a woman in mourning apparell to ſpeak the truth, you would hear her Complaining, <hi>Her Sonns have ſtriven together in the field, and ſmitten and ſlaine one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> but for the iniquity, <hi>let the King and his Throne be guiltleſſe,</hi> 2 Sam. 14. and farther adding, Let the name of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be ſacred, and the Authority of Parliament blameleſſe; but there are certain Men upon whom the iniquity will lye heavy as the grave-ſtone, and upon whoſe tombs, if this Land give them buriall, poſterity will write, <hi>Better theſe Men had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been born.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If therefore the Ambition, Envy or Avarice of any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular men have engaged you under the ſpecious pretences of Religion and Liberty, look upon your ſelves at length, and how you are uſed but as their ſword and buckler to make way for their ends, and to defend them from the ſtroke of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; And ſhould they by your aid attain thoſe ends (which God for bid) will they for your conſpiring with them, <hi>give every one of you fields and vineyards, and make you Captaines of thouſands, and Captaines of hundreds?</hi> hath not His Majeſtie offered enough for the reſtoring of your peace and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, if they would let you underſtand it? can you ſee to the end of theſe troubles, but by returning to your forſaken Loyaltie? ſhall you not be divided again, and cal'd to Faction
<pb facs="tcp:155829:4"/>and ſiding upon the diſpoſing of the offices and revenues of the Kingdom amongſt your Leaders? Or if that buſineſſe could be ſetled, and the world provided for, ſhall you not be divided again when you come to think of a form of Religion? or ſhall you every man be recompenſed with a freedom of his own way, for lending his help to unſettle that One Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which the Laws have eſtabliſhed?</p>
            <p>However your vain hopes doe at length ſucceed, or your Conſcience in the mean time be ſatisfied, I am ſure God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be well pleaſed, and will not (though he hath hitherto ſuffered it for the juſt puniſhment of this ſinfull Land) be long mocked after this faſhion; for do but hearken to the Cry of Blood, to the Cry of the Fatherleſſe and Widdowes, of this Land, of Ireland, to the complaints of the poore every where for want of that reliefe which they had from thouſands of families, now diſſolved by the cauſleſſe impriſonment of the Maſters; if your Eares be not open to them, His are, or if you think you are not chargeable with this heavy account, look to the wayes your Leaders drive you through, how they lye through blood and oppreſſion, through the breach of your Faith, your Allegiance, your Proteſtation, of which it is ſtrange to conſider what advantage has bin made, to the ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming performance of one clauſe in it, (the Priviledge of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments,) by the breach of all the reſt, which concerne the Kings Rights, the Religion eſtabliſhed, the Subjects Liberty and Property; and in all this conſider, how your way is forced through the breach of many of Gods Commandements; I need not tell you them, your very children (if ever you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed them in their Catechiſme) can ſay your practice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees not with what you taught them; but this I muſt tel you, if this be Conſcience, it is a Conſcience that is condemned of it ſelfe, and grown deſperate; if this be Religion, it is a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion that ſaith there is no God. If therefore there be yet any
<pb facs="tcp:155829:5"/>ſenſe left of Conſcience and Religion, any fear of God, ret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> from theſe perverſe wayes, or elſe heare what he threatens to ſuch wilfulneſſe, Lev. 26.23. <hi>If you will walk contrary to me, then will I alſo walk contrary to you.</hi> &amp; Eſa. 30.12. <hi>Becauſe you deſpiſe this word, and truſt in oppreſsion and perverſneſſe, and ſtay thereon, therefore this iniquity ſhall be to you as a breach ready to fall, ſwelling out in a high wall, whoſe breaking commeth ſuddainly at an inſtant.</hi> A great forbearance of God hath it been, that Houſes have not broken down, where the Conſultations have been ſo oft held for the direction of theſe wayes, or that Churches have not faln, where ſo many blaſphemous Prayers and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings have been made, in order to the advancement of them. I ſuppoſe you are not prime Leaders in this way, yet the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger your Directors ſpin out the time, &amp; you hold on to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance the Action, ye doe but increaſe the Cryes of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed throughout this Kingdome againſt you, and cauſe that judgement on high to break down the ſooner; Do not dally any longer with Him that can doe it <hi>ſuddenly in an inſtant,</hi> but look what hangs over our heads, and read what is written, and the Lord give you underſtanding.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155829:5"/>
            <head>CONSCIENCE <hi>SATISFIED.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">That there is no warrant for the Armes <hi>now taken up by the Subjects.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">By way of Reply to ſeverall Anſwers made to a former Treatiſe, eſpecially to that which is called the FVLLER ANSVVER.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 1. <hi>The caſe, and the Queſtion upon it ſtated.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is neceſſary I begin with the Author of that <hi>Fuller Anſwer,</hi> for he begins with a diſcourſe of his owne, and the better to ſet it off, will needs doe mee the favour to rectify the <hi>Caſe,</hi> and ſtate the <hi>Queſtion</hi> for mee. <hi>Blowing aſide,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>the Pinduſt of the stile, which guilds but inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts the letter of his Treatiſe, I finde the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of it to be a groundleſſe ſuppoſition of the Parliaments taking Armes, upon a bare ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Kings meere intention to ſubvert Lawes and Liberties; for who ever maintained they might take Armes upon ſuch a bare ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi> Pag. 1. <hi>alſo I am inforced to anſwer what he would have ſaid, for he reſolves upon a Queſtion, that never came in queſtion,</hi> pag. 2.</p>
               <p>Firſt I muſt deprecate what here and every where this Anſwerer
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:155829:6"/>imputes unto mee, as if I charged the Parliament <hi>(i.e.)</hi> the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes with this Warre; it was no where ſaid, they did take up theſe Armes, but often inſinuated and proved, that, if that were the Caſe, they might not doe it, the more forceably to convince them that have now done it, under the name and pretence of Parliament.</p>
               <p>Then I muſt tell him, it is an eaſie but commonly deceitfull way of Anſwering to ſay the Queſtion is miſtaken, and make the Reader be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve all that was written is nothing to the purpoſe, when as the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake is in him that complaines of it. For if this Anſwerer <hi>in blowing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Pinduſt of the Letter,</hi> as he ſpeakes, had not received much of it into his eyes, he might have ſeen (the Conſciencious Reader will) that the Queſtion for the Rationall part of it, was put to the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of them that plead for Reſiſtance not as he renders it <hi>whether they may take Armes upon a bare ſuppoſition of a meer intention in the King to ſubvert Lawes and Liberties?</hi> as if he knew not what the word <hi>(ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe)</hi> meant in putting of a Caſe, but to this ſenſe, <hi>ſuppoſe or grant the King will not diſcharge the trust, but is bent or ſeduced to ſubvert Lawes and Liberties, whether then may Subjects take Armes?</hi> this implies in the caſe as much or more, then he himſelfe pretends here to bee the cauſe of your Armes, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The actuall invaſion of Liberties, the invitation and detention of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents from tryall by Law, to be a party in Armes againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to diſſolve or remove it, the importation of forraigne. Armes, and Souldiers, illegall Commiſſions to imploy them, &amp;c.</hi> ſo he, pag 1. To take no notice for the preſent of the falſhood of theſe imputations where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with His Majeſty is here charged, we muſt look upon them, as the ſuppoſed cauſes of their Armes.</p>
               <p>And firſt I cannot but wonder, why among theſe particulars here's no mention of Religion, when as the people are made to beleeve that's it they fight for; happily he included it in the &amp;c. as indeed in the conſultations of theſe unhappy daies, the care of it (though time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moved by worthy Members of both Houſes) has been caſt off to the fagge end of other more neceſſary occaſions, that I may not ſay Deſignes, a likely way to make all proſper.</p>
               <p>When the people are dealt with by ſuch men as theſe Anſwerers, then <hi>Religion</hi> is the main Engine to draw them into Armes, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed were they not abuſed with that plauſible pretence, they could never have been ſo farre engaged againſt their Soveraigne: but when
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:155829:6"/>theſe men enter the liſts with an Adverſary about the cauſe of this warre, <hi>Religion</hi> is not inſiſted on, not once touched in this, expreſly declined in the other Anſwers: but <hi>Nature</hi> is rather ſought unto by them, for a ground of ſelfe preſervation; for upon ſtrict examination theſe men know, it will appear what <hi>actuall invaſions</hi> have been made upon Religion againſt the known Lawes of this land, and who are to anſwer for them; they know alſo what offence it would give to ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Sects (which are and will be alwaies ſerviceable to new deſignes) ſhould Religion be either countenanced, as it is by Law eſtabliſhed, or any one way declared for.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly I would fain know, whether they can in Conſcience be perſwaded, that ſome <hi>actuall invaſions of Lawes and Liberties</hi> can be a ſufficient cauſe for Subjects to Arme and Reſiſt, when it evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeares their Soveraigne is not bent to continue in that deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive way; will it not ſuffice, if he reſtore thoſe Liberties, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw the encroachments made upon them? If he promiſe ſecurity and paſſe ſeverall Acts of Grace for further aſſurance of them? If he be content that, All Armes laid aſide, the Law ſhall judge who are Delinquents, and accordingly cenſure them?</p>
               <p>They that have formerly written for Reſiſtance in ſome Caſes, have thought it unreaſonable that Subjects ſhould pretend to Armes, till they find their Prince in ſuch a Condition, as was inſinuated in the <hi>caſe</hi> propoſed, <hi>viz. Bent or ſeduced to ſubvert Lawes, Liberties, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or to <hi>make havock of the Common-wealth or Church,</hi> as D. <hi>Willet</hi> ha's it in <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>q.</hi> 17 and as we ſee by the limitations, teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, examples in <hi>Paraeus</hi> upon <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. and in <hi>Phil. Par.</hi> his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Owen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But our Pleaders for Reſiſtance at this day, becauſe they cannot find His <hi>Majeſty</hi> in ſuch a condition; or hope to make men (that know a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of His Perſonall Vertucs, or His Acts of Grace paſſed this Parliament) believe, he is ſo <hi>bent,</hi> doe now pretend they have cauſe enough for taking Armes, <hi>what ever the Kings mind be and although there be no ſuch horrible things intended by him as the Doctor ſpeakes of,</hi> ſo M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</hi> pag. 140.141. and to the ſame pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>poſe this <hi>Fuller An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi> inſiſts upon <hi>actuall invaſions of Liborvies, Lawes,</hi> as the cauſe of their Armes.</p>
               <p>Yet that they may ſeem to have better pretence of Reaſon for what they doe, and more win upon the people, that leaſt know the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155829:7"/>gratious diſpoſition of their Soveraigne towards them, they doe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to charge His Majeſty with the like deſtructive intentions, as were to be ſuppoſed in the caſe.</p>
               <p>To this purpoſe we find this Anſwerer every where rendring the reaſon of their taking Arms to be, <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>uſe the King refuſes to performe His truſt,</hi> and in the firſt page; becauſe His Majeſty has <hi>drawn in Delinquents to be a party in Armes thereby to diſſolve or remove the arliament;</hi> where he puts the Cauſe upon His Majeſties intention. And we well remember upon His Majeſties firſt Guard at <hi>Yorke,</hi> it was (I will not ſay voted above) given out among the people, <hi>He in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to make Warre againſt His Parliament,</hi> and ſtill we have it ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged as a Cauſe of theſe Arms, that His Majeſty is <hi>ſeduced by wicked Councell,</hi> and the like.</p>
               <p>Therefore the Caſe being ſo laid upon his ſuppoſed intentions to continue in a ſubverſive way of Lawes, Liberties, the queſtion upon it was put to the full, for the rationall part, <hi>whether, ſuch a caſe being ſuppoſed or granted, it were Lawfull for Subjects to take Armes and reſist?</hi> Then for the other part of the queſtion, which concerned mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact, <hi>Whether that caſe were now? (i.e.)</hi> whether it were true of His Majeſty which they ſuppoſed and took for granted, and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to make the people believe of Him? it was of a ſecond conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and examined after by it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Every mean underſtanding might eaſily conceave this to be the ſenſe of the Queſtion, the briefe of the Cauſe, and of my Treatiſe.</p>
               <p>But this Anſwerer it ſeems, had a diſcourſe of the power of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s lying by him, (for no man will think it occaſioned by my book, but applyed to it) and therefore thought fit to quarrell at the Queſtion as propoſed by mee, and in ſtead of my three Reſolves, to give the Reader three Propoſitions of his own, he ſhould have made them moe, but for obſerving number. And then he boaſts, <hi>How many weekes ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Doctor has been about the Treatiſe, it is well known to many, the Anſwer coſt not many houres the doing,</hi> pag. 3. he means the apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of what was done before; but any one may perceive by his confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed jumbling of things, and his frequent miſtakes when ever he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats and anſwers what I had written, that he was ambitious of doing the buſineſſe haſtily, rather then ſurely.</p>
               <p>Wee'l follow him as we may, firſt examining how he makes good his Propoſitions or grounds he goes on, then how he applyes them to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:155829:7"/>what I had written, where we ſhall tak in the other Anſwers, as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion requires.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II. <hi>The frame of this Government as it is fancied in the</hi> Fuller Anſwer.</head>
               <p>HIs whole reſolution of the Cauſe is laid down in his firſt Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, which is this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Parliament may with good Conſcience in defence of the King, Lawes, and Government eſtabliſhed, when imminently endangered, take up Armes without or against the Kings Perſonall commands if He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe.</hi> His other two Propoſitions are ſubſervient to this, tending to the proofe of it; <hi>That the finall reſult of this States judgment, what thoſe Lawes, Dangers, and meanes of prevention are, reſides in the two Houſes of Parliament,</hi> Prop. 2. <hi>That in this finall reſolution the People are to reſt, and in obedience thereto may with good Conſcience bear and uſe Armes,</hi> Prop. 3.</p>
               <p>To make this good he firſt endeavours to ſhew this Monarchy is mixt, by a <hi>Coordination of the two Houſes with the King in the very ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy of power it ſelfe,</hi> ſo he pag. 3. Whereupon if the King refuſe to provide for the ſafety of the Kingdome according to their advice, then <hi>His coordinates; the two Houſes muſt according to their truſts ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,</hi> ſo he tells us, p. 3.8.10. And that this power was <hi>reſerved by the people at the firſt conſtitution of this government,</hi> pag. 24.25. and that this conſtitution was made <hi>by conſent of King and People in the firſt Coalition of Government,</hi> pag. 4. by the <hi>Conſent of the People th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t firſt made the King,</hi> pag. 13. <hi>Contrived by the people in the firſt conſtitution <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f Gov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ernment,</hi> pag. 8.</p>
               <p>Theſe Particulars we find in this his diſcourſe confuſedly ſpoken of, if we give his conceptions their due order, they ſtand thus. Firſt, he ſuppoſes all the Power of government to be derived from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and that the Conſtitution of this Government was their contriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when firſt they made a King; then, that by this firſt Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſuch a Coordination of the two Houſes with the King was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived, by which they have power reſerved, not only to conſent in making Lawes, but to ſupply the refuſalls of the King, as they ſhall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155829:8"/>think good for the ſafety of the State; and for this, the finall reſult of the States judgement is in them to declare what is Law without him, and unto their finall reſolution, and commands thereupon, though arbitrary (as this anſwerer acknowledgeth <hi>Pag.</hi> 17) the people ought to obey.</p>
               <p>Thus has he fanſied the reaſon and conſtitution of this Government, but I ſuppoſe the honourable houſes of <hi>Parliament</hi> will not thanke him for raiſing them to that height of Supremacy, he has placed them in; I am ſure we Subjects have not cauſe to thank him for that arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary power he has placed in them.</p>
               <p>If any man expect from this his diſcourſe, ſatisfaction for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, he ſhall find nothing but uncertainties, and improbabilities, not fit grounds for it to reſtupon; and if conviction of Reaſon be look't for here, I ſuppoſe there is no man that upon ſerious conſideration of what this Anſwerer brings us to, will not think it more reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be under the arbitrary Government of one, then of many, nay, under the Government of one that challenges not obedience as due, bat according to Law, then of many, whoſe commands are Law un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us; as this Anſwerer makes them.</p>
               <p>And here we doe not undertake to ſet down the extent of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and Priviledges of <hi>Parliament;</hi> no more then of the Kings Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and prerogative. They are both of them beyond our skill, and we may not take the boldneſſe to meddle with either of them, farther then the neceſſary information of Conſcience doth inforce: to which purpoſe as we may by uſe of Reaſon certainly conclude, the King has not this or that Power, as to make Lawes by himſelfe, to rule arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily; ſo of the two Houſes without offence we may as certainly conclude, That they have not ſuch a power by the firſt Conſtitution of this Government, as this Anſwerer every where beggs for them, but no where proves it.</p>
               <p>It is granted that the two Houſes of Parliament are in a ſort Coor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate with His MAIESTY, <hi>ad aliquid,</hi> to ſome act or exeaciſing of the ſupream power, that is to the making of Lawes by yeelding their conſent; and that they have this by a fundamentall Conſtitution. But that they have ſuch a fellow ſhip with His MAIESTY in the Supremacy it ſelfe, as this man imagines, or ſuch a Power of reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance reſerved at firſt to ſupply His MAIESTIES refuſa's; or ſuch a finall and arbitrary Power and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmand, as he attributes to them, Conſcience can never be truly convinced off.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:155829:8"/>
               <head>SECT. III. <hi>Of the Originall of Governing power, and of the beginnings of Government in this Land.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE will begin with his ground-work, Which lies ſcattered through all his diſcourſe, That firſt Coalition or Conſitituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Government in this Land, which he ſuppoſes to be framed by the agreement or Contrivement of the people when they made the firſt King; wherein they intruſted him with ſuch Power as was thought fit, and reſerved to themſelves what power they held neceſſary for their owne ſafety, upon extraordinary times and occaſion of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
               <p>So then Conſcience, if it will obey the power of Armes now uſurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Subjects, muſt be clearly convinced (which is impoſſible) of theſe particulars, That the Governning Power is from the people, that Monarchy was here raiſed upon ſuch a contrivement, wherein ſuch a power of ſupply, and of reſiſtance, was reſerved to the People, and that all Kings ſince, do conſent to ſuch conditions, and are admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted under them.</p>
               <p>All the proofe that I can any where find this Anſwer ha's brought for all this, is from the words of <hi>Forteſcue, Hanc poteſtatem a populo effluxam,</hi> this Power the King ha's derived from the People; and from the mutuall Oath of King and People, <hi>pag.</hi> 5. Let the Reader give me leave to ſpeak a little of the Governing power ſimply; then of the beginning of Government in this Land, that Conſcience may ſee what little ſatisfaction this or any man els can give it, to perſwade either that the governing power is derived from the people, or that the Government of this Land began in ſuch a Contrivement or conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution as this man phanſies.</p>
               <p>It was ſaid in my other Treatiſe, that the Governing power was from God, not only as an ordinance of the precept that commands Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, but alſo as an Efflux or iſſue of that providence, which ſets up &amp; pulls down, which tranſlates Kingdomes, and governs the whole world, Creatures Reaſonable and unreaſonable; and this not obſcurely in the <hi>Apoſtle, Rom.</hi> 13. where the powers are ſaid to be not only <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> from God, but alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as orders ranked by him and under him.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:155829:9"/>
               <p>Well then, this Governing power was not <hi>a populo effluxa,</hi> as he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſaid, but flowed from that providence at firſt through the veines of nature in a paternal or Fatherly rule, and by that as by a pattern in a Kingly Rule or Government, upon the encreaſe of people and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for when the Reins of Paternall Government could not reach them for their extent, or hold them in for their unrulines, &amp; injuſtice, it in larged it ſelfe into a Kingly power, which bore and uſed the ſword; for that is given them to uſe ſtreight after the Flood. <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.6.</p>
               <p>This is plain by the booke of God, that the firſt Fathers of Mankind, were the firſt Kings and Rulers; for we ſee the Earth divided among <hi>Noah's</hi> three Sons, and upon the Encreaſe of their Children many Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonies were ſent into Countries farre diſtant, and thereupon many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependant Governments raiſed; which muſt be by the direction and order of <hi>Noah,</hi> that firſt ſent them out and aſſigned them thoſe parts of the Earth; And ſtill as they encreaſed, they ſpread farther upon the face of the Earth, new Colonies being excluded and thruſt forth (like ſwarmes of Bees) under their Rulers, who were the cheife Fathers of thoſe new Progenies, and had the Government, both Regall and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotall by Primogeniture, unles the chiefe Patriarch, from whom they all iſſued, ſaw cauſe to order it otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>Therefore of all the Sons of <hi>Noah</hi> &amp; the Nations ſprung from them it is ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 10. <hi>theſe are the Sons of Noah —after their Families in their Countries and Nations. verſ.</hi> 5, 20, 31. and we find many of thoſe firſt Princes and rulers to leave their names to the people that came of them, and to the Countries they were ſeated in; as may be ſeen, <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>Hence it appeares. Firſt, that Monarchy was the firſt Government it being late ere any Popular Rule, Ariſtocraticall or Democraticall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the world. Secondly, that the firſt Kings were not by choice of the People, but that Monarchy (however we cannot ſay it is <hi>jure divino,</hi> by divine precept commanding all Nations to be ſo governed, or <hi>jure naturae</hi> by natures law enforcing it) is plainly <hi>ductu naturae,</hi> by nature leading men from Paternall to Regall Government, and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplo divino,</hi> as I may ſay, by divine example and inſinuation; the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment that God ſet up over his people, being Monarchicall ſtill, in <hi>Moſes,</hi> the <hi>Iudges,</hi> the <hi>Kings;</hi> whereas Ariſtocracy, and Democracy, (that I'may not call them Defections and Revolts from the Naturall
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155829:9"/>way of government) are meer inventions of man; In ſeverall Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies indeed we ſee divers limitations &amp; qualifications of power, and ſeverall offices &amp; wayes of executing that power, theſe are meer inventions of man. And this I note for explication of what was in the other Treatiſe ſaid of Monarchy in relation to <hi>Ius divinum,</hi> which by this Anſwerer is often interpreted, as if I granted Monarchy, and Ariſtocracy, and Democracy to be equally of humane invention.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it appears that the power of Kings was as of Fathers, and that the people had no power of coertion over them, more than chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren over Fathers. Fourthly, that albeit within few ages after the flood, people began to chuſe themſelves Rulers, (as likely they did that departed from the building of <hi>Babel</hi> in ſeverall companies, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your ſeverall languages) yet was ſuch popular election to be accounted a kind of defection from, and a diſturbance of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall way of the deſcent of governing kingly power, by a Paternall right; and this irregular way began in the progeny of <hi>Cham.</hi> Laſtly, that albeit when a people are free, as upon the utter failing of the royall Line, they may chuſe a Governour, (there being then no other way to ſet up one but by choice) yet then do they no more give the power, than if they received a King by naturall deſcent, or by Gods deſignment, and ſtill the King ſo choſen is a Father, as in the fifth Commandement, and the people as children in the ſame relation for obedience and coertion, as at firſt in the generations of <hi>Noah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Accordingly kings at firſt among the Nations though choſen, ruled as Fathers, arbitrarily, their diſcretion being law unto the people, as was obſerved out of <hi>Iuſtin,</hi> in the former Treatiſe, and as we may really ſee in the fiction of the Golden Age.</p>
               <p>Now for the beginning of Government in this Iſland, how ſhall conſcience find any certainty, that it was ſo ſet up &amp; contrived as this Anſwerer ſuppoſeth? If he will begin ſimply at the very firſt coaliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Government (as he phraſes it) he muſt ſuppoſe a multitude of people meeting together to contrive a Government, and theſe either to ſpring on a ſuddain out of the earth, as <hi>Cadmus</hi> his race, but then in all likelyhood they would not ſo well agree; or to live diſperſedly in caves &amp; woods, and ſo to be brought together by ſome <hi>Orpheus</hi> his pipe, but then we cannot imagine ſuch rude men to be ſo politique and cautious as to make ſuch a contrivement, for he tells us the <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> which we ſee in this State, is that ſame reaſon that firſt contrived
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:155829:10"/>the Government when they made the firſt King; Or laſtly, he muſt ſuppoſe this land was peopled by a colony from <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Germany,</hi> and then as likely they had the conſtitution of the Government from the King which ſent them, or that the government which the firſt Kings uſed here was arbitrary, as it was every where elſe at firſt.</p>
               <p>But let us come down to times of more certainty, and, as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of Parliament, 24. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 12. directs us, looke in Hiſtories and Chronicles, which tell us, <hi>this Realm of England has been accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for an Empire, governed by one ſupream head; unto whom a body po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique, compact of all ſorts and degrees of people, of the ſpiritualty, and Temporalty, are bounden to bear, next to God, a naturall obedience,</hi> ſo in that Statute. Now this firſt conſtitutionof government in this Land, (as this Anſwerer ha's phanſied it) can neither conſiſt with the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of this Parliamentary Declaration, as we ſhall ſee anon, nor can it have any footing in Hiſtories and chronicles to which that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration refers us.</p>
               <p>For thoſe chronicles, and <hi>Caeſar</hi> in his commentaries tells us, there were in this land then divers Princes independent, in which of them ſhall we look for this conſtitution? or ſhall we ſeek it among the Brittiſh kings, whom the <hi>Saxons</hi> drove into <hi>Wales?</hi> if we could find it there, it would not concern us, for we are not now upon the Brittiſh but Engliſh government, which followed the <hi>Saxons.</hi> If the Anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer will begin his conſtitution and firſt king at this period or revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion of the Monarchy, (for higher he cannot, &amp; lower at the conqueſt, I truſt he will not) why did not he tell us ſo, that he might have give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſcience ſome direction to find out his firſt conſtitution and firſt King? He knew well enough there was little help for him here.</p>
               <p>For we find this Engliſh Saxiſhgovernment at the beginning, bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching it ſelf into an Heptarchy, &amp; riſing in arms; it is likely thoſe Captains took upon them as kings by the conſent and acclamation of the ſouldiers, as when in the ſtate of <hi>Rome</hi> the pretorian guard, or ſome army abroad ſaluted an Emperor, and thruſt him upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. But what then will become of his firſt conſtitution by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivement of the people, when they made their firſt king? ſhould any of theſe ſeven Monarchs come in by ſuch a popular contrivement; (wch cannot be imagined) muſt our government needs be the ſame? Or can we think that <hi>Egbert</hi> who made himſelfe ſole Monarch was bound up by ſuch a conſtitution &amp; reſervation as he ſays was contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:155829:10"/>at their making of the firſt King? from that <hi>Egbert</hi> to King CHARLES, our Authentique Hiſtories and Chronicles (to which the Declaration of Parliament above mentioned refers us) do ſhew a glorious ſucceſſion of Monarchs, not one made by election, but <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rold,</hi> who yet ha's not obtained the ſtile of <hi>Rex Haroldus,</hi> and his title, if any, dyed with him.</p>
               <p>We ſee upon what uncertainties and improbabilities, conſcience is left for this firſt election and precontrivement; this Anſwerer ha's not directed it any wayes how it ſhould be aſſured of it, much leſſe of that reſervation of power, which he imagineth to be made by the people, at that firſt election of a King. He gives us no record to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes it, turnes us to no authentique Hiſtory or chronicle, ſhews us no conſtant practice or judgement of foregoing Ages; what he ha's from the mutuall oath of King and people, <hi>pag.</hi> 5. may be good upon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter agreement between them, as will appear; and his <hi>hanc poteſtatem a populo effluxam,</hi> out of <hi>Forteſcue,</hi> although it ſuppoſes derivation of power from the people; (the uſuall miſtaken principle of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which later times have given cauſe to examine and find un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound) yet doth it not imply, the people ha's reſerved any power, much leſſe ſuch a paramount power, as he imagines.</p>
               <p>Conſcience has this certain by the continuall practice of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, that there is ſuch a conſtitution as gives power of conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the two Houſes in making and declaring Law, when ever the beginning of it was; it cannot ſee that it began by a contrivement of the people at the ſuppoſed choice of the firſt King, but rather that it was ſubſequent to Monarchy, and procured by the people for their greater ſecurity, not precontrived by them.</p>
               <p>If objected. The conſtitution is fundamentall, therefore prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the firſt King; we anſwer it followes not, for it may be a funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall, yet not of Monarchy ſimply, but of government as now it ſtands, a fundamentall not of the Regall power, but the peoples ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. For Government may receive a change &amp; qualification by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of King and people, from more abſolute to mixt; &amp; ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution is a fundamentall, becauſe all after-lawes are built upon it, but not a fundamentall to the Regall power, for it gives no power to him as it doth to the two Houſes, but rather leſſens his power by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting it upon agreement, that he will not impoſe any laws upon his people without their conſent.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:155829:11"/>
               <p>But as for that reſerved power of declaring law without the king, and of commanding all, when they ſhall judge it expedient for the ſafety of the kingdom, upon the Kings refuſall, Conſcience has no aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance from this Anſwerer, that ſuch a power was reſerved (which is enough to leave it without excuſe, if it obey ſuch a power) but on the contrary, has ſtrong preſumptions and reaſons againſt.</p>
               <p>For firſt, it cannot ſee how ſuch a reſervation of power can conſiſt with the beginnings of government in this land, whether we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Norman</hi> or the <hi>Saxons</hi> entrance. Secondly, it cannot ſee how it can conſiſt with the known eſtabliſhed Government, for by ſuch a power the <hi>Supremacy</hi> would be plainly ſetled in the two Houſes, they may when they judge it neceſſary, uſe this reſerved power, which tranſcends all ordinary power in the King.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, ſhould the Kings of this Land be admitted upon ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement for this reſerved power, Conſcience cannot but think it an unreaſonable condition, and neither for the Kings nor peoples ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but a very ſeminary of jealouſies and ſedition; as if in Matrimony (for the King is alſo <hi>sponſus Regni,</hi> and wedded to the kingdom by a Ring at his Coronation) the parties ſhould agree, upon ſuch and ſuch neglect of duties, to part a ſunder; or children (for the king is alſo a Father of the kingdom, and the body politique owes to him <hi>naturall obedience,</hi> 24. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 12.) ſhould condition with their Parents upon ſuch or ſuch uſage to be acquitted of their duty and obedience; what our Saviour ſaid of their light &amp; unlawfull occaſions of Divorſe, <hi>non fuit ſic ob initio,</hi> it was not ſo from the beginning, when God at firſt joyned man and woman, may be ſaid of ſuch a reſerved power of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, it was not ſo from the beginning, when at firſt Rulers and Kings were Fathers, and ſo are ſtil called in the fift Commandement, not to be reſiſted or abdicated by their children, their ſubjects.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, this contrivement ſeems plainly to contradict it ſelfe, for it places this reſerved power in the Comites and Barons, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be before the firſt King, for <hi>Bracton</hi> tells us (as he is cited by Sir <hi>Edw. Coke</hi> in <hi>mag: Cart.) Reges aſſociant ſibi Comites &amp; Barones or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances eos in magno Honore,</hi> Earls and Barons are made by the King, and aſſumed for Councell, therefore inveſted with a long Robe, and for defence, therefore girt with a ſword; which ſhews the power they have, is not by a contrivement or reſervation at the ſuppoſed making of the firſt King, but from the King by grant and of grace;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:155829:11"/>much leſſe is it ſuch a tranſcendent and paramount power as this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer imagineth to be reſerved in them, and the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, at the firſt conſtitution of government in this Land.</p>
               <p>We have hitherto ſearched into the ground-worke of this frame of Government, as he had layd it in a ſuppoſed contrivement and reſervation of the people when they made their firſt King, and have found it to be groundleſſe, ſo that Conſcience cannot reſt upon it, to make reſiſtance in obedience to ſuch a reſerved power which this man tells Us is in the two Houſes, but gives no proofe for it at all, nor indeed can. So that this which has been ſayd againſt it, were enough to overthrow the <hi>Co-ordination, ſupply, Finall reſolution,</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Commands,</hi> that he has built upon this fiction; but we will particularly examine his diſcourſe upon them, which is but an opening and enlarging of his phancies upon the new Principles of theſe dayes, ſet off with plauſible ſhew of reaſon to deceive the unwary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV. <hi>Of the Co-ordination of the three Eſtates, and of the Supremacy of Power.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HIs Co-ordination he has thus expreſſed, <hi>This mixture or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination is in the very Supremacy of power it ſelfe, and the Monarchy or higheſt power it ſelfe is compounded of three Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate eſtates,</hi> pag. 3. <hi>There is but one Higheſt, but that one is a mixt one,</hi> pag. 4. It was granted, there is a Co-ordination to ſome pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, but not ſuch as he urges it for, in the matter of <hi>Supremacie</hi> and <hi>Supply;</hi> which that we may the better diſcern, we muſt accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our skill (and that ſhall be no farther, than the common uſe of reaſon, and the Grammaticall conſtruction of what the knowne Law does plainly declare, may lead every mans apprehenſion) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold wherein Supremacy of power doth conſiſt.</p>
               <p>There is a power of Enacting and of Executing or adminiſtration; accordingly the Supreame power ſhews it ſelfe in making new Laws, and abrogating old, in calling aſſemblies to that and other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, in Treaties with forreign Princes, ſending Embaſſies, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Officers of State, Judges of Courts, and other Miniſters of juſtice through the Kingdome.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:155829:12"/>
               <p>Now if the Co-ordination of the King and two Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, were ſuch as he doth expreſſe &amp; would ſeem to inferre by the <hi>ſupply</hi> they are to make upon the Kings refuſall, they ſhould be <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinati ad omnia,</hi> ſimply co-ordinate and equall in thoſe powers &amp; acts of Supremacy, wheras in plain ſpeech he cannot ſay they are co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate with His Majeſty, but only in conſenting to the making of Laws, <hi>pag.</hi> 4. in all the reſt the King is <hi>ſolely ſupream,</hi> and all power of adminiſtration derived from Him. So then their conſent is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to one act or exerciſe of ſupream power, but not to the deniall of His Supremacy, for He is ſtill by Law acknowledged the <hi>onely ſupream Governour,</hi> and the <hi>ſupream Head;</hi> which being urged in my former Treatiſe, this Anſwerer ſhould have ſhewn us how the King can be ſo, and yet this co-ordination of his, ſtand good to all purpoſes as he would have it.</p>
               <p>If he reſtrain that <hi>only ſupream Governour,</hi> and <hi>ſupream Head,</hi> to ſupremacy of power in Execution or Adminiſtration, it would be plain that none can uſe power in this government, but derivatively from His Majeſty, which were enough for the purpoſe, I urged Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy in the former Treatiſe, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſhew His Majeſty cannot be reſiſted; for reſiſtance is a taking of the ſword or power without him, and from him, and alſo a uſing of it againſt that power of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration which is ſetled in him, and therefore againſt him, as he is the <hi>only ſupream Governour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This would be enough to checke any mans conſcience that will dare to reſiſt, yet muſt not the ſupremacy be ſo reſtrained; for albeit, for the greater ſecurity of the people, Kings have bound themſelves from impoſing Laws upon them without their conſent, yet may wee alſo ſee the beams of His Supremacy ſhining in the <hi>power of enacting</hi> exerciſed with their conſent. For he has the power of calling them to that purpoſe, and the conſtitution that has given them power of conſenting, has left in him power of diſſolving them: Alſo, ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (as I have heard knowing men ſay) the Law enacted began thus, <hi>Rex ſtatuit,</hi> the King ordains, and before the Laws and Statutes in each Kings Raign, we find the title or introduction thus uſually ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, <hi>The King by the advice and aſſent of the Prelates, Earls, and Barons, and at the inſtance and requeſt of the Commonalty has ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp;c.</hi> And ſtill for the procuring of his aſſent, we ſee them Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning under the ſtile of Loyall Subjects, and while they ſit in that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:155829:12"/>there is ſtill that other relation of Head &amp; Body between them, and accordingly He was declared in Parliament to be <hi>Supream Head of the body politique, He being inſtituted and furniſhed by the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſufferance of Almighty God with plenary, whole entire power, preheminency, authority, praerogative, and Iuriſdiction, to render and yeeld Iuſtice and finall determination to all manner of Subiects within this Realm in all cauſes. Alſo that ſundry Laws and Ordinances had been made in former Parliaments, for ſure and entire conſerving the Prerogative and preheminency of this Crown.</hi> 24. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>From all this ſo plainly declared in Law, &amp; confeſſed, can we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with this man, that the two Houſes are Co-ordinate with his Majeſty in the very Supremacy? or that the higheſt &amp; Supream head is a mixt one? No! but that the Legiſlative power is Supreamly in the King, only this power is excited by <hi>the inſtance and requeſt</hi> of the Commons, repreſenting to him the grievances of his people abroad, and cannot be exerciſed or come to the act of Ordaining, but with conſent of them &amp; the Houſe of Lords. This may eaſily be conceived, if we conſider, that Kings at firſt ruled arbitrarily, and then the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative power was ſolely in them, afterward the people obtained ſuch limitations and qualifications of that power, as might make for their ſecurity; as for example, That they ſhould not have Laws im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on them without their conſent: this does not make them co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate with their King in the very Supremacy of power it ſelf, (as this man has conceived it) but ſtill leaves the power of Ordaining ſupreamly in him as in the fountain, though the efflux or exerciſe of that power be not ſolely in his will, but expects the conſent of the People.</p>
               <p>Now let us gather up his ſcattered proofes as we can find them. Such a co-ordination there muſt be, <hi>or els,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Monarchy is not mixt, pag.</hi> 3. &amp; 4. It doth not follow, if there be a mixture in it, therefore ſuch an one of equall ingredients; or if it be mixt <hi>ſecundùm quid</hi> in ſome reſpect, therefore ſimply, or as he would have it; though we ſay not the <hi>Monarchy</hi> is mixt, as he, yet we grant, the Government is mixt; not as he, by placing ſuch power in the co-ordinate parts; but mixt, that is, not abſolute or arbitrary in his Majeſty, yet not without Subordination on their part, and predominancy on his; And to ſay the Monarchy it ſelfe is compounded of three Eſtates as hee doth, is abſurd.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:155829:13"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the Treatiſer himſelfe calls it that excellent temper of the three Eſtates in Parliament, confeſſing them to be the fundamentalls of this Government; and if Fundamentalls, what ſubordination can there be in them, they admit not of higher &amp; lower; all foundations are alike, pag.</hi> 3. The Treatiſer acknowledged it a Fundamentall of Government, that provided this temper of the three eſtates in <hi>Parliament</hi> as the reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable means of our ſafety; therefore ſaith the Anſwerer, the three e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates are Fundamentalls, a good argument <hi>A genere adgenus;</hi> from the conſtitution that places this power in the two Houſes, to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that bear the power; for when we ſpeak of Fundamentalls, we ſpeak of Laws and conſtitutions, which may provide ſuch a <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> and yet do it with ſubordination, that it be not <hi>temperamentum ad pondus,</hi> but <hi>ad juſtitiam,</hi> not with Arithmeticall, but Geometricall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, not with exact equality of all, but with a predominancy of one; otherwiſe it would ſometime fall out, that this body of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth could not act or move any way, like as the naturall body could not, if all the elements were equally tempered in it.</p>
               <p>And to ſhew he is for an <hi>Arithmeticall proportion</hi> in this <hi>temper</hi> of the three Eſtates, he <hi>wonders we cannot ſee that the King is</hi> Univerſis minor, <hi>when as we may eaſily reckon that of three, one is leſſe than two. pag.</hi> 3. Very good, we ſhall have enough of ſuch arguments as theſe for the preſent we will make a note of this in the Margin, and ſhall have occaſion anon to call him to his reckoning upon it.</p>
               <p>Then he keeps a trifling to ſhew how the two Houſes are ſubjects <hi>diviſim,</hi> taken ſingly, and not ſubjects <hi>conjunctim,</hi> in the co-ordination <hi>pag.</hi> 4. In one word, their conſent is not ſubject to the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, yet they are ſubjects even collectively taken, for ſo they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent ſubjects that choſe them; they are ſubject to his command ſtill, to remove or riſe, when He Prorogues or diſſolves, and ſo they acknowledge themſelves Subjects in all their addreſſes to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, which they make as a body collective. He is the Head of them not taken ſeverally (for then He ſhould be Head of many bodies) but as joyntly making one body.</p>
               <p>And left he ſhould ſeeme to forget they are his Councell, which would take off from that fellowſhip in the ſupremacie, where he has placed them, he grants <hi>they are his Councell, but by the firſt conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not to be elected by him, but aſſigned to him, not aſſumed as</hi> Moſes <hi>his under Officers were upon</hi> Jethero's <hi>advice, pag.</hi> 4. How this of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:155829:13"/>
                  <hi>fes</hi> is pertinent (though often hinted in this book) I ſee not, for <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> did not aſſume them as Counſellors about making of Lawes, for neither he, nor they, nor both together could make any, but as Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers to eaſe him in the execution, or judging of the people accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thoſe Laws they received from God.</p>
               <p>As for the Commons in <hi>Parliament,</hi> they being a repreſentative body, could not be choſen but by them they repreſent, yet are they ſent upon his command and have a truſt upon them, not onely from thoſe that elected them, but alſo from the King that ſends for them to repreſent unto him the grievances of his people, and faithfully to conſult about the remedies; accordingly it is in relation to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty that they take the oaths of ſup remacy &amp; allegiance at their admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance into the Houſe, and although they have there the power not onely of conſulting, but of conſenting alſo, and denying for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the people whom they repreſent, yet who ſees not by all this, in what relation they ſtand to his Majeſty.</p>
               <p>For the Lords, they are aſſumed by the King, <hi>Bracton</hi> ſaid above <hi>Reges aſſociant ſibi Comites &amp; Barones,</hi> and we ſee the King calls by his Writ whom he pleaſes to that Houſe; nor doth it helpe that hee ſaith <hi>pag.</hi> 5. <hi>the Lords are</hi> Conſiliarii nati <hi>born Counſellors to the State,</hi> for though Nobility in ſome be <hi>Native,</hi> yet was it at firſt <hi>Dative</hi> as they ſpeake, by the grace of the King.</p>
               <p>We may adde here what he ſaith in the ſame place, <hi>The very ſtile of</hi> Comites <hi>and</hi> Peers <hi>implies a Co-ordinate ſociety with his</hi> Majeſty <hi>in the Government, they are in Parliament his</hi> Comites <hi>his</hi> Peers. Yet <hi>Bracton</hi> tells us, <hi>Rex non habet parem</hi> has no Peer, &amp; gives us another reaſon of the ſtile Comites (as he is cited by ſir <hi>Edw: Coke</hi> in <hi>Mag: Charta) quia ſunt in Comitatu,</hi> without relation to Parliament, becauſe they are either in the Traine of the King, or becauſe ſet in each county <hi>adregendum populum,</hi> and ſo aſſumed by the King to the like end that <hi>Moſes</hi> did his under Officers in ruling his people; So that other place of <hi>Bracton</hi> cited by this Anſwerer, <hi>pag.</hi> 4. <hi>Rex habet Superiorem—Curiam ſuam viz,</hi> Comites &amp; Barones, is not meant of the Court of Parliament, for ther's no mention of the Commons, but it follows in that place <hi>debent Regi fraenum imponere,</hi> it is likely hee ſpoke this in favour of the <hi>Militia</hi> raiſed againſt <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. (for then he wrote) and might call that aſſembly of Earls and Barons then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined againſt the King, <hi>curiam,</hi> the higher Court or Councell. But
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:155829:14"/>when he ſpeaks like a Lawyer, he ſaith plainly, <hi>Rex in Regne parem habere non debet, cùm par in parem non habeat poteflatem, multo forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us non habeat ſuperiorem,</hi> which how it agrees with that above, let this man, or the skilfull in the Law judge.</p>
               <p>Let us examine what reaſon will conclude by his argument from the ſtyle <hi>Comites;</hi> it would follow thence, That the Commons muſt be his <hi>Comites,</hi> and Peers too, for they are co-ordinate with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, as well as the other; and ſo this Anſwerer muſt ſet up three thrones, one for the King, another for the Lords, and a third for the Houſe of Commons; I ſhould not think any thing too honorable for the Houſes of Parliament, but only Majeſty. Now it is a rule in policy, <hi>Majestas cum ſupremà poteſtate conjuncta est,</hi> Majeſty goes along with the ſupream power, as in the popular State of Rome, it was uſually and properly ſaid, <hi>Maieſtas populi Romani,</hi> and ſo might it be ſaid here too, were this mans contrivement good, but I know the honorable Houſes of Parliament look not for it.</p>
               <p>But we return to the beginning of <hi>pag.</hi> 5. In reading the firſt line of it, I was in hope he would have bleſt us with ſome demonſtration of this conſtitution to be ſuch as he has borne us in hand it is, <hi>how doth it appear that the conſtitution of this government is ſuch? I anſwer, by the mutuall oath that the King &amp; people take to maintain the laws that have ſo conſtituted it;</hi> Altogether inconſequent; The King takes oath to maintain the Laws-therefore they are ſuch as this man fanſieth them; it ſhews indeed an obligation on his Majeſty to perform, it does not ſhew ſuch a co-ordination, ſupply, reſerved power, &amp;c. ſurely never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny King ſwore to it in that ſenſe, or had reaſon to underſtand it ſo; for he findes he is expreſly bound by that oath to preſerve the immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>immunities &amp; liberties of &amp;c. to protect &amp;c. which he ſhould not be well able to do if his power might be taken from him at the pleaſure of others.</p>
               <p>So when he anſwers to that which I have ſaid, the King is King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he take the oath; <hi>True, but he is King but upon the ſame truſt, which his Predeceſſors ſwore to, and the Oath, which the Law provides for the King to take, virtually bindes him before he takes it.</hi> He An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers nothing, unleſſe he could ſhew that the truſt which this Oath implies to be in the King, was ſuch a truſt upon which the people in their firſt contrivement (as he phanſieth) conditionally admitted the firſt King, and that the Law which provided this oath, was that firſt conſtitution or contrivement, which would be abſurd, for the oath
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:155829:14"/>ſpeaks the Language of later times, and would not fit the Mouth of the firſt King in the firſt Coalition of Government, for it binds Him to preſerve the <hi>immunities of Holy Church,</hi> which if it ſhould be of an after addition to the Oath, yet ſurely <hi>Leges</hi> and <hi>Conſuetudines Angliae</hi> were in it from the beginning; now thoſe are cuſtomes of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and cuſtomes muſt have ſome continuance of time paſt to make them ſo, therefore the firſt King in the firſt Coalition of Government ſwore not this Oath; what he ſhews indeed by this argument we admit, that the King is bound to take the Oath, is bound to perform the duty of it, but this is nothing to prove ſuch a firſt Conſtitution as he dreams of.</p>
               <p>He brings a proof out of <hi>Forteſcue, Hanc poteſtatem a populo ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluxam habet, &amp;c. Principatu nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> nedum Regali, ſed &amp; politico ſuo populo dominatur, now the word</hi> Politico <hi>implies the</hi> Principat <hi>of many, eſpecially when oppoſed to</hi> Regali, <hi>pa.</hi> 5. This place tells us what manner of power the King ha's, does not tell us the two Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have ſuch power as this man pretends; We examined that <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluxam a populo</hi> above, whether the power of the King was derived from the people by agreement in the firſt coalition of Government. Here we grant the King ha's a limited power, but not ſo limited as this Anſwerer would have it, which he might have read in the words cited: for he ſees there the King ha's His <hi>Regalis poteſtas,</hi> but Rules not only by that <hi>(i.e.)</hi> by a power meere <hi>Regiaſed &amp; politico princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patu,</hi> by a politicall power alſo, in as much as in the making of Laws the advice and conſent of many is required, and his power regulated by ſuch Law.</p>
               <p>But this <hi>Principate of many,</hi> as it is ill rendered out of the Latine, ſo is it ill meant, to the excluding of His <hi>Regalis poteſtas,</hi> &amp; ſo to make this government Democraticall, or Ariſtocraticall, rather then Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall; Now there cannot be ſuch a blend or mixture of the Forms of government, but that one muſt be predominant, and Supream, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe elſe the body Politique could not move or act any thing, as it was ſaid above, when we ſpoke of the <hi>Temper</hi> of the three Eſtates.</p>
               <p>This Anſwerer, to free this body Politique, (when the three E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates lock and binde one the other by their Negative voyce, as upon the Kings refuſall) and to make it active without him to all ends and purpoſes, places the <hi>Finall reſolution</hi> in the two Houſes, to which all muſt obey, and ſo indeed places the <hi>Supremacie</hi> there, but why then
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:155829:15"/>ſhould this be a Monarchy rather then a popular government, were it not for Supremacy in the King? or why ſhould that firſt Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which he ſaith placed this finall reſolution in the two Houſes, leave ſuch a power in the King, to diſſolve them? which power, ſay we, looſes the Body Politique, when through the aforeſaid binding it cannot move a new way by a new Law, and gives it motion by the former Laws, which will appear anon to be with leſſe inconvenience, then if in ſuch a caſe it ſhould be moved by ſuch a finall reſolution.</p>
               <p>Having thus far ſpoken of his <hi>Coordination,</hi> before he comes to the <hi>Supply,</hi> the two Houſes are thereupon to make, he ſpends two Pages, the 6th and 7th in repeating his Notes he ha's taken at Court-Sermons, where he ſaith, <hi>the Divinity of Monarchy, and the abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of this in the Kings ſole perſon, ha's been uſually cryed up,</hi> as if there were no <hi>medium</hi> between ſuch an abſolute Monarchy, and ſuch a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinative one as he ha's phanſied; Let them bear their burden that ſpeak not their conſcience at Court, I would they would now do it ſincerely at <hi>S. Margarets Weſtminſter,</hi> for I could tell him what ſtuffe is preached there too, what omnipotency is aſcribed to ſome in the world, I would alſo this man would have uſed a conſcience in repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and interpreting my words, for he often makes me ſpeak contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions through his own inadvertency, and in this place he abſolves me in the beginning of his relation, and charges me thus at the end;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This and much more was preached, and all upon this errour, that the Dr. reſolves on, that the ſole Supremacie of power was in the Kings Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and that His Judgment was the ſole Supream rule of Power.</hi> He ſhould have done well to have cited the place where I reſolve ſo, for they are not my words, nor do they render my ſenſe any where ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed to that purpoſe. For when I ſay (as I did, and proved in my other Treatiſe) that the King is Supream, or the higher power, I do not mean he is ſole and abſolute in making or impoſing Laws (the contrary was often expreſſely acknowledged by me) but that He is ſtill, notwithſtanding the conſent of the two Houſes, required to that act or exerciſe of ſupream Power, the <hi>only ſupream Governour,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the oath of ſupremacie, which was enough for the purpoſe I urged it; <hi>viz.</hi> not for his abſoluteneſs, but againſt our reſiſting of him. It is well known the conſent of the Senate and people of <hi>Roms</hi> was required to the Laws their Emperour would have enacted, and yet He was Supream, ſo acknowledged, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. And it is well
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:155829:15"/>known, The King was in Parliament acknowledged the Supream Head of the Body Politique.</p>
               <p>And now what can conſcience conclude hence? Firſt, that the two Houſes of Parliament are in ſome ſort coordinate with the King, by reaſon of that conſent neceſſarily required in the making and declaring Law, and that's enough for our ſecurity againſt an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute or arbitrary government. Alſo that the King, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch their coordination and conſent, is, and has been ſo declared in Parliament, the Supream Head of the Body, Eccleſiaſticall and Civil, alſo the onely Supream Governour, and that is enough to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conſcience from reſiſtance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V. <hi>Of the Supply which is phanſied upon the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Coordination.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw leſt it ſhould appear unreaſonable, as needs it muſt, that the two Houſes of Parliament ſhould have power to make Laws and Ordinances without the King, which He acknowledges He can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do without them, and to ſeize the <hi>Militia</hi> or power of Arms, with which His Majeſty is entruſted, as this Anſwerer confeſſeth; the device to make this good, is by a rule miſapplyed, <hi>Coordinata invicem ſupplent,</hi> which Rule he gave us, <hi>Pag.</hi> 3. and now comes to miſapply it, <hi>Pag.</hi> 8. <hi>If the King fail in His truſt, His coordinates in the mixture of this Supream power, muſt according to their truſts ſupply.</hi> But before we ſhew how weakly this coordination inferres the ſupply, let us firſt ſee wherein this ſupply ſtands, and when the time is for them to make uſe of it; this Supply, he tells us, is in applying the means of ſafety to its end, that is in ſetling the <hi>Militia</hi> as may be moſt ſafe for the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and the time when it is neceſſary to apply them, is in imminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of Danger; to this purpoſe, <hi>Pag.</hi> 8, 9, 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The King acknowledges imminencie of Danger in His Writ of Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> Conſideratis periculis imminentibus, <hi>Pag.</hi> 9. There may be imminent dangers ſufficient to move his Majeſty to call a Parliament, and require their advice, though not ſufficient to cauſe them to uſe this Supply, by taking the <hi>Militia</hi> into their hands. <hi>Where by the way</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we may take notice, that His</hi> Majeſty <hi>is by Law to call a</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:155829:16"/>
                  <hi>when there ſhall be any imminent danger, ib:</hi> and by the way we may take notice, that the King is the ſole Judge of thoſe imminent dangers, when he calls a Parliament, and alſo (which is not the way to make him haſty in calling a Parliament) that according to this mans contrivement, ſo oft as his Majeſty calls a Parliament, they may uſe this ſupply, and ſeize the <hi>Militia,</hi> becauſe of thoſe imminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in the Writ of Summons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This imminency of danger ha's a competent Judge, the two Houſes, (wherein the Law makes the Reaſon of the Kingdom to reſide) who have by Vote concluded it. Pag.</hi> 9. ſo it was by Vote concluded, that his Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſty, upon the raiſing of a Guard at <hi>Yorke,</hi> for the ſafety of his perſon, intended to make Warre upon the Parliament, are they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Judges of his intentions too? indeed thoſe horrible imminent dangers that were pretended, have been for the moſt part as inviſible as Intentions are.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the King refuſed to paſſe the Bill for the Militia, according to the advice of the two Houſes, which is (ſaith the Law) the ſame ever living Reaſon of the State that firſt adviſed the Government, and muſt ſtill ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe the way of applying it,</hi> pag. 9. His Majeſty did not barely refuſe, but gave his Reaſons for it, and if they had their dangers and fears moving them to gain the <hi>Militia,</hi> ſo had he his to withhold it, as he had amply teſtified to the world. But here's a Reaſon of State, to which his <hi>Majeſties</hi> Reaſon muſt give way; and that ſurely is Law. Certainly the <hi>Militia</hi> is to be applyed by the Reaſon of State, but we muſt not make the King no part of the State as he does, and as he ſaith the Law does, but we would fain ſee that Law; we are ſure it is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8.21. <hi>Your Royall Majeſty, and Your Lords and Commons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the whole Realm.</hi> This reſtraining of the whole Reaſon of State to the two Houſes, is but the ſame device with that which made the firſt conſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this government, to be the contrivement of the people when they made the firſt King, and was above confuted; So this neceſſity that is here laid upon the King, alwaies to follow the advice of the two Houſes, is but a ſtrain of that device which places a finall and Arbitrary reſolution in them, and ſhall be handled anon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His Majeſty will apply the Militia, but by the advice of them againſt whom it is to be ſecured, whom the Parliament has Voted enemies to the State, againſt whom eſpecially it was called,</hi> pag. 10. This is ſhooting at Rovers; if he ſhould tell who thoſe voted ones were, and who
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:155829:16"/>thoſe enemies againſt whom this Parliament was called, I do not think he would find any of them about his Majeſty, when he refuſed to paſſe the Bill for the Militia; but he tells us a little after, <hi>pag.</hi> 10. <hi>The King gathers theſe voted enemies into an Army againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that had voted them ſuch;</hi> and a little after, <hi>What ſhall the two other States do, but uſe that power of Arms, which the government in ſuch caſe of the Kings refuſall has entruſted them with, to its own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation</hi> (that's alwayes ſuppoſed, never proved) <hi>eſpecially when 'tis but for the apprehending of ſuch enemies to it, as (beſide that voted de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquencie) are ſufficiently convinced by their own flight;</hi> Now we know who thoſe voted delinquents are, againſt whom the Militia was by bill to be ſecured; ſome five or ſix that fled beyond ſea. But theſe though beyond ſea, are gathered together into an Army here by the King: to paſſe by this, let us ſee what is more materiall; The Kings Army is raiſed againſt the Parliament, Their army againſt thoſe delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents to bring them to juſtice; But can any man in conſcience bee perſwaded, that was the Kings deſign? was that a time to provoke them that were ſo powerfull with the people? or was the King in a condition then fit to enterprize againſt them that were ſo furniſhed with all the Arms of the Kingdom, he not knowing where to have ſufficient for a ſmall guard? Nay, let his offers, ſent them from <hi>Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingham</hi> many moneths after ſpeak to Poſterity, by whoſe refuſall it was, that we are not now in ſafety; when as it pleaſed God within a few weeks after to raiſe him ſuch an aſſiſtance, that he was able to appear againſt thoſe forces that pretended they were ſent from the Parliament.</p>
               <p>And now that it comes to blows, why ſhould it be interpreted, that the King intends to overthrow the Parliament, becauſe he fights againſt thoſe pretended Parliamentary forces, more than that the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament intends to overthrow the Kingly power, becauſe their force fight againſt thoſe that aſſiſt him? certainly, as they deſire the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of his Kingly power, ſo does he the continuance of free Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments; knowing he cannot ſuffer by ſuch.</p>
               <p>And for the apprehenſion of thoſe Delinquents which fled, being here pretended as the cauſe of their ſeizing the Militia, and taking Arms, Can we think them ſo conſiderable? or that they would have been with-held, when as thoſe that were greater and neerer to His Majeſty, had been delivered up to the juſtice of the Parliament? cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:155829:17"/>this would not have made the Breach, if firſt a great Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent on that ſide had not been denied to be delivered up to tryall, if the <hi>Militia</hi> had not been ſeized, and ſome further deſign thereby threatned according to His Majeſties apprehenſion.</p>
               <p>Having done with theſe pretences, we come to his argument for this ſupply, <hi>Co-ordinata invicem ſupplent,</hi> if the King refuſe, His Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinates the two Houſes muſt ſupply.</p>
               <p>We anſwer, Co-ordinates doe ſupply each others failings, not alwayes and to all purpoſes, but then and ſo far forth as is appointed by that conſtitution that makes them ſo, there are two parts of this Anſwer.</p>
               <p>Firſt, they do then ſupply when it is expreſſed ſo in the conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that has co-ordinated them, and not els; he gave us as an inſtance of this co-ordination, the example of a father and ſon, entruſted with lands to certain uſes, <hi>pag.</hi> 5. Now put caſe, the father refuſes to expend any thing upon ſuch uſes as his ſon preſents to him, becauſe he apprehends them not ſuch as were intended; may then his ſonne <hi>ſupply</hi> and do it himſelfe, unleſſe it be ſo expreſſed in the deed of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feoffment? which is improbable it ſhould, for then the whole power would be placed in the ſon. So if this power of <hi>ſupplying</hi> may bee challenged by the two co-ordinate parts, upon the refuſall of the third, it muſt be as expreſſe in the conſtitution of the Kingdome, as the co-ordination and power of the three is: We ſee ſuch reſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons expreſſe in meerly conventionall Kingdoms, where the Prince is choſen and admitted on ſuch conditions.</p>
               <p>He tells us indeed it is fundamentall and of the firſt conſtitution, but proves it not, we ſee it not expreſſed in the Enfeoffment, as I may ſay, wherein we find three Eſtates entruſted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If any would know what are thoſe fundamentall Laws, ſo much jeered at in this and other Pamphlets; It is that originall frame of this Co-or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate Government contrived by the people in its firſt conſtitution, and ſince in every ſeverall Raign confirmed by mutuall oaths between King and people; and in the Parliament ſummons of Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>this Law is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Lex ſtabilitata &amp; notiſſima,</hi> pag. 8. If any man would know what jeering is, he may read the premonition before this fuller Anſwer, and the firſt leafe of the anſwer; but if he would know what theſe Fundamentals be indeed, he muſt not expect to know them truly by this Anſwerer, that layes the foundations of this Government, in the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:155829:17"/>airy conceptions of his own phancie, ſuch are, a contrivement of the people when they made the firſt King, A reſervation of power to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply upon the Kings refuſall, and the like; ſuch fundamentals as theſe were reaſoned againſt (which is not jeering) from the analogie and proportion that muſt be betweene the foundation and the building, the fundamental conſtitutions and the Written Laws; in my former Treatiſe.</p>
               <p>It is a known and written Law that declares the King Supreame head of the body Politike, alſo that declares him the only ſupreame Governour in this Realme, can the fundamentals, as this man layes them beare this ſuperſtructure, or rather conſiſt with this fundamentall thus openly declared and laid in Law? So it is a knowne Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Conſtitution, that the making of Laws is in three Eſtates, ſecured againſt each other by a power of denying, and that it is in the Kings power to diſſolve the Court; can this conſiſt with the fundamentalls of this mans laying? Alſo the contrivement of the people at the ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed election of their firſt King, was proved above altogether uncertain, improbable, and unreaſonable.</p>
               <p>What is ſworn to by the Mutuall oathes of King and People, wee granted above to binde them, but not to prove ſuch a Conſtitution; What that <hi>Lex notiſſima</hi> is, he ſhould have done well to have expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it, for we know he is apt to deceive us with generals, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, where ever he meets <hi>with Fundamental Law</hi> or <hi>conſtitution of Government,</hi> it is his Law and conſtitution as he hath framed it.</p>
               <p>The Coordination of the three Eſtates, we grant is fundamental &amp; <hi>Lex notiſſima,</hi> but this power of Supply would not be ſo ſtrange and new a Doctrine now, if it had been then <hi>Lex Notiſſima.</hi> Nay the Rule of Coordination is againſt it, which, when three are expreſly entruſted, gives not power to two, unleſſe it be ſo expreſſely provided in the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall conſtitution; and this coordination is ſuch that it gives us an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt it too, that the originall conſtitution of this Government, meant there ſhould not be a ſupply by two Eſtates, becauſe it hath ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the proviſion of the Kingdome in three, ſecured againſt each other by a Negative voice, and hath left the power of diſſolving in the King, which would make ſuch a power of Supply vain.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we Anſwer to the Rule, Coordinates ſupply only in that whereunto they are coordinate. Now the two Houſes are Coordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate with His Majeſty only <hi>ad Conſentiendum</hi> for the making new
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:155829:18"/>proviſions of ſafety by new Lawes, we doe not finde them Coordinate with him in command of the <hi>Militia,</hi> or appointing officers for it, or deſigning Miniſters of Juſtice through the Kingdome, therefore the <hi>Supply</hi> cannot hold in theſe; for if one part of the body can ſupply the defect of another, yet cannot they ſupply the office of the head.</p>
               <p>But the Anſwerer may reply, though the King alone is ordinarily entruſted with the <hi>Militia,</hi> the deſigning of officers, &amp;c. yet may theſe fall under their ordinance of <hi>Supply,</hi> as the <hi>ſubſtratamateria,</hi> the matter about which that ordinance may be converſant, as about the meanes of preventing imminent dangers. We Anſwer, that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance cannot extend it ſelfe farther then Law will give it leave, it may not over-rule knowne Laws; if it be Law and the Conſtitution of the Kingdome, that when the preventing of imminent dangers require new proviſions, thoſe proviſions or new Laws be made by three E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates entruſted, and ſtrengthened with power of denying, then it's plain, ſuch ſupply or proviſion cannot be made by an ordinance; and better run the hazard of inconvenience by the refuſall of one then to leave the whole power in the other two. Otherwiſe an Ordinance ſhall prevail to diveſt the King of all the power ſetled in Him by Law, what then will become of the property of the Subject? No marvaile this proceeds on to an arbitrary power, as we ſhall have this Anſwerer confeſſing anon.</p>
               <p>But he told us above, <hi>Pag.</hi> 3. that the three Eſtates are fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls. If therefore the King be one of the Fundamentals, according to his phraſe, then according to his argument, <hi>Pag.</hi> 8. the King is not to be ſtirred out of his Place, ſo long as the government ſtands, for there he tels us foundations are not to be ſtirred ſo long as the building ſtands; ſhall He then be like a looſe ſtone in the Foundation, to be taken out and laid aſide, when they ſhall judge He is not fit to beare his burden, the Truſt the Law hath put upon Him? howſoever ſome ſtone in the ſide wall may be ſo uſed, the chiefe corner ſtone cannot.</p>
               <p>If he reply as he doth, <hi>Pag. 9. This Vote or Ordinance of the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes takes not away the Kings negative voice in making Laws, 'tis not an Act of Parliament, 'tis but an occaſional ſupply of this Coordination, leaſt the whole ſhould ruine.</hi> Yet will you tell us preſently, The Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in caſe of the other parts abſence and refuſall, are virtually the whole, and have the Parliamentary power, if ſo, why then can they not make an act of Parliament as well as ſuch an Ordinance? but call
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:155829:18"/>it what you will, Act or Ordinance, whereby either King or Subject are deſpoiled of what is theirs by Law, it matters not greatly, ſeeing that Ordinance is of force ſo long as they pleaſe to judge neceſſary, who, according to this Anſwerer, have the finall and arbitrary reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; what will it ſatisfie the King to tell him this is but an <hi>occaſionall ſupply,</hi> if He ſee it is in their powers to take or make the occaſion? or to let Him know, that ordinarily he hath the power and is entruſted with it, but upon extraordinary times and dangers it is theirs, He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing their direction, if He knows it is in their power to make that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction when they pleaſe, and to apply it? Or when will ſome think themſelves ſafe enough to part with this power again? ſeeing greater feares are now likely to prevaile with them for the holding it, then did at firſt for the ſeizing it.</p>
               <p>But he ſuppoſes, <hi>Pag.</hi> 11. That <hi>the two Houſes upon the abſence and refuſall of the other part, are virtually the whole,</hi> and then askes, <hi>whether there be not a Parliament actually in England? if ſo, why have they not then a Parliamentary power?</hi> This tearm <hi>virtually</hi> doth often ſtand him inſtead, for under that he can enlarge the power of the Houſes to the extent of his fancie; but let us know in this great point, wherein <hi>Conſcience</hi> expects cleare ground to reſt on, whether the Law hath <hi>actually</hi> inveſted the Houſes with ſuch power.</p>
               <p>A Parliament we grant, and a Parliamentary power in it, and if any deny the two Houſes to bee the Parliament, it is becauſe in proper ſpeech and in truth the name and power of Parliament which belongs to three Eſtates, ſhould not be reſtrained to two. The two Houſes have ſtil the power belonging to them, and what ever is now by them preſented to the King, and by Him paſſed, it is done with full power of Parliament, what is done without his conſent is not: it is no more now, then if the King were preſent in the Houſe, and ſhould deny to paſſe a Bill; for preſence or abſence is nothing, His power of denying is all.</p>
               <p>For put the caſe the King and the Lords ſhould agree, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſtand out, there were a Parliament ſtill, but where is the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary power? I doubt hee will not ſay the King and Lords have then the full power of Parliament; but where then is this <hi>Supply?</hi> will he ſay in the Houſe of Commons? we muſt call him now to his reckoning, <hi>Pag.</hi> 3. where he tels us; <hi>Of three Eſtates one is leſſe then two,</hi> and alſo to his rule he gives us, <hi>Pag.</hi> 4. <hi>Coordinates ſupply each
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:155829:19"/>others failings,</hi> and Pag. 11. <hi>The refuſall of one part exempts not the other from their duty;</hi> So that if this man hold to his own conceit, hee muſt grant the King and Lords may <hi>Supply,</hi> if the Commons refuſe. But if in that caſe he will not ſtand to his own reckoning and his owne Rule, then muſt he quit his vain conceit of <hi>Supply</hi> by the two Houſes, in caſe the King refuſe.</p>
               <p>After this he ſeekes a reaſon of this <hi>Supply</hi> in the neceſſity of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding for the ſafety of the whole, which elſe would be fruſtrated of its ſafety. <hi>However this Reſolver ſleight the Obſervators Argument, drawn from the higheſt end of Government, the peoples ſafety, he cannot deny, but the Rule holds always, finis quò ultimatior eò in fluxu poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier; to that end all other ſubordinate ſtand but in the office of meanes, and this is evinced by the text, the higher power is a Miniſter for thy good, Pag.</hi> 11. The Obſervators argument deſerved to bee ſleighted by the Reſolver as inconſequent, but it was confuted at large, by ſhewing ſuch meanes make not for that end (the ſafety of the State) but are remedies worſe then the diſeaſe; Nor hath this full Anſwerer ſtrengthned the conſequence one whit; We grant the ſafety of the Common-wealth is the higheſt end, and unto that end all other are as meanes, and that the higher power ought to <hi>miniſter</hi> unto that end. But doth it follow, therefore ſuch a <hi>Supply</hi> by diveſting the Kingof His power, by turning the higheſt <hi>Miniſter</hi> out of His office, is the means to that end.</p>
               <p>The joynt agreement of the three Eſtates is the meanes for new proviſion for that end; but in caſe they agree not about that proviſion, which may happen by the refuſall of the Lords, or the Commons, or the King; then that the two agreeing parts, what ere they be, ſhould ſupply the defect of the third, had beene far more reaſonable, then that the ſupply ſhould be made onely by the two Houſes, <hi>(i.e.)</hi> by the body only without the Head; For this is not only to the notorious prejudice of the Supream Head with whom the Kingdome is immediately and chiefly entruſted, but alſo it is alame proviſion, and argues the firſt Contrivement (as this man fancies it) very inconſiderate, in not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding, in caſe the King and Lords, or the King and Commons ſhould joyne.</p>
               <p>Now as the not providing in ſuch Caſes, and the power of diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving (which reſides in the King) doe plainly ſhew that ſuch a <hi>Supply</hi> is not the Contrivement of the firſt Conſtitution, but a phanſie of late
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:155829:19"/>popular Stateſmen, from whom this Anſwerer hath borrowed it; ſo in very deed this way of <hi>Supply</hi> would not be a meanes of ſafety, but of more inconveniency, as at this day experience teacheth us, and at large was ſhewed in the former Treatiſe.</p>
               <p>Therefore if the three Eſtates cannot joyntly agree, which is the reaſonable meanes of making new proviſion for ſafety. There is in the King by the ſame Conſtitution power to diſſolve, and protect His Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in their Religion, and properties, and Liberties, according to the former Lawes eſtabliſhed; And although His Majeſty hath bound Himſelf from diſſolving them without their conſent, for this time, (of which this Anſwerer does vainly endeavour to make advantage in many places) yet have not they thereby any more power then what they ſhould have had without that Grant, and ſo they have acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged themſelves.</p>
               <p>To conclude, <hi>Conſcience</hi> cannot be truly perſwaded this <hi>power of Supply,</hi> is in the two Houſes by the Conſtitution of this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But muſt needs ſee it is inconſiſtent with it, and with that power the known eſtabliſhed Law declares to be in the King, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Conſcience</hi> cannot yeeld obedience to that power in making reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance againſt the King.</p>
               <p>The Anſwerer immediately after the text above cited by him, <hi>The higher power is a miniſter for thy good,</hi> hath theſe words, Pag. 12. <hi>Yes a fine way you'l ſay of preſerving the King by fighting againſt Him.</hi> So ſtarting from the ſafety of the people (which was there ſpoken of as the higheſt end) to the Conſideration of the Kings ſafety, as if he had been ſtruck on a ſuddain, with the terrour of that Battle that was made againſt the King, or elſe becauſe Truth it ſelfe upon the mention of the <hi>higher Power</hi> wrung from him a thought and acknowledgment of His Majeſty in it. Well, let us ſee how he will have the King pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by their fighting againſt Him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>No ſuch matter</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the King hath a double Capacity,</hi> Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique <hi>and</hi> Naturall, <hi>in fighting for the preſervation of the Kingdom, they fight for Him in His</hi> Politique <hi>Capacity as King—in that He cannot be divided from His Kingdom or Parliament—They fight to diſingage His Perſon from that unſafe and unworthy imployment thoſe Enemies to Him and His Kingdome put it to — however he be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by them it is His cauſe that hath ingaged them; it is their own guilt and danger,</hi> Pag. 12.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:155829:20"/>
               <p>So we are uſually anſwered, when we tell them of their Hands ſo many times lifted up in Battle againſt the Lords Annointed, and of <hi>Davids</hi> reſolution upon it, <hi>who can lift up — and be guiltleſſe?</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26. They reply it is but againſt the Cavaleir's and that unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Company that is about Him, and have thus engaged Him; and in ſo doing they fight for the Kingdome, and for the King too, in His <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique</hi> Capacity. A ſhift that will no more ſave them from the Guilt, then it will doe Him from their violence. If He had been taken away in His <hi>naturall</hi> Capacity at <hi>Keinton</hi> Battle, had there been any ſuch thing as a King at <hi>Weſtminſter?</hi> had it not divided Him in His <hi>Politique</hi> Capacity from the Parliament there? take away the Body, and the ſhadow too, deſtroy Him in His Perſon or <hi>Naturall</hi> Capacity, and you deſtroy Him in His <hi>Politique,</hi> and the Parliament too, which ceaſes upon it.</p>
               <p>Nor is that diſtinction of His double Capacity altogether vain, but only in this point of Armes and reſiſtance by force; As juſt ſentences of Iudges, againſt His Perſonall Commands, are for Him in His Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique Capacity; ſo all denyalls of active obedience to unjuſt perſonall commands; why! heres all this while no power taken from Him, or uſurped againſt Him, No danger to His <hi>Perſon,</hi> to His <hi>Naturall</hi> Capacity; but in reſiſtance by force of Armes, eſpecially in a Battle againſt Him, (which not onely takes the ſword out of His Hand and uſurpes the power, but may alſo take Him away in His Naturall Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity) the diſtinction is moſt vaine.</p>
               <p>For the Enemies that are ſaid here to enthrall His Perſon and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade Him, I ſuppoſe he meanes thoſe Voted ones of which we ſpake above; if any of them be entertained lately; for one of them there's above a thouſand of His good Subjects, whoſe Nobleneſſe and honeſty hath ſtill engaged them honourably, though to the weaker ſide; before in behalfe of the Subject groaning under former grievances, now in ſervice to His Majeſty oppoſed by popular fury, Subjects that out of Conſcience of their allegiance cleave unto him, as they did to <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ul, whoſe hearts the Lord had touched</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. On the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it is well known how the guilt and danger of ſome deſperate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have engaged the poor people and oppoſed them as a buckler be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt themſelves and the ſtroke of Iuſtice. And how ever this man thinks His Majeſty is carried away; We are ſure he hath ſpoken ſo much reaſon in His Expreſſes and Declarations, that it plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:155829:20"/>He is not perſwaded by Enemies to Himſelfe or the Kingdom, but hath been forced to this juſt and neceſſary defence of Himſelfe; and hath cauſe to think, He may be ſafer every way by his own Army, then by that which pretends to preſerve him in his <hi>Politique,</hi> but gave him Battle to the moſt imminent danger of His Perſon and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall</hi> Capacity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI. <hi>Of the finall Reſolution of this States Iudgement, and power of declaring Law.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Anſwerer goes on to his ſecond Propoſition, placing the finall Reſolution of this States Iudgement in the two Houſes, unto which all muſt yeeld obedience. <hi>Pag.</hi> 13. How proves he this? <hi>In this mixture of Supream power and truſt of Government the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes make a part, what's their ſhare? to conſult? nay, but to conſent with the King in making Lawes.</hi> Be it ſo, that ſhare we grant them; but if you will place the finall reſolution in them, you muſt not ſpeak of a ſhare, but challenge the whole, The King is but a <hi>Cypher.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then he tells us againe of the firſt Conſtitution of Government, when the people made the firſt King, but nothing at all to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of ſuch a Conſtitution, or clearing of ſuch a finall reſolution ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the two Houſes; And as if there were no way to overthrow the firſt Conſtitution of this Government, as he hath contrived it, but onely by Conqueſt, he leapes from this <hi>Finall reſolution,</hi> of which he ſhould give us ſome proof, to ſpeake of the Title by Conqueſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conqueſt I confeſſe may give ſuch a Right as Plunderers uſe to take in houſes they can maſter, Pag.</hi> 13. I had not mentioned <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> but to take away the exception made to the Apoſtles prohibition of Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from the abſoluteneſſe of the Roman Emperors, and to ſhew they made themſelves ſo abſolute by force of Armes; but ſeeing this Anſwerer will make a buſineſſe of it, he muſt take notice that <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt</hi> is one of the meanes by which God tranſlates Kingdomes; and that <hi>David</hi> being provoked by the King of <hi>Ammon,</hi> brought that people under, and had a right over them by <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. that the <hi>Edomites</hi> were ſo brought under the Dominion of <hi>Iudah,</hi> from which they revolted, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 21.8. The Romans alſo had a right
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:155829:21"/>over <hi>Iudou,</hi> by Conqueſt, our Saviour acknowledges it in <hi>Caeſar, give to Caeſar, &amp;c.</hi> and in his ſubſtitute <hi>Pilate,</hi> that he had power given him from above. If this Anſwerer ſhould looke through all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, he would ſcarce find a Kingdom that deſcends by inheritance, but it had a beginning in Armes, and yet I thinke he will not ſay the Titles of theſe Kings are no better then of Plunderers; for though it may be unjuſt at firſt in him that invades and Conquers, yet in the ſucceſſion, which is from him, that providence which tranſlates King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, manifeſts it ſelfe and the will of God; and there are <hi>momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta temporum,</hi> for the juſtneſſe of ſuch Titles, though we cannot fixe them.</p>
               <p>If he ſay they begin to be juſt, when the conſent of the people is yeelded; were it ſo; and not ſo till then; yet is that in all likelyhood an overawed conſent (as he grants the conſent of the people of <hi>Rome</hi> was to their Emperors, <hi>Pag.</hi> 21.) and little to the advantage of the people; however let their conſent be free, what the people gaine up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that conſent, is by an after agreement, and grant of the Prince, not by precontrivement at their making of the firſt King; as he dreames it to be in this Kingdom; We need not looke farre for inſtance, we ſee <hi>Mag: Char:</hi> begins each clauſe with a <hi>Conceſſimus</hi> to the antient liberties of the Subject.</p>
               <p>By which we ſee how vainly he breakes into paſſion in the words following, <hi>How undoctor all, how unchriſtian, inhumane Barbariſme it is, to talke of a right by Conqueſt in a Civill, a Chriſtian State?</hi> Pag. 13. and a little after, <hi>how many wayes doth this Reſolver abuſe His Majeſty herein?</hi> I had indeed abuſed Him, had I talked of His Right as fondly as this man hath done; I ſaid, he King claimes from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror, and that of uncertain plea of ſuppoſed firſt Election could not give Subjects ſuch power againſt him, as is now pretended to. I ſhewed the Emperors of <hi>Rome</hi> made themſelves ſuch by force of Armes, ſo did the <hi>Saxons</hi> here, ſo did the <hi>Normans</hi> after them maſter this people; this Anſwerer ſpeakes nothing to theſe beginnings of this Government in the <hi>Saxon</hi> and <hi>Norman</hi> Lines, but ſtill tells us of a firſt Election, and 'tis un-Chriſtian to talke of Conqueſt, that is, to ſpeake the truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>David,</hi> as it was ſaid above, being provoked by the King of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> tooke away his Crown, made that people to ſerve as ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es. The Conqueror had a Title from the <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings, being denyed,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:155829:21"/>he purſu's it, and in the purſuit of it by Armes ſubdues this Land; can we thinke he was bound to ſuch a firſt Conſtitution, as this man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives? We ſee it otherwiſe; and what has been conſented to by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Kings.</p>
               <p>My Collection then was, ſhall the pretended right of the people by ſuch an Election be good againſt a King that claimes not by it, but receives the Crown by ſucceſſion, deſcending through ſeverall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, and yet the right of the <hi>Roman</hi> people not good againſt their Tyrannicall Emperours that made themſelves of Subjects, Lords over them by force of Armes! I know not how this ſhould be injurious to Chriſtianity, unleſſe it be un-Chriſtian to reſtraine the reſiſtance and rebelling of Chriſtians againſt a Chriſtian Prince, when as the Apoſtle did forbid Chriſtians and all the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> to reſiſt their Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, though Heathen and Tyrannicall.</p>
               <p>Let us ſee whether it be injurious to His Majeſty, <hi>How do's he abuſe His Majeſty herein? A Title he yeelds Him by Conqueſt; and yet He muſt not rule by it, a King as Conquerour, and yet He muſt not rule as a Conqueror. How injurious does he make the King to His posterity, in that he ſubſcribes and ſweares to a limited title, and has a free one the while to hold by?</hi> pag. 13. it was no injury to his Majeſty, to ſay, He cannot rule as Conquerour, for he is not a Conquerour, but claimes from him that was; nor is it injurious to His Majeſties poſterity, that he ſweares to a <hi>limited power</hi> (that <hi>limited title,</hi> as this man has it, is a phancy) for he has not a free one as a Conquerour had, yet not limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſuch a firſt election and contrivement, as this Anſwerer dreames of, but by priviledges and immunities granted or reſtored to the people ſince the Conqueſt, unto which His predeceſſors bound themſelves by oath, and ſo doth he.</p>
               <p>It is not for me to ſettle His Majeſties Right, but ſhould I doe it, as this man hath preſumed, I had been injurious to Him and His poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, for as he ſayes here of right by Conqueſt, though falſely, it may give <hi>ius in re,</hi> not <hi>ius ad rem,</hi> ſo I of the right by ſuch an Election as he ha's contrived, however it might give His Majeſtie <hi>ius adrem,</hi> it ſeemes to lend him but a ſlender <hi>ius in re,</hi> a weak aſſurance of holding it, making Him like a Tenant at will, to be outed of Poſſeſſion, ſo oft, and ſo long, as they that have the finall reſolution, ſhall judge expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent; So has he conceived it.</p>
               <p>Now let us goe on, and examine how he makes good this finall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:155829:22"/>
                  <hi>The power of declaring Law,</hi> ſaith he, Pag. 14. <hi>muſt reſt ſome where;</hi> true; In thoſe, ſay we, that have the power of making Lawes, <hi>(i.e.)</hi> in the King and both Houſes.</p>
               <p>Here the Anſwerer puts two Caſes. Firſt, what if they be divided, as at this time? does it reſt in the King or the two Houſes? In neither ſay we, fully, and to the like purpoſe, as it doth in the three Eſtates, which power is ſuſpended while one part ſuſpends.</p>
               <p>He endeavours to ſhew, Pag. 15 &amp; 16. this finall reſolution ſhould reſt in the two Houſes rather then in the King, from their ability and skill. their fidelity, their ends and intereſts, <hi>which do not interferre ſo with thoſe of the Subiect,</hi> Property, Priviledge, &amp;c. <hi>as thoſe of the Kings do,</hi> abſoluteneſſe of Rule, Monopolies, Patents, &amp;c. the compariſon is odious, though we are to hope the beſt of the Members of the two Houſes, yet we know they are <hi>men ſubiect to like paſſions,</hi> as others are, and we are aſſured the King is intruſted with us as well as they, and has beſide Rights and Priviledges of His owne to looke to; But ſeeing this is Comparative onely, <hi>rather in them then the King,</hi> not abſolute, that it ought to reſt in the two Houſes; we may let it goe.</p>
               <p>His ſecond Caſe is, Pag. 17. What if either of the Houſes be divided into equall parts? it is eaſily reſolved, The Speakers voyce caſts it; True. But he ſhould have put two caſes more; Firſt, what if an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity be watched, and one of theſe equall parts do not exceed the fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth part of the whole number, by reaſon of the abſence of the reſt; we are in an ill condition, when that muſt be the finall reſolution of this States judgement; nay, of that number that prevailes, may be ſcarce any Lawyer of known abilities, which was one of his prejudices he layed againſt the King in his Comparative between Him and the Houſes for declaring what is Law.</p>
               <p>The other caſe is, what if the two Houſes be divided in judgement the one from the other? where then reſides this finall reſolution? It may be it will be replied, they ought to ſit together and vote together; ſo indeed ſome would have it, but it is confeſt that the Parliament con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of three Eſtates, and that the Lords and Commons are two ſeveral Eſtates. Well then, if the King concurre in judgement with the Lords, why ſhould not the finall reſolution be in them? for we muſt here call him againe to his reckoning, and tell him as he did us, Pag. 3. it is eaſie to reckon the one is leſſe then two.</p>
               <p>And the more ſtrange this will ſeem, if we conſider what it is, that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:155829:22"/>is now to be declared, no caſe miſ-judged in inferiour Courts, no late written Law, whoſe ſenſe is doubtfull, but the very conſtitution of Parliament that has continued ſo many Ages, whether in that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticution there be ſuch a Law as gives this power of <hi>Supply</hi> by ſeizing and commanding the <hi>Militia;</hi> We underſtand the literall ſenſe of the Oath of Supremacy and Allegiance, and have it confeſſed by this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer, that the Truſt of the <hi>Militia</hi> is ordinarily in His Majeſty, <hi>Pag:</hi> 10. and we ſuppoſe, no man can think that when the Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſweare to obſerve the Lawes and Cuſtomes of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they ever took the Oath in ſuch a ſenſe as to binde them to take for Law, what ere the two Houſes ſhall, without them, declare to be ſo; or that when we bound our ſelves by Proteſtation to maintaine the power and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of Parliament, we meant what ever they declare to be ſuch; for this were too much to reſigne up our faith to man.</p>
               <p>Well then, if there be a diſagreement upon ſuch a declaring, it is better we follow what the known Law commands us to, and that there be a ſuſpenſion of ſuch a declaring, till all that are entruſted for us can agree, then that ſuch a power of declaring be aſſumed by any two of the three Eſtates, for in the ſame 17. <hi>Pag.</hi> it is acknowledged <hi>Arbitrary.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VII. <hi>The finall Reſolution is not Arbitrary in the two Houſes, but onely in the three Eſtates.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IT appears then, that this power is as arbitrary in the two Houſes as it would be in the King, I anſwer, it cannot be denied nor avoided, &amp;c.</hi> It would not be ſo in the King, ſo long as the two Houſes have, what He denies them not, the power of diſſenting; But to tell us plainly, The Power is arbitrary in the two Houſes, is very ingenuous; this Anſwerer is ſeldome ſo, but here beyond all reaſon, for it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows as an admirable proof of what he hath confeſt. <hi>As the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the forme of it, was at firſt an act of the will, and ſo Arbitrary, ſo it ſtill remaining the ſame, it muſt remain ſome where arbitrary ſtill, elſe our fore-fathers ſhould not convey that ſame government to us, which they began, they cannot binde us in that wherein they were themſelves free, Pag.</hi> 17. when were they free? it muſt be before they ſet up the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:155829:23"/>Government <hi>(i. e.)</hi> when they were without government. We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee when the people were ſo free, or that the frame of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment was an arbitrary act of their will; enough has been ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore againſt ſuch conceits; The like we have in thoſe words, <hi>the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſtill remaining the ſame;</hi> the ſame with what? it muſt be with that arbitrary act of their will, which is ſuppoſed to frame that government, or elſe no force of argument in the Conſequence, to prove our Government is ſtill arbitrary ſome where; and if ſo, then no ſenſe in the Antecedent, that our government ſhould be ſaid to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main the ſame with the arbitrary act of will, which at firſt framed it.</p>
               <p>But to pardon his <hi>antecedents,</hi> let us ſee what follows; They were free when they began, or ſet up this Government, therefore we are not bound, now it is ſet up; that frame of Government was an act of their will, and arbitrary, therefore the Government is ſtill arbitrary in them; when people ſet up an abſolute Monarchy over themſelves (as he ſayes the people of <hi>Rome</hi> did, when they conſented to their Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors) that form of Government was an act of their will, and arbitrary when they began it, therefore ſtill it is arbitrary in them; Theſe are good proofs, ſuch indeed as this Anſwerer uſes to bring, framed only to deceive the unwary.</p>
               <p>But ſometimes he expreſſes that firſt Conſtitution, as made by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of King and people, ſure then that Conſent of the King at firſt was an act of His Will, and Arbitrary; and ſo it follows, that the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verment for making of Laws and Conſtitutions, is Arbitrary in the King and people <hi>(i. e.)</hi> in the three eſtates conſenting and agreeing together, and that is the very truth. Onely this depends not upon an arbitrary Act of the peoples will, preceding all Government when they were free, as he ſaid (for that is not imaginable in this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) but muſt needs proceed from an after conſent or grant of the King, admitting them to this arbitriment or freedom of will in the making of Laws, which is enough to binde Him and ſecure us.</p>
               <p>Nor is this Arbitrarines beſt ſecured from doing hurt in the Votes of Parliament (that is of the two Houſes) by reaſon of their <hi>number, truſt,</hi> and <hi>ſelfe intereſt</hi> as he tells us, <hi>Pag.</hi> 17. But it is better ſecured in the three Eſtates, that is, in all that are entruſted for us; for Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines is likely to doe leaſt hurt, where it depends upon thoſe that have ſeverall wills, and ſeverall private Intereſts, as the three Eſtates have, but whoſe publike Intereſt is the ſame; ſo that if the King purſue
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:155829:23"/>His private intereſt, it is croſſed by the private intereſt of the Subject, if they theirs, then will his private intereſt hinder the compaſſing of it, if he may have, what for that purpoſe is left in him by the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of this Government, the power of denying; that ſo being croſſed in their private wayes, they may meet in their publique inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts the good and welfare of the whole State, which is beſt for them both.</p>
               <p>But he tell us, <hi>in the body Naturall the will followes the laſt dictate or reſolution of the underſtanding, that being in this body Politique the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of its Great Councell,</hi> pag. 17. That I may not trouble him in his Philoſophy by telling him, The will has an influence back again upon the underſtanding; I know what he means by the application of it, That the King muſt always follow the final reſolution of the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; which if ſo, what would he be better then a Duke of <hi>Venice,</hi> or this State other then Popular. And to this end have we ſo many diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes tending to the praiſe of <hi>Ariſtocraticall</hi> Government; and he that put out the third Anſwer againſt my Book prefers the State of <hi>Venice</hi> before all for the ſureſt Government. Give me leave to note this by the way, Although it be well known what inconveniences that State lyes under, by reaſon of the ſeverall ſactions and ſidings of their great Families, yet this means of ſecurity they have, Their reſolutions of high concernments are not carried but by ſuch a number of the whole Senate, though many be abſent; And let me take the boldneſſe to ſay, We ſhould conceive our ſelves in a ſuret condition, if ſuch buſineſſer, which nearly concern the Kingdom and the very Conſtitution of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, were not carried by the major part of thoſe that are preſent, but by a more unanimous conſent, that is by the better halfe, at leaſt, of the whole number, that belong to each houſe; ſuch buſineſſes, if need were, had better ſtay till the triall could be made by ſuch a number, then to run the hazard of a watched opportunity, when ſew are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; and ſuch reſolutions would better ſway with his Majeſtie, and better ſatisfie the whole Kingdome.</p>
               <p>Now to this Argument of the laſt dictate; The debates and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of the two Houſes are indeed great helps to inform His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties</hi> underſtanding, but not as the <hi>laſt dictate</hi> immediately to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine his will, for they are <hi>extrinſecall</hi> to him, as the reſolution of one Houſe is to another, They being three ſeverall Eſtates: His will muſt needs follow the dictate of his own underſtanding, having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:155829:24"/>information from them. And whereas I ſaid concerning the Kings Judgement upon ſuch an advantage, <hi>He ſees with the eyes of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, even of thoſe that are of different Judgement from him,</hi> this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer makes me ſay, as he would have it, that <hi>the King is to ſee with the eyes of others,</hi> as if, ſhould they preſent him with black for white, He were bound to think it ſo.</p>
               <p>Then for the binding of the Subject to obedience by this finall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the two Houſes, he tells us, pag. 18. <hi>As their intereſts with us tye them more to doe aright, ſo our elections of them tie us more to ſuffer what they doe, if not aright.</hi> It would trouble this Anſwerer to give the Clergy any aſſurance from theſe mutuall intereſts; for they have none to repreſent them, they have no voice in the election of them that vote there again; this reaſon from repreſentation and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection concerns onely one of the Houſes; and how men of publike truſt may, and have purſued their private intereſts under pretence of the publique good, Experience has heretofore ſhewn it, and time will diſcover it ere long to eyes, that yet cannot ſee it. For their tye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us we grant it, but not to all purpoſes without His <hi>Majeſties</hi> conſent; who is intruſted for us as well as they, nay, in whom the Supream truſt of the Kingdom is. It is not a tie to bind us to obey their arbitrary commands. M. <hi>Burrowes</hi> will tell us in his Anſwer to the fifth Section, ſhould a Parliament ſo far degenerate as to enſlave us, he thinkes the light of nature would ſhew us a way to provide for our ſelves by re-aſſuming the power given to them.</p>
               <p>There is nothing more uſuall in theſe mens mouthes then the Law is our inheritance, we are born unto it. It is true, and it concernes us to look to it; but ſhall our freedom and inheritance, our Petition of Right, our liberties and Priviledges be only good againſt the King, and the reſolution of the Houſes <hi>inevitable</hi> to us for all our intereſts, all we have? So this Anſwerer would make us beleeve.</p>
               <p>In the purſuit of his third propoſition, he tells us, pag. 18. <hi>They are not in themſelves infallible, but to us inevitable; here is no Parliament Papacy, as the Doctor pleaſes to deſcant.</hi> Certainly the Pope himſelf does not beleeve himſelf to be infallible, nor do his learned flatterers, that would maintain it; but the deceived people beleeve it down right, and it is for the advantage of the other, that they do ſo; The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor ſaid not there was infallibility in the great Councell, but wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the miſled people to examine whether they have not ſuch a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:155829:24"/>thought, to worke them into an implicite faith of beleeving and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving without Examination what ever is concluded there.</p>
               <p>He leaves us a private diſſent of judgement from their determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but we are bound by them from gainſaying, or reſiſtance, and ſo it is to us inevitable. <hi>Such a power of binding has a generall Councell to its deciſions, and why ſhould a Civill Generall Councell of England have leſſe power in it?</hi> So he, pag. 18. We Anſwer the great Councell of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> has ſuch power of binding inevitably if you adde the aſſent of the King; as all Eccleſiaſticall Councels expect the Confirmation of the ſupream Civill power for the binding of thoſe, that are under them, to their Canons and deciſions; But if we keepe our ſelves from gainſaying or reſiſtance, will it ſatiſfie? no, their Reſolution or Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance cals us all to active obedience, to Arme, kill, and ſlay; and this we muſt believe after ſo many ages to be a fundamentall Law; when as we heare the known Law (which is inevitable to us) not onely binding us from being active againſt His Majeſty, to the endangering of His Perſon, or diminution of His Crowne and Dignity, but alſo not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring us to be ſilent or ſit ſtill when the defence of His Rights, or Perſon requires our aid.</p>
               <p>We have now done with his propoſitions, and his diſcourſe upon them, whereby he hath wound himſelfe up to the pitch of <hi>Bractons</hi> ſpeech, which he brought and rejected as too high to be attempted, pag. 4. <hi>the King hath above him beſides God and the Law, His Court of Earles and Barons.</hi> But this Anſwerer has placed both them and the Houſe of Commons in that height, by this finall Reſolution and arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary inevitable Command; and this reſerved by them in their firſt choice of a King, which according to the rules of Policy, makes the King to have but <hi>imperium communicatum,</hi> leaves the ſupream comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding power in them.</p>
               <p>From the Premiſes he concludes his reſolution for Conſcience, pag. 19. <hi>This great Centurion of the Kingdome, the Parliament, ſaies to one of this now neceſſary liſted Army, Goe and he goes, to another come and he comes — what other authority hath a Sheriffe to put a Malefactor to death?</hi> We have had enough of the Centurion already, too much (God knowes) of the Military Commands; we ſhould have liked it better if he had likened the Parliament to that wiſe and peaceable woman which gave advice to throw the Rebels heads over the walls, and ſo the matter was ended, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.18. But hath the Sheriffe no
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:155829:25"/>other Authority but ſuch as a Centurion gives to Kill and Slay? He ha's it derived from the only Supream Governour the King, and ſo ſhould every one that takes the Sword.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſcience alſo ha's Gods warrant too, firſt of Charity, by the ſixth Commandement, which not onely forbids Murder, but commands preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of ours and our Neighbours life; Secondly of Juſtice, Render to all what is due; to the great Councell what is due to it upon the Kings refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall; laſtly, of obedience, Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man —Hence every Souldier in this Army hath warrant enough for his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience if he apply it.</hi> I am ſure his three warrants here from Gods Law are miſapplyed and will not ſecure their Souldiers Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Firſt, that warrant of ſelfe defence and preſervation tels us we muſt not doe it by murthering of others, which may happen when our ſelfe preſervation uſes meanes not allowed by the Law, it is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated by; if it be the defence of the body Naturall, then muſt it be according to the Law of God and Nature; if of the body Politique, then according to its Law, which this man has not any waies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to preſcribe this way of preſervation by Subjects taking Armes; we ſee by the Law, the King is the onely ſupream Governor, and ſo the Sword is put into His hand for preſervation of order, and executing of wrath, from whom the Authority of the Sheriffe and all other Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of power is derived. But he that takes the Sword by his owne au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and not by Commiſſion from or under Him, commits murder, and ſhall periſh by the Sword; The Law is yet to make, that may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive the warrant of killing and ſlaying from any other fountaine of power.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ender to all what is due,</hi> is a good rule of Juſtice, and tels us what is due to the King by the fift Commandement, Honour, and Feare, and Tribute, as the Apoſtle goes on in that place, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. but it's miſapplied by the Anſwerer to urge the rendring of <hi>Obedience</hi> to the Arbitrary commands of the two Houſes, for unto ſuch it is not due (as has been ſhewn) though this man phancy it never ſo ſtrongly.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, <hi>The ſubmiſſion to every Ordinance of Man</hi> is alſo miſapplied by him, for there was never any ſuch Ordinance or Contrivement, which reſerved ſuch a power at the firſt Conſtitution of this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as he ſuppoſes, but never could prove.</p>
               <p>Therefore I may conclude according to my firſt reſolve in my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Treatiſe, <hi>Conſcience cannot finde any warrant or ſafe ground to goe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:155829:25"/>upon for making this reſiſtance.</hi> For, according to the principles of the now pleaders for this reſiſtance, It finds nothing but a pretended Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, at a ſuppoſed Capitulating Election, contriving and reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for the people ſuch a power; finds this un reaſonable in it ſelfe, inconſiſtent with the uſuall and eſtabliſhed government of this Land, and ſo cannot thinke it ſafe to reſt on, or fit to give it warrant againſt the known Law which places the power of Armes in the King, which acknowledges him <hi>Only ſupreme Governour,</hi> which challenges, by Our Allegiance, ayd and aſſiſtance from us for the defence not onely of His Perſon but alſo of His Rights, His Crown and Dignity, which are moſt injuriouſly wronged by this Contrivement, or frame of Government, and exceedingly invaded by this reſiſtance and power of Armes raiſed and uſed againſt Him at this day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VIII. <hi>A Confutation of what is replied by the Anſwerers upon the firſt Sect. of the former Treatiſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw we come to the application of what hath been hitherto ſaid, to ſee how it meets with what was written in the former Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, where we ſhall take in the other Anſwerers alſo; And firſt we muſt caſt an eye over Mr. <hi>Bridge</hi> his grounds, which he layes for this reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, before he enters upon the firſt Section.</p>
               <p>He tels us, there are three grounds of their proceeding by Armes. 1. <hi>To fetch in Delinquents to be tryed in the higheſt Court.</hi> 2. <hi>To de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the State from forraine invaſion.</hi> 3. <hi>To preſerve themſelves and their Country from the inſurrection of Papiſts; And that all this is done as an act of ſelfe-preſervation, not as an act of Iuriſdiction over their Prince,</hi> Pag. 2. That Delinquents ſhould be brought to a Legall tryall, and the State defended, is juſt and neceſſary, yet to be done in an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly and Legall way; not by an Army raiſed by Subjects, taking the <hi>Militia</hi> and power of the Kingdome out of choſe hands, in which the Law has in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſted it. And if Conſcience were to ſpeake the Truth, it could not ſay, that any Delinquents were denied or with-held, till the <hi>Militia</hi> was ſeized, and a great Delinquent in the matter of <hi>Hull</hi> was denied to be brought to tryall at His Majeſties inſtance, of which ſee more above, Sect. 5. Neither can Conſcience ſay, that Subjects have
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:155829:26"/>had cauſe upon feares and pretences of forrain invaſion, or inſurrection of Papiſts to Arme and reſiſt,</p>
               <p>Whether this be done by an Act of juriſdiction, we may diſcerne by the plea of the fuller Anſwerer, for he would have us believe, they are inabled to this by Law and the Conſtitution of this Government, and that they doe it by an act of judgement, the States judgement reſiding in their finall reſolution, and that this power of theirs is tranſcendent to any power ordinarily in the King, for it declares Law without Him, it does arbitrarily command the power of the Kingdome, and the obedience of the people without and againſt the commands of the King (ſo we found it in the examination of his diſcourſe) and what is more required to an act of Juriſdiction I know not; let Him and Mr. <hi>Bridge</hi> agree it.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Bridge</hi> gives us proofes for this way of preſervation; Firſt, from the Law of Nature, <hi>ſelfe preſervation is naturall for a Man, for a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity; and therefore when a Community ſhall truſt a Prince with their welfare, that act of truſt is but by poſitive Law, and cannot deſtroy the Naturall Law, which is ſelfe-preſervation,</hi> pag. 2. But the <hi>Fuller Anſwer</hi> will tell him there muſt be a Conſtitution to enable them to this ſelfe-preſervation. And were this Argument good, then might private men, or the people without the Parliament, take Armes and reſiſt; for ſelfe-preſervation is naturall to them, and no poſitive Law (which according to the <hi>Fuller Anſwer,</hi> reſtraines their reſiſtance upon their truſt given to the Houſes of Parliament) can, according to Mr. <hi>Bridge</hi> his reaſon, deſtroy that naturall Law. Alſo abſolute Princes (with whom the people have intruſted their welfare without any reſevati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on might be reſiſted, (which the <hi>Fuller Anſwer</hi> againe denies) for that act of truſt is but by poſitive Law, and according to Mr. <hi>Bridge</hi> it muſt not reſtraine them, for it cannot deſtroy the Naturall Law of ſelf-preſervation.</p>
               <p>But he ſhould have obſerved, that as the naturall body is to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it ſelfe according to its Law, and no otherwiſe, ſo a Community or politique body, muſt doe it according to its Law, which preſcribeth the order, and way, and means of preſervation; and for want of hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that way, we ſee people often, under pretence of this ſelfe-preſervation, drawne by ſeditious Leaders into Armes to their owne deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he proves it from the Law of God, by places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:155829:26"/>but ſo wildely, that I am aſhamed to repeat them; yet the judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Reader muſt give me leave for the peoples ſake, that are abuſed by theſe mens abuſing of Scripture.</p>
               <p>1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.19. <hi>It is expreſly ſaid, that David went out againſt Saul to battail, but he was Sauls ſubject at that time,</hi> pag. 2. A deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate undertaking, to make people beleeve this is expreſſe Scripture, for Subjects to go out to Battaile againſt their King, but he ſhould have added what is expreſſed there, it was <hi>with the Philiſtines</hi> that he went out, and that <hi>He helped them not,</hi> for he did but make ſhew of tendring his ſervice to <hi>Achiſh.</hi> See below, Sect. 9. where this place is touched again.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>Be ſubject to the higher powers. But the Parliament is the higheſt Court of Juſtice,</hi> pag. 3. this is well aſſumed; but we grant the Concluſion, there is a ſubjection due to them; and if he means by the Parliament, the three Eſtates concurring, then all manner of ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and obedience is due to them. But he takes them as divided; for it follows, <hi>Though the King be ſupreame, yet they have the high power of declaring Law,</hi> pag. 3. this is a good explication of the Supremacy. <hi>Yea this Doctor confeſſeth they are moſt fit to judge what is Law.</hi> Take in all my words which were theſe <hi>(none ſo fit to judge what thoſe fundamentalls are, as They that have power to build new Laws upon them)</hi> and then make what you can of them, or look what is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken above of Supremacy. <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. of the power of Declaring Law, <hi>Sect.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>Then he undertakes to ſhew out of Scripture, that Kings receive their power from the people, and has the ill hap to light on <hi>Saul, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> for examples, becauſe it is ſaid, <hi>They made Saul King before the Lord,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. and ſo of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon;</hi> which was the peoples not giving of power, but receiving and acknowledging him for King whom the Lord had deſigned.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, he has found an example and proofe for the truſt of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Davids</hi> time, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.1, 2. <hi>David</hi> conſults with the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Leaders, and with all the Congregation about the fetching of the Ark; what then? <hi>Theſe were Officers not of the King but King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and though under him, yet were they with him truſted in the affairs of the Kingdom,</hi> pag. 5. Excellent Collections! The <hi>Fuller Anſwer</hi> will tell him preſently, that the Kings of the <hi>Iewes</hi> were abſolute Monarches; though I ſay not ſo, yet this I ſay, thoſe were Officers of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:155829:27"/>the King and Kingdom, meerly deſigned by him, not the people, and called by him to that truſt; what he infers, <hi>that the Parliament is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted by the people,</hi> though not deduceible from that place, I grant; yet ſo, as that they have a truſt from the King upon them too; as was above ſhewn, <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. But <hi>that in caſe they think the King miſled, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to their truſt, to take the Armes of the Kingdom,</hi> as M. <hi>Bridge</hi> would inferre, can neither be drawn out of that place of Scripture, nor any Law of this Land, that ever could yet be ſeen. The like rambling diſcourſe he has upon the 5. <hi>Sect.</hi> touching the Monarchicall Government which God ſet up over his people, wherein as he is for the concluſion altogether contrary to the <hi>Full Anſwerer,</hi> who held the Jewiſh Monarchy abſolute, ſo for his proofes and places of Scripture alleaged, altogether impertinent.</p>
               <p>At length he will ſeem to give us Law for it, <hi>Inferiour Courts have power to ſend for by force, if need be, thoſe that are accuſed, much more the Parliament, the higheſt Court,</hi> pag. 6. And therefore alſo inferiour Courts have power to raiſe Armies to force in the Accuſed, if they refuſe to come in upon Summons; that would make good work.</p>
               <p>But the Law has provided a force, if need be, a <hi>Poſſe Comitatûs,</hi> and the Kings Officer or Miniſter for that is the Sheriffe; but this new way turnes both the King out of His power, and His Miniſters out of their Office, ſending Voluntiers and liſted Souldiers into every Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to force in Delinquents.</p>
               <p>But he tells us, they may ſend a Sergeant at Armes for a Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, therefore twenty if twenty be accuſed, and therefore an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and ſo goes on till he has made an Army of 10000. Sergeants at at Armes, pag. 6. I did not know before, that the Souldiers pretended to be ſent from the Parliament: were all Sergeants at Armes? what need ſo many? certainly before this Army of Sergeants was raiſed, very few would have ſerved to have warned in Delinquents; it has made many a ſorrowfull Father in the Countrey to ſee his ſonne called to ſuch an imployment, whom he had bound Apprentiſe in <hi>London</hi> to another trade; Nay, the whole Kingdom has rued the ſending of ſuch and ſo many Sergeants at Armes (who do not onely arreſt mens per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as they pleaſe, but alſo plunder their Eſtates) and does earneſtly deſire, that as it is pretended Delinquents muſt be brought to triall by Law, ſo they may be fetched or forced in, by the way and meanes, the Law (as was ſaid) has provided.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:155829:27"/>
               <p>He concludes with an Anſwer to an Objection, <hi>If the power of the Prince be derimed from the people, then they may take it away, when abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and depoſe their Prince.</hi> Anſw. <hi>No, we doe not ſay ſo, the people need not think of ſuch an inference, becauſe they never gave away the power of ſelfe preſervation,</hi> pag. 7. Theſe are but cold denials, though you ſay they need not go ſo farre, yet you have opened and paved the way for them, to be led on ſo far upon theſe principles: and what ſhall withhold them? <hi>becauſe they have the power of ſelfe preſervation by taking Armes, whereas if they had not that power, it were the way to breake all in pieces,</hi> pag. 7. So it ſeemes, the way to keepe people in obedience, is to give them liberty of Rebelling; but what ſecuritie has the Prince, that they will truſt him with the power againe, if a few ſeditious Preachers tell them, their Prince will not uſe the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er well, if they truſt him again with it? they gave it him at firſt, and now they may conferre it upon another, who will manage it better in order to their ſafety; Or if they doe lay downe their Arms and truſt Him with power again, it ſhall be to his prejudice, he ſhall be forced firſt to conſent to what they pleaſe, and what this is called by our Law, every one, that underſtands any thing, knows.</p>
               <p>Then in Anſwer to what was ſaid in the firſt Section of the former Treatiſe (that our Divines by denying reſiſtance unto Subjects, doe not endeavour to raiſe the King to an arbitrary power, for they allow the denying of Obedience to all commands unlawfull by the Law of God, or the eſtabliſhed Lawes of the Land) M. <hi>Bridge</hi> firſt would ſeem to returne me to a Catalogue of Proteſtant Divines, allowing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance in ſome Caſes, and then tells me, if we may not reſiſt, we yeeld the King an arbitrary power. For His forreigne Divines; the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the <hi>Centuriſts,</hi> ſpeaks not to his purpoſe; Of the French, and Low-Countrey Divines he brings no teſtimonies, but for proofe tells us, <hi>we know their practice;</hi> ſo I for Anſwer may returne him his owne words, we know what has beene the practice of thoſe Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, and ſo they are parties intereſſed, not ſo fit to give in witneſſe; but this I will ſay for them, they can juſtifie the cauſe of their Armes, better then M. <hi>Bridge</hi> can doe his; Now for our Engliſh Divines, its plaine they ſpeake of ſuch Government, ſuch States, ſuch caſes as will not agree to this Kingdom, or this time; yet doe ſome of them allow of reſiſtance in ſome caſes; true, for ſince the revolt of the Low-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and the firſt motions of the Proteſtants in <hi>France.</hi> I finde in many
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:155829:28"/>of our Divines a willingneſſe to excuſe, as much as may be. But if we looke beyond thoſe times into our Homilies, we ſhall finde the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of our Church expreſly againſt Subjects taking of Armes.</p>
               <p>Then he tells us, though we may deny Obedience to the Kings un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Commands, yet if we may not reſiſt, but ſuffer, when He pleaſes to puniſh for not obeying, we raiſe him to an arbitrary power, <hi>Pag.</hi> 12. <hi>Anſwer:</hi> To ſay He may command any thing not repugnant to Gods Law, and puniſh lawfully for not obeying, is to raiſe him to an Arbitrary power; but to ſay He may not command any thing againſt the Law of the Land, and if He puniſh for not obeying ſuch His com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, it is unjuſt and againſt the Law; yet unlawfull alſo for us to take Arms againſt Him for it, is not to raiſe him to an arbitrary power; For <hi>Arbitrary</hi> and <hi>limited</hi> power is diſtinguiſhed by the <hi>Reſtraint,</hi> which the Law or Conſtitution of Government caſts upon the governing power, not by the <hi>abuſe</hi> of that power, which ſometimes in the moſt limited Governments may break out into a licentious arbitrarynes; If force and not Law muſt tell us what Arbitrary power is, and releeve us againſt it in the Prince, I fear we ſhould too often feel it from the hand of Subjects.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Fuller Anſwerer</hi> would make me contradict my ſelfe, in deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the King an arbitrary Government, <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. and yeelding him the <hi>finall Iudgement, Sect.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Now the Reader will diſcern, this is not my failing, but his uſuall miſtaking of what I ſay; the place he aimes at, is <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. <hi>Pag.</hi> 26. where in anſwering the objection, <hi>many ſee more then one, and more ſafety in the Iudgement of many, then of one,</hi> it was ſaid. <hi>The King ſees with the eyes of thoſe many, and all times have thought it reaſonable to have Monarchy, which ſettles the chief power and finall Iudgement in one.</hi> That was for the generall, which I ſuppoſe is the reaſon and frame of Monarchy; how it was good in our King, by His <hi>power of denying,</hi> appears in that place, for the finall Judgement was no otherwiſe challenged for him; Now if ſuch a Judgement of the Kings be called <hi>a finall Iudgement,</hi> becauſe it is the laſt, and after the Judgement of many, it matters not, it will not infer an arbitrary power, as <hi>the finall Reſolution,</hi> which this man placeth in the two Houſes, doth; for if it be diſſenting from the Judgement of thoſe many, it is onely <hi>Negative,</hi> it is not <hi>Concluſive</hi> any other way. Such, I ſay, is the Kings finall Truſt or Judgement, by conſenting to thoſe many, or denying, not by
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:155829:28"/>concluding, or commanding any other way, as he pleaſes.</p>
               <p>The laſt exception of theſe Anſwerers to the firſt Section, is againſt my interpretation of <hi>Omnes ordines conſentientes,</hi> to imply a generall and unanimous conſent of the Members of the two Houſes in this point of reſiſtance; Firſt; they ſay it is enough if the major part agree, or elſe many Acts of Parliament would be voyd. <hi>Anſwer:</hi> however it is enough to other votes and Acts, if the major part agree upon it; yet in the concluding for reſiſtance, if the condition of it by there grants be, <hi>omnibus ordinibus conſentientibus;</hi> and their reaſon for it be, <hi>Rex eſt uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſis minor,</hi> and reſiſtance it ſelfe be an oppoſing of the body againſt the head; there muſt be in all equity an univerſality in the conſent, and an unanimous inclination of the whole body, and not a part of the body againſt the head, and another part of the ſame body.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Mr. <hi>Bridge</hi> replies. <hi>If this be our ſentence, why doth the Dr. object againſt us, that the Chriſtians in the primitive times did not take up Armes againſt the Emperors, ſeeing they had not the conſent of all the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Empire,</hi> Pag. 13. The Doctor never intended that objecting of the Chriſtians for an argument by it ſelfe, and therefore to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians perſecuted, did uſually ſubjoyn the Senate and people enſlaved, ſhewing they might not reſiſt, being all under that <hi>higher power</hi> or <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream</hi> (as St. <hi>Peter</hi> cals the Emperor,) and contained within that uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall, <hi>whoſoever reſists.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IX. <hi>A Confutation of what was replyed upon the ſecond Section of the former Treatiſe, touching places of Scripture pretended for, or alleadged againſt Reſiſtance.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe <hi>Fuller Anſwerer</hi> ſpeakes confidently. <hi>The inſtances of Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance (of the peoples in behalfe of</hi> Jonathan, <hi>of</hi> Davids, <hi>of</hi> Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhah's,) <hi>we make no uſe of, we need them not, and therefore need not Anſwer the refutation of them, Pag.</hi> 21. But all your fellowes make uſe of them, who having not ſo fine a wit to contrive a power of reſiſtance <hi>reſerved</hi> by the people when they made the firſt King, did conceive they ſtood in need of Examples to defend the peoples <hi>aſſuming</hi> of ſuch a power.</p>
               <p>Well, however this Anſwerer pretends, he needs them not, yet
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:155829:29"/>does he ſticke upon the example of <hi>David,</hi> and tels us, Pag. 21. <hi>what uſe of His Army, but to fight againſt?</hi> nay, a reach above all his fellows, <hi>that David (though againſt the King) is ſaid to fight the Lords battels,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. The words are <hi>Abigails,</hi> and the Comment is his, more then once given us in this booke, he had before ſpent two pages, the fixth and ſeventh, in repeating what notes he had taken at Court-Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, now he gives us a taſte of what is preached at St. <hi>Margarets,</hi> and up and down the City. <hi>That to fight againſt the King now, is to fight the Lords battels,</hi> or as Mr. <hi>Burrows</hi> in his Sermon, <hi>that the Armies now againſt the King, are the Hoſts of the Lord,</hi> and in his Epiſtle, he cals the Earle of <hi>Eſſex, the Lord of their Hoſts,</hi> ſo uſually doe they intereſſe the Lord in their quarrell, and are bold againe with his Titles; We know that to fight the battels of the Lord, was againſt the Enemies of his people, <hi>Philiſtins, Ammonites, &amp;c.</hi> and that <hi>David</hi> was deſigned to it; that he had done it already under <hi>Saul</hi> againſt the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> and was to doe it more fully after <hi>Sauls</hi> death, againſt the enemies of <hi>Iſrael</hi> round about; and accordingly the words of <hi>Abigail</hi> have this mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; though it be known that my Lord is appointed to fight the Lords battels, and to deliver his people from their enemies round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, yet is there riſen up a man to purſue after, &amp;c. Certainly if to fight againſt <hi>Saul</hi> had been to fight the Lords batrels, <hi>David</hi> had not fought them well, that declined all battel with him, made uſe of no advantages when he had <hi>Saul</hi> twice in his power. <hi>David</hi> knew the battels of the Lord, which he was to fight, were againſt the Lords enemies abroad, not againſt the Lords annointed at home.</p>
               <p>But this Anſwerer ſaid, <hi>what uſe of an Army, unleſſe to ſight againſt?</hi> we ſee <hi>David</hi> did not put it, did not intend it for that uſe; yea, but he would have put it to that uſe at <hi>Keilah,</hi> if the Inhabitants would have been faithfull to him: So they conclude upon <hi>Davids</hi> intention, for defending of what was actually done at <hi>Hull;</hi> I call'd that an uncertain ſuppoſition not fit to ground Conſcience on.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Burrows</hi> tels us, <hi>the caſe is as plaine for Davids intention, as if Sir</hi> John Hotham, <hi>upon comming of the Kings Forces againſt</hi> Hull, <hi>ſhould inquire of the Towneſ-men, whether they would deliver him up or no, and upon knowledge that they would, ſhould flie away; were this an uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſuppoſition that Sir</hi> John <hi>would have defended himſelfe there?</hi> In Sir <hi>John Hotham</hi> it would be a very probable ſuppoſition, becauſe we know the inclination of his mind, and the intent for which he came
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:155829:29"/>thither, but in <hi>David</hi> it is not onely uncertaine but improbable, for we know his reſolution and cuſtome was ſtill to flie as the King purſued, and to that end he enquires what they intended againſt him, and in caſe they were minded to deliver him up, he might more timely provide for his flight, and prevent their ſhutting of him up in that City, which, as the text notes, had <hi>gates</hi> and <hi>barres.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>M. <hi>Bridge</hi> upon the Anſwers in the former Treatiſe made to their inſtances of reſiſtance, replies, <hi>that, in ſaying it was a loving violence by which the people reſcued Ionathan, and Davids Armes were meerely for defence without all offence, the Doctor gives away the Cauſe, and allows Subjects more then prayers and teares, Pag.</hi> 14.5. The Doctor had no where (though M. <hi>Bridge</hi> makes him often ſay ſo) prayers and teares, as the onely remedy left to Subjects; but beſide their Cries to God, he allowed them Petitions to their Prince, interceſſions, reproofes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall of Subſidies and Aydes; and the peoples reſcuing of <hi>Ionathan</hi> was by interceſſion ſet off with a Souldierly boldneſſe, ſuch as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple uſed to <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.3. and <hi>Ioab</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.5. Nor is it the giving away of the cauſe to acknowledge <hi>Davids</hi> Armes were for ſuch defence; for the ſeverall anſwers returned to <hi>Davids</hi> example were given, to ſhew they that have now taken Armes may not doe ſo much as <hi>David</hi> did, for his example was extraordinary, and alſo that they have done more then <hi>David</hi> did, for he uſed thoſe armed men meerely for his guard, without all offence to <hi>Saul</hi> or them that were about him; and ſo <hi>Davids</hi> example can no waies be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to thoſe that have now taken Armes, and uſe them as they have done.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If his example be extraordinary, then he had an extraordinary command for what he did, if ſo, how doth the Doctor ſay, there is no command or war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in Scripture for ſuch a practice or kind of Reſiſtance, Pag.</hi> 16. As if all extraordinary warrants and inſtincts given to ſpeciall perſons ſhould be written in Scripture, <hi>Ehud</hi> ſure had one to goe and ſlay the Tyrant <hi>Eglon, Iudg.</hi> 3. yet not expreſſed; Or as if extraordinary Commands, though expreſſed, were warrants for all to doe ſo; as that which the Iſraelites had for ſpoyling the Aegyptians, were now good warrant for the pretended Parliamentary forces, to ſpoile all thoſe they call Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants, and eſteem little better then Aegyptians.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But a meere defence, how then a worke extraordinary in</hi> David? <hi>ibid;</hi> if his were not an extraordinary example, then may private and ſingle
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:155829:30"/>men doe ſo too; But tis nor for Subjects private or publique of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to draw armed men together. The Houſes when they conceived it fit to have a guard, could not raiſe armed men for that purpoſe, but by deſiring it of the King. Now we ſee Armies of Subjects raiſed by Subjects, flie up and down all Countries. giving the King himſelfe and His men battell, where they can fall upon them with advantage, and yet <hi>Davids</hi> example is pretended; And Mr. <hi>Bridge</hi> will yet give us one more inſtance from it, not much unlike what the <hi>Fuller Anſwer</hi> had above, concerning <hi>Davids</hi> fighting the Lords battels againſt <hi>Saul;</hi> it is this.</p>
               <p>David <hi>would have gone with the</hi> Philiſtins <hi>into battell againſt</hi> Saul, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.19. <hi>and ſaid to</hi> Achiſh <hi>what have I done, that I may not goe fight againſt the Enemies of my Lord the King?</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 29.8. <hi>Now among thoſe Enemies was</hi> Saul, <hi>Pag.</hi> 15. Deſperate ſhifts that theſe men are put to, when pretences and ſimulations muſt be made Scripture grounds for Conſcience to ſecure it in battell againſt the King; <hi>David</hi> a little before had made ſhew of madneſſe before King <hi>Achiſh,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21. had pretended to <hi>Achiſh,</hi> he had made an inrode upon the South of <hi>Judah,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. now might Mr. <hi>Bridge</hi> as well inferre, therefore he was mad, therefore he did fight againſt the Subjects of <hi>Saul,</hi> and its lawfull for Subjects to fight againſt Subjects of their King, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of this.</p>
               <p>In the example of the Prieſts, and King <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> out of 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 26. he cannot ſee <hi>why they ſhould be commended for Valiant men if not for reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, nor how it appeares by Scripture that Gods ſmiting him with leproſie ſhould diſcharge him of the Kingdom,</hi> Pag. 17. Surely they deſerve the Commendation of Valiant men, that when a King doth or comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth unlawfully, dare withſtand either by a home reproofe, or by withdrawing from him the holy things, he is not to meddle with. For the other matter, he might have remembred, that by the Law the Lepet was to be put out of the Congregation and dwell apart, which is not conſiſtent with Government, therefore it is ſaid of this King, <hi>He was a Laper and dwelt in a ſeverall houſe, and</hi> Jotham <hi>his ſonne reigned in his ſtead,</hi> 2 King. 15.5.</p>
               <p>What is replyed by Mr. <hi>Bridge,</hi> or Mr. <hi>Burrowes</hi> upon the Anſwer to the example of <hi>Eliſha,</hi> may be anſwered by what is ſaid above, <hi>Sect.</hi> 8. concerning the preſervation of the body Naturall and body Politique, and concerning the ſending for Delinquents.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:155829:30"/>
               <p>Now for the inſtances that were brought in the former Treatiſe againſt Reſiſtance or Armes taken up by Subjects. To that of the power of the Trumpet placed in the Supreame Magiſtrate, <hi>Numb.</hi> 10. M. <hi>Bridge</hi> replyes. <hi>The Parliament hath ſounded no Trumpet for Warre, but what the Supreame Power hath given Commandment for; For it is an eſtabliſhed Law that the Parliament ſhould have power to ſend for Delinquents, and ſuch Law is to be obeyed, becauſe (as the Doctor ſaith, Sect.</hi> 1.) <hi>it has the Kings deliberate conſent, however he is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed now to ſound a retreat by his ſuddain will, pag.</hi> 20, 21. The King has given His conſent to that Law, that gives power to the Houſes to ſend for and cenſure Delinquents, and is ſtill willing that accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, all Armies laid aſide, Delinquents ſhould be brought to a legall triall; but He never gave conſent to a Law that ſhould inable them to raiſe Armes under that pretence, for there is no Law preſcribes them that way or means to bring in their Delinquents.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>Burrowes</hi> replies. That of the Trumpet <hi>was a Iudiciall Law, and binds onely in the equity of it; Elſe it would be a ſinne to put the</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia <hi>into any other hands for any time, for it might not then be done, no not with</hi> Moſes <hi>his conſent.</hi> True, it was a Judiciall Law, and that might have told M. <hi>Burrowes</hi> his many exceptions from the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and ſpecialties of that Law were needleſſe. But an equity he grants, and ſo there is in all Judiciall Lawes, and we require no more in this then the equity of it, which tells us (and we ſee it in all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments) the power of the Trumpet, or calling aſſemblies for War, is ſtill placed in the ſupream Magiſtrate, and cannot be put into other hands, without His conſent.</p>
               <p>To that place of 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.18. The people had no remedy againſt the oppreſſion of their unjuſt Kings, but crying to the Lord, M. <hi>Bridge</hi> replyes, <hi>Samuel tells them not what ſhould be their duty, but what their puniſhment.</hi> The Lord will not heare you, pag. 20. It ſeems their duty was to take Armes and bring their Kings into order; <hi>but he tells them not of their duty, he tells them of their puniſhment,</hi> It was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed their puniſhment, becauſe all the remedy they had (which was by crying to the Lord) ſhould not helpe them; which had not been ſuch a puniſhment, if they had meanes to help themſelves by power of Armes, the power of ſelfe preſervation, as theſe men call it.</p>
               <p>To that which was ſaid of the Prophets, It is a marvellous thing, that none of them ſhould call upon the Elders of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> for
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:155829:31"/>this duty of reſiſtance againſt their cruell and Idolatrous Kings, Maſter <hi>Bridge</hi> replies, <hi>ſee here is a Prophet Eliſha calling on the Elders to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon the Kings meſſenger, Pag.</hi> 22. How happy are theſe men in their application of Scripture: But what Elders were theſe? of the Citie without doubt, where <hi>Eliſha</hi> was. And I feare that ſome of the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of our chief City, have been animated by Preachers, that never were brought up in the Schooles of the Prophets, upon ſuch abuſed examples, to lay hold on the Kings Meſſengers comming with not ſuch an illegall commiſſion, as this did, but lawfull and neceſſary Commands and Proclamations; Againe, what did <hi>Eliſha</hi> call upon theſe Elders for? to impriſon the meſſenger? that's more then the text will bear, unleſſe to ſhut the doore againſt a man be to impriſon him; for this performance there needed not the authority of the Elders; had any elſe been with the Prophet they might have done it without command, had they known the Meſſengers errand as the Prophet did. It is no more then any Debter may doe, ſhut the door of his houſe againſt a Sergeant though comming legally to arreſt him; Had our City Elders (that now have Forces at their command to ſecure themſelves againſt all Miniſters of Juſtice, that have entred the Kings Houſe and Caſtles, keeping the gates ſhut againſt Him) done no more, but contained themſelves within their owne houſes, keeping the door faſt againſt the Sergeant, the King would not have had cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of them.</p>
               <p>To that place, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.18. and to that obſervation (that none of the Prophets called upon the Elders for this duty of reſiſtance) the ſumme of M. <hi>Burrowes</hi> anſwer is, <hi>Pag.</hi> 118. and 122. the Argument is Negative, and he brings ſeverall Inſtances negative, which hold not. <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true that many times ſuch Arguments faile, yet may they be within their own compaſſe very convincing, as in this caſe: It was ſaid, the Apoſtles prohibition againſt reſiſtance was very expreſſe, and that Conſcience could finde no warrant or exceptions againſt it from other places of Scripture; how ſhould this be cleared, but by anſwering ſuch ſeeming inſtances as they brought, and by bringing ſuch places, as were moſt likely to have given allowance to this remedy which is placed in the power of reſiſtance? for if Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence cannot finde allowance for it in Scripture, how ſhould it adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon it againſt the expreſſe prohibition of the Apoſtle, delivered without any exception or limitation?</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:155829:31"/>
               <p>One of his Inſtances I muſt touch, as ſeeming to concerne the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe more neerly, <hi>when the ten Tribes caſt off</hi> Rehoboams <hi>Government for his oppreſſion, no Prophet rebuked them, Pag.</hi> 122. They were not at that inſtant rebuked, for the thing was from the Lord, and to take effect; yet as it was from their licentious will of revolting, it is called <hi>Rebelling againſt the houſe of David,</hi> 2 <hi>Chro. c.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 19. and reproved by <hi>Hoſea, c.</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 4. which is enough to tell Conſcience, what to think of it.</p>
               <p>Now we come to the <hi>Fuller Anſwerer.</hi> To the Inſtances brought againſt Reſiſtance in the former Treatiſe he replyes, <hi>They are all in ſimple and abſolute Monarchies, thoſe of the Iewes and Romanes, nothing to our caſe, Pag.</hi> 21. This is ſhort worke; yet doth M. <hi>Bridge, Pag.</hi> 40. tell us by the example of the Jewiſh Monarchy, what government pleaſeth him beſt: That, wherein the people have choice of their King, and make a Covenant with him at his Coronation, and have power to take up Armes againſt the Monarch when cauſe requireth, all this he endeavours to exemplifie in the Jewiſh Monarchy, very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe tinently, I muſt needs ſay, yet enough to ſhew his diſagreement, with this <hi>Full Anſwerer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us then ſee what ſatisfaction Conſcinece can receive from this Anſwer, either in the generall, that Reſiſtance is lawfull in limited, not abſolute Monarchies, or in particular, that thoſe of the Jewes and Romanes were ſuch. An abſolute Monarch is he, that may impoſe Laws without conſent of people; a limited or not abſolute one is he that hath bound himſelfe to require their conſent, and to rule accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Law ſo made. Now Conſcience findes in Scripture <hi>Manaſſes</hi> and ſuch wicked Kings ſubverting Gods worſhip. Juſtice, and all good government, and no reſiſtance allowed, the Prophets never calling upon the Elders of the people for it; alſo among the Roman Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, It finders the like Tyrants, and ſtill hears the Apoſtle forbidding reſiſtance: Well, It is under a Chriſtian King, one not wicked but commended by many vertues, yet one that has invaded ſome liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties granted to the Subject upon agreement; How ſhall it thinke it has warrant to reſiſt this King, becauſe he is limited by ſuch an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the other not to be reſiſted? for it ſees, that ſafety of the State (in order to which this power of reſiſtance is challenged) is the end of government as well in the abſolute as limited Monarchy. It ſees alſo, that the abſolute Monarch is bound by the Lawes of God
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:155829:32"/>and nature, and by that duty of a Prince, which is upon him in order to that end, the ſafety of His people, and it cannot be ſatisfied how the breach of ſomething due by a civill agreement or Nationall poſitive Law ſhould more expoſe the ſo limited Monarch to this power or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, then thoſe outrages againſt the Lawes of God and Nature, againſt the very end of Government do the abſolute Monarch; It will not think if it may not reſiſt this for ſuch heinous provocations that it hath power to take Arms againſt the other for the breach of ſome li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties due to the people by a civill compact.</p>
               <p>If it bee replyed that the King is limited by ſuch a Condition as leaves power of reſiſtance in the people, reſerved to them in the firſt conſtitution: we anſwer, It has been cleared, that ſuch a Condition is a meer fiction and moſt unreaſonable, a ſeminary of Tumults and Sedition; The King is limited, yet not ſo, but (as above declared) by reaſon he cannot impoſe Laws by himſelfe upon his people.</p>
               <p>Now in particular of your Jewiſh Monarchy; How appeares it to be abſolute? we know thoſe Kings could not make any Laws either with or without the conſent of people, but were limited by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Laws which God gave them for that policy or Government; and me thinks that this man ſhould have conceived, it would make too much for the approving of abſolute Government in Kings, to ſay God ſet up an abſolute Monarchy over his people; and if it was the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God to entruſt his people with abſolute and unlimited Kings, why ſhould not Chriſtian Kings be truſted a little more then Subjects would now have them?</p>
               <p>But ſomething he ſayes by way of proofe that it was abſolute. <hi>The Jewes deſired to be governed after the manner of the Nations which was arbitrarily (as the Doctor obſerves out of</hi> Juſtine) <hi>and thereupon it is that God by</hi> Samuel <hi>tells them, what ſuch a King would doe to them, not what he might doe, as the Doctor ſeems to infer out of that place,</hi> pag. 21. To ſay the Doctor ſeems to infer ſo, is a groſſe miſtake, not to have been admitted by him, if he would have me or himſelf ſpeak any ſenſe; if I had inferred the Kings of the <hi>Iewes</hi> might doe ſo, my argument thence had been none; but I concluded it plainly to be unjuſt violence and oppreſſion, and thence ſhewed ſuch uſage of a people was not juſt cauſe of reſiſtance to them. As for his Argument, it concerned him to infer <hi>they might do ſo,</hi> or elſe how does he ſhew they had abſolute and arbitrary rule?</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:155829:32"/>
               <p>But his other inference from the Text is as good, <hi>That the people in deſiring to have Kings after the manner of the Nations, deſired to be governed arbitrarily, and that arbitrary government was ſet out in what</hi> Samuel <hi>declares their King would doe;</hi> As if the people here deſired to have a King to oppreſſe and ſpoile them, the thing they complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of in <hi>Samuels</hi> ſonnes, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. The truth is, the people deſired to have a King to <hi>judge them,</hi> we know in what meaning that phraſe <hi>(to judge them)</hi> is uſed in the booke of Judges, and explicated, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 10. <hi>viz.</hi> to goe in and but before them, to ſave them from their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and how that God had raiſed up hitherto Judges among them to that purpoſe: Now they deſire, not to have Judges extraordinarily ſent them as before, for they ſaw they lay long under oppreſſion ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times ere ſuch came, but to have a King among them as other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions had by an ordinary ſucceſſion, ſo they thought they ſhould not be to ſeeke upon all occaſions for one, to goe out before them againſt their Enemies; this is the ſumme of their deſire, not to have a King to Rule arbitrarily, to uſe them as he pleaſed, or as <hi>Samuel</hi> told them he would, nothing here to prove the Kings of the Jews were abſolute Monarches.</p>
               <p>The Monarchy of the Romans he tels us was abſolute too, by the conſent of the people, ſo doth M. <hi>Burrows</hi> alſo. And this is one of their Anſwers to the 13. to the <hi>Rom. They might not be reſiſted for they were abſolute Monarchs.</hi> It concerned them to bring proofe, for I had ſpoken to this in my other Treatiſe; here again this <hi>Fuller An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi> ſaith barely, they were abſolute Monarch's; and M. <hi>Burrowes</hi> ſaith it reſted upon me to prove they had not abſolute power, and ſo puts it off; Indeed in ſtrictneſſe of diſpute it is enough for the Anſwerer ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to affirm or deny, but in giving an exception to a place of Scripture by writing, and that for the ſatisfaction of Conſcience, it had beſeemed them to prove what they ſay, theirs being the affirmative, mine the Negative.</p>
               <p>I will therefore give my reaſons againſt it, that there was not ſuch a formall conſent on the peoples part, and ſuch a totall reſignation of themſelves to be governed by thoſe Emperours, as is required to make them lawfull abſolute Monarchs. Firſt, becauſe its altogether impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that a people ſo addicted to liberty ſhould ſo conſent to ſuch a ſubjection, and againe ſet up that <hi>Regiam poteſtatem,</hi> that abſolute Kingly power they ſo much hated; Therefore we ſee how <hi>Brutus</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:155829:33"/>and <hi>Caſſius</hi> were honoured for reſtoring their invaded liberty; and how againe they were ſenſible of that recovered liberty, when <hi>Nero</hi> was taken away; but they held it not, the Souldiers ſtill putting Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours upon them one after the other.</p>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe unto all the Lawes and Edicts of thoſe Emperors, there was required the conſent of the Senate and people of <hi>Rome;</hi> they could indeed force that conſent upon all occaſions, yet for forme of Law ſtill, <hi>Senatus Populuſque Romanus</hi> was added. Thirdly, we find in <hi>Suetonius</hi> how <hi>Caligula</hi> intended to aſſume the <hi>Diadem,</hi> (which was the Signe of that <hi>Regia poteſtas)</hi> that is, to profeſſe he would Raigne abſolutely; but He was diſſwaded by his friends.</p>
               <p>This therefore being certaine, that by force of Armes they made themſelves maſters of that people, my inference is, as it was in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Treatiſe, If the Senate and people of <hi>Rome,</hi> who a little before had the Supreame Government, might not reſiſt the then Emperors, that of Subjects had made themſelves Lords over that people, much leſſe can the people of this Land have power of reſiſtance, againſt the ſucceſſion of this Crown deſcending from the Conqueror, who by like force of Armes, but with more Juſtice, gained this Kingdome.</p>
               <p>But the Anſwerer excepts concerning our King. His <hi>Title of Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on waies excludes conſent, for it began in the election and conſent of the people, Tag.</hi> 21. The Roman Emperours by conſent of the people were abſolute (ſaith this man) and not to be reſiſted, our Kings by conſent of the people are ſo limited that the people have reſerved a power of reſiſtance; one as true as the other. If we begin the title of ſucceſſion from the Conqueſt, where is that election? that conſent, and reſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? if higher, we run Conſcience upon uncertainties; it cannot ſee how ſuch an Election ſhould give beginning to this Crown, but finds the beginnings ſtill in Armes, as the enterance of thoſe Emperors was; which beginnings might over-aw the conſent of the people (as he ſaith of the conſent of the Senate given to thoſe Emperors, that it might be <hi>an over-awed conſent)</hi> or elſe draw it; but cannot be imagined to ariſe from ſuch a capitulating Election ſuch a pre-contriving arbitrary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the people, as this man feignes.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>Burrowes</hi> is very angry that I call'd Election, a <hi>ſlender plea,</hi> and ſaith, I cannot get a better and ſurer claime for the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> Pag. 129. But he might have conſidered, I call'd it a <hi>ſlender plea,</hi> not fot ſucceſſion of a Crown, whenſoever it is made by a people that are
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:155829:33"/>free, as upon the failing of the Royall line, but for reſiſtance againſt it; it being all the plea that is made for theſe Arms, or power of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, and a ſlender one, becauſe it appears not how election gave beginning to this ſucceſſion, but that ſuch an election, &amp; contrive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the people reſerving the power of reſiſtance ſhould do it, is altogether improbable and unreaſonable.</p>
               <p>For the beginning of this ſucceſſion at the Conqueſt, &amp; the kings of <hi>England</hi> claiming from thence (againſt which M. <hi>Burrows</hi> here inveighs) ſee above, Sect. 6. and below, Sect. 11.</p>
               <p>The Fuller Anſwerer goes on with his replyes to the 13. to the <hi>Rom. If not written particularly to the</hi> Romans <hi>who were under an Abſolute Monarchy, and then not concerning us, yet ſuppoſe it referre to all Government in generall;</hi> pag. 21. I would this Anſwerer would leave his uncertainties, now he deals with conſcience; the reaſons the Apoſtle gives us in the 3.4, 5, 6. <hi>verſ.</hi> plainly ſhew it concerns all times and Government, ſo long as in all government there is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to be preſerved, there is a miniſter of God to execute Wrath, there is one that bears not the ſword in vain; reaſons eſſentiall to government, and perpetuall againſt reſiſtance, as was ſhewn in the former treatiſe, if this man would have pleaſed to take notice of them.</p>
               <p>Well, now that it refers to all Government, what then? <hi>It makes (ſaith he) altogether for us, it requires obedience to ordained powers, that is, legall commands, not wilfull pleaſures of Governours.</hi> True, but we would know, not what is required, but what is forbidden; we ſpake not of obedience, but resiſtance; we gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t active obedience is to be yielded to ordain'd powers, and denied to the illegall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; but we may resiſt their power, if they imploy it tomake good thoſe illegall commands? We muſt ſupply his Anſwer out of <hi>Mr. Burrows</hi> pag. 113. <hi>If one that is in authority command out of His own wil,</hi> I <hi>reſiſt no power, no authority at all, if</hi> I <hi>neither actively nor paſſve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obey.</hi> Alſo, <hi>we diſtinguiſh between the man that hath the power, and the power of the man, the power muſt not be reſiſted, the illegall will of the man may,</hi> and p. 124. <hi>the Apoſtle requires them not to reſiſt their power their</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>does not charge them not to reſiſt their Tyrannie.</hi> Between the power, and the perſon that bears it, as alſo between the power &amp; the illegall will, or the abuſe of the power, we may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh in conceit, abſtracting the one from the other, and by our
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:155829:34"/>active and paſſive obedience we may diſtinguiſh them, yielding this to the power &amp; perſon that bears it, denying that to his illegall will, but in reſiſtance wee cannot ſever them, for the reſiſting of him that bears the power, though unlawfully commanding, is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of the power alſo; it is plain by the Apoſtle, who ſpeaks not here of power abſtractly taken, for ſo it cannot be the objectof our obedience or reſiſtance, but Concretely as in the ſubject or the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate that bears it; therefore preſently it follows in the Apoſtles reaſons againſt reſiſtance, for <hi>he is the Miniſter, he beares the ſword;</hi> ſo St. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us what he meanes by the <hi>Ordinance the King as ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream, or they that are ſent by him;</hi> for though the will and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand be illegall, yet becauſe he that bears the power lawfully, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that power (though illegally) to compaſſe that will and execute that command, the power it ſelf is reſiſted in reſiſting him that ſo uſes it; as <hi>Saul</hi> had lawfully the power and command of Arms, but that power he uſes unlawfuly; in purſuing his unjuſt wil againſt <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid;</hi> And I aske, when theſe Emperours took away lives and goods at pleaſure, was that a pwoer ordained by God? no, but an illegall will, a Tyranny; therefore, according to M. <hi>Burrows,</hi> they might have been reſiſted in doing ſo; No, for that power and ſoveraignty they imployed to compaſſe thoſe illegal commands was a power or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained and ſettled in them. When <hi>Pilate</hi> condemned our Saviour it was an illegal will, yet our Saviour acknowledges in it <hi>Pilates</hi> pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that was given him from above.</p>
               <p>Again this anſwerer of theirs makes void that diſtinction of private men, and of publick ſtates in the point of reſiſtance, it voids alſo their other diſtinction of abſolute <hi>Monarchs,</hi> &amp; limited; For accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this anſwerer, it ſhalbe lawfull for private men to reſiſt their Princes, though abſolute, if they command illegally, and to ſay as M. <hi>Burrows</hi> teaches them; We reſiſt <hi>no power, no authority at all, but the illegall will and pleaſure of man;</hi> and ſo might the Chriſtians have reſiſted, and ſo replyed, if then anſwer be good.</p>
               <p>The truth is, the lawfull power is reſiſted, when armes are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt Princes abuſing that power to the compaſſing of unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full commands; which alſo I inſinuated often in the other treatiſe, &amp; that from the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> reaſons in this place againſt reſiſtance, drawn from that order, that good, for which the power is ordain'd, though then the execution of the power in thoſe Emperours was nothing anſwerable to that end.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:155829:34"/>
               <p>That which the fuller Anſwerer preſently adds pag. 22 <hi>There are two kinds of tyranny,</hi> Regiminis <hi>and</hi> Uſurpationis; <hi>that of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt be endured though never ſo heavy;</hi> Not only to the good but to the froward alſo, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18. <hi>That other of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation hath no right at all.</hi> I know not what it means, if it be not a plain confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of what I have ſayd againſt reſiſtance, and a direct confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what himſelfe and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Burrows</hi> has anſwered for it. M. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes</hi> alſo tels us, pag. 113. <hi>VVe profeſſe againſt reſiſting power and authority though abuſed.</hi> A man would think he came home to us, and ſo he muſt if he will ſpeak reaſon; but his device is, <hi>If thoſe who have power to make lawes ſhall make wicked lawes, and force obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to them, there is nothing left us but flying or paſſive obedience.</hi> In this hole he often lurks to defend himſelfe againſt the prohibition of reſiſtance, by making us believe the abuſed power, that muſt not be reſiſted, is only ſeen when ſinfull lawes are made and impoſed; but I ask, have they power to make ſuch Laws? No, for it is not of God; they have power from Him to make Laws, but ſuch Laws and Commands are their illegall wills; then may they that reſiſt ſay, in M. <hi>Burrowes</hi> words, <hi>we reſiſt no power, no authority, but the illegall wills of men. Pilate</hi> had power from above to judge the accuſed brought before him, not to condemne the innocent, that was the abuſe of the Legiſlative power; and the power it ſelfe is reſiſted by reſiſting the abuſe of the one, as of the other.</p>
               <p>Now all this has bin ſaid againſt reſiſtance, in caſe His Majeſties Commands, in the uſe of that power which is in Him, were unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; but <hi>Conſcience,</hi> that knows He ha's by Law a power to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand aſſiſtance for the defence of Himſelfe, and protection of His Subjects, will eaſily conclude it a Legall power and command, not only not to be reſiſted, but alſo to be actively obeyed, as all Legall &amp; ordained powers ought to be. Notwithſtanding theſe Scriptures ſo plain againſt Reſiſtance, or Arms taken up by Subjects, M. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes</hi> profeſſeth his Conſcience is not one whit ſcrupled; I hope he will better conſider it, ere he come to dye and give an account of thoſe poor ſouls he ha's ſeduced.</p>
               <p>Finally, we muſt ſubjoyn M. <hi>Bridge</hi> his replyes upon this 13 to the <hi>Romans,</hi> he, as if his conſcience were as little ſcrupled with the Apoſtles prohibiting, as M. <hi>Burrowes</hi> his was, thus begins. <hi>The</hi> Dr.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:155829:35"/>
                  <hi>indeavours to ſear the tender Conſcience with the word Damnation; but it is rather to be tranſlated judgement, &amp; by it, is meant the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Magiſtrate in this life,</hi> pag. 14. M. <hi>Bridge</hi> might have had reſpect to our tranſlation which renders it damnation, &amp; with good reaſon, for reſiſtance is a breach of the 5 Commandement, it is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of the ordinance of God, as in this chapter, and M. <hi>Bridge</hi> knows it is no vain ſcaring of Conſcience to tell it, the breach of Gods Commandement &amp; ordinance makes it guilty of damnation.</p>
               <p>And if we conſider the condition of the Chriſtians in thoſe times, what great matter had the Apoſtle told them, in aſſuring them they ſhould be puniſhed by thoſe Emperors if they reſiſted? when as they were ſure of that, whether they reſiſted or reſiſted not; but he gives them to underſtand, however thoſe Emperors were enemies to chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, the reſiſting of them was an offence againſt the ordinance of God: or if we conſider the principles of theſe daies, which teach people to take the ſword out of the Princes hand, &amp; ſeize the Arms of the Kingdom in order to their own preſervation, what great matter would the Apoſtle threaten to ſuch, in telling them they ſhould be puniſhed by the Mag ſtrate? when as they have provided for their indemnity by taking the ſword from their Prince, or cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Him to bear it in vain; therefore there is the ſtroke of a higher hand alſo to be expected, and thoſe that have been lately taken in actuall reſiſtance, and through His Majeſties mercy eſcaped the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved puniſhment of this life, muſt, if they continue not in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, look for a greater condemnation.</p>
               <p>Again, M. <hi>Bridge</hi> anſwers, <hi>That only active obedience to lawfull Commands is there enjoyned, not paſſive under unlawfull Commands,</hi> pag. 23. Both ſay we, as appears by the injunction of ſubjection &amp; prohibition of resiſtance; for if the Apoſtle had enjoyned onely obedience to juſt commands, he had given the <hi>Romans;</hi> that lived under ſuch unjuſt Emperors, but a lame inſtruction; the refore in eaſe they had unjuſt commands impoſed on them, he tels them how to behave themſelves, that is, not to resiſt: what then remains but paſſive obedience.</p>
               <p>But he would prove it thus, <hi>The power they were to be ſubject to, and not reſiſt; is the ordinance of God, and the miniſter of God for good: but when a Prince Commands a thing unlawfull, He is not ſo,</hi> pag. 23. <hi>Anſw.</hi> A lawfull Prince, though commanding unlawfully, is ſtill
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:155829:35"/>the miniſter of God for our good <hi>(i.e.)</hi> appointed for that end, and the power he is inveſted with, though abuſed to the execution of ſuch a command, is the ordinance of God; And that is it which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids our reſiſtance according to the Apoſtles reaſons here, which are taken not from the <hi>actuall miniſtration</hi> of any prince, as if we ought to obey when he commands juſtly, and might reſiſt when un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly, but from the <hi>end,</hi> for which God has ordain'd him to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter for our good; from which end though princes ſometime ſwerve (as theſe Emperors did uſually) yet are they not to be reſiſted, for that ſtrikes at the power and Ordinance it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Yea, M. <hi>Bridge</hi> a little after acknowledgeth, <hi>that inregard of their place they are Gods miniſters, but in regard of the unlawfull thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded they are not.</hi> Therefore when princes command unlawfully we muſt look upon them with a double regard, the one <hi>to the thing commanded,</hi> the other <hi>to their place,</hi> to the unlawfull command we muſt return a deniall of obedience, but in regard of their place uſe no reſiſtance. Deniall of obedience can ſever the illegall command from the place and power they bear, but reſiſtance cannot; for it cannot oppoſe the unlawfull command, but by uſurping the power, and invading the place God hath appointed them in.</p>
               <p>But M. <hi>Bridge</hi> concludes, <hi>It is the Doctors continuall miſtake to thinke the Apoſtle forbids the reſiſting of the higher powers in their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull commands, when as he forbids the reſiſting of them in things lawfull.</hi> We muſt beare with the importunity of theſe men, who wil not conceive the force of the Apoſtles reaſons, though laid op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n to their eyes, which was ſo often done in the former Treatiſe, that they tell me, I had worn the place thred bare, and yet they will not ſee the web and texture of it. Once more therefore; if the Aooſtle forbid reſiſtance only in things lawfull, it would not have bin a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient inſtruction, whether we reſpect the duty of ſubjection, which by this would not have bin directed, how to anſwer the unlawfull commands of Princes; or whether we conſider thoſe higher powers which then were tyrannicall, uſualy commanding things unlawfull; alſo this would have bin the way to leave the gap open to Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, for how eaſy would be the inference, therefore we may reſiſt, when they command unlawfully?</p>
               <p>Theſe Anſwerers it ſeems, are ſtill willing to keep the gap open, or elſe they might have ſeen how the Apoſtle brings reaſon enough
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:155829:36"/>to ſtop up the way againſt all reſiſting of power though abuſ'd, for he takes it not from the <hi>uſe</hi> of the power, but from the <hi>end</hi> for which God ordained it, the higher powers then being nothing anſwerable to that end, not miniſtring for good, but rather ſubverting of that which was good and juſt.</p>
               <p>We come now to the other ſcripture, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. <hi>To the King as ſupream, or unto Governours, as thoſe that are ſent by Him.</hi> Out of which was proved, that the higher power, in St. <hi>Paul,</hi> not to be reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by any, was the King in that ſtate; and that in this Kingdome All, who have power, fall under that diſtinction of St. <hi>Peter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſee how acutely M. <hi>Bridge</hi> replyes (for theſe men have ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity enough to abuſe the people) Dr. <hi>Bilſon</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>tels us by higher powers muſt be underſtood not onely Princes, but all publique States where the People or Nobles have the ſame intruſt to the ſword as princes have in this Kingdome. How then will the</hi> Dr. <hi>have the King only meant by theſe higher powers?</hi> As if the D. meant to prove that a King was the ſupream or higher power in the republicke of <hi>Vinice,</hi> or the Low-countries. <hi>But the</hi> Dr. <hi>acknowledges the</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>is the higheſt Court of juſtice, therefore they fall under theſe words, the higher powers.</hi> It is the higheſt Court, but you muſt not then exclude the king, in whom is the fountain of power; we farther grant, the two Houſes by themſelves doe alſo fall under the words <hi>higher powers</hi> in regard of the people, but not under the word <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream,</hi> ſo were thoſe, that were ſent by the Emperor, higher pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, yet ſubjects and inferior to him that is here called <hi>ſupream.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yea, but (as</hi> Calvin <hi>and other Interpreters tell us) the prononn (him) is referred to God by whom all in authority are ſent. ibid:</hi> 'Tis true, all are ſent by God, which might ſerve to check the bad conſtruction and uſe theſe men make of the foregoing words, <hi>every Ordinance of man.</hi> But it is as true, that the Governours of the provinces, where theſe ſcattered Chriſtians lived, unto whom St. <hi>Peter</hi> writes, were ſent by the King or Roman Emperor, and that he is here called <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream;</hi> which being a word including a relation, might have told M. <hi>Bridge,</hi> that al who had authority beſide in the Roman Empire, were inferiour to him, and immediatly ſent by him, though originally their power was alſo from God, or from above, as our Saviour ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth in <hi>Pilate</hi> the Governor of <hi>Judea</hi> under that Emperor.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Fuller Anſwerer</hi> replyes. <hi>The</hi> D. <hi>takes advantage in the words</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:155829:36"/>Supream <hi>and</hi> Sent, <hi>but the two Houſes are</hi> called, <hi>not</hi> ſent, <hi>a difference (at leaſt) as great as between</hi> to <hi>and</hi> from, <hi>Pag.</hi> 23. Very good. It ſeemes he will have the people ſuppream that ſends them from the Country to the King; ſo are the Clerks of the Convocation alſo ſent from them that chuſe them. We ſpeak not of Terms of place but Reaſons of Authority; if they be called by him, the authority is his, they come not of themſelves but at his call, &amp; therefore ſent by him.</p>
               <p>But he addes, <hi>They are a Coordinate part with him in the ſupream power, otherwiſe they could not hinder him from making Laws, nor finally declare Law without him, the two higheſt acts of ſupream power.</hi> Declare Law without him? then are they ſupreame without Him, and he is <hi>ſent</hi> by them, He muſt go and do as they declare; Can we think that he ſends for them with ſuch an intention? or that they, which are called to adviſe and conſent, come to ſuch a purpoſe, to do the buſineſſe without him? But enough of this feigned Coordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and of the Supremacy above, <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>SECT. X. <hi>A Confutation of what is replyed upon the third Section of the former Treatiſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AT the beginning of that third Section it was ſaid. The ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work of their Fundamentalls is this; Power is originally in &amp; from the people, therefore if the Prince intruſted with the power wil not diſcharge his truſt, it falls to the people to ſee to it, they may reaſſume the power and reſiſt. M. <hi>Bridge</hi> replyes. <hi>Then indeed it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth to the people to look to it, which they do as an act of ſelfe preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not of juriſdiction over their Prince, and this is not to reaſſume the power, or turn the Prince out of Office — as if we went about to depoſe our King, Pag.</hi> 52.53. For your act of ſelfe preſervation, and Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, we examined them above. <hi>Sect.</hi> 8. if we conſider what power of Law and Arms is now challenged &amp; uſurped by ſubjects, I think it cannot but appear to be a reſuming of the power entru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with the King (for it leaves him none) and a turning him out of office for the time, though you intend not to depoſe him, but to truſt him again, when and how you pleaſe.</p>
               <p>And according to M. <hi>Bridge</hi> his ſimilitude (ſo much uſed amongſt
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:155829:37"/>them) if the careleſſe ſteerſman, during the ſtorm, be made to ſtand by, and another ſet at the ſtern by the paſſengers, then is that ſteerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man out of office, or put from the execution of his office for the time but now for the application of this his ſimilitude: The Prince is not as the ſteerſeman (for he executes by his Miniſters) but as he that ſtands above and commands to the Star-bord or Lar-bord, &amp; if the Prince command amiſſe, that is contrary to the Law, His Miniſters under him for execution may deny actively to obey, and may give within the bounds of their place and office, direction according to the law and their oaths, this does not put him out of office.</p>
               <p>Then to that which was ſaid in the ſame <hi>Sect:</hi> That the governing power, as it is a ſufficiency of authority for command &amp; coercion running through every form of governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, is from God, though the limitations and qualifications of it for the ſeverall wayes of execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. it be of man by conſent: &amp; proved, <hi>Ro.</hi> 13.1. <hi>The powers that are &amp;c. M. Bridge</hi> replies. <hi>None denieth it,</hi> only he will make it incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with what was ſaid before. But if none deny it, why then up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this principle of <hi>derivation of power</hi> from the people, do you ground your resiſtance? for in doing ſo, what power or ſufficiency of authority for command or coercion, do you leave your Prince, the thing he has received (as you deny not) from God alone?</p>
               <p>But let us ſee how its inconsiſtent. <hi>By thoſe words, The powers are of God,</hi> Rom. 13.1.1. <hi>the D. muſt underſtand the power it ſelfe of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy, diſtinguiſhed from the qualifications thereof, and the perſon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned thereto, how then did he ſay,</hi> Sect. 2. <hi>that the higher power in</hi> Paul <hi>is the ſame with the King as ſupream in</hi> Peter? <hi>Anſ.</hi> The power of Magiſtracy, abſtractively taken, may be theſe words be proved to be of God, though the higher powers here be underſtood concrete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with connotation of the perſons that bear the power, for they are here propoſed as objects of our obedience, which cannot be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected but upon power in ſome perſon, and here it's ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the powers that are,</hi> now power cannot be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> exiſtent, but in ſome perſon. Yet do theſe words prove the power it ſelfe to be of God, for why elſe ſhould theſe Magiſtrates or Princes choſen by the people be ſaid to be powers ordained of God, but becauſe the power and authority they bore was from God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In like manner the Dr. proves the power is of God, becauſe the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate is called the miniſter of God, ſlipping from the power it ſelf to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:155829:37"/>the Perſon deſigned to the power, for the power it ſelfe is not called the miniſter of God.</hi> Good ſtuffe. I muſt come home to M, <hi>Bridge</hi> to make him underſtand the force of my inference; The Major of <hi>Norwich</hi> is the Kings Miniſter, therefore his power is from the King; will M. <hi>Brigde</hi> reply, no, for the power it ſelf is not the Major, or call'd the Miniſter of the King.</p>
               <p>Then the Anſwerers come to the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Peter, the Ordinance of man,</hi> which in the former Treatiſe was ſaid to be taken <hi>ſubjectively</hi> in regard of the power it ſelfe, which is from God <hi>cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally,</hi> and placed in man as the Subject; and if there be in that phraſe any cauſality, or Creation, or invention of man implyed, it is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the qualifications and ſeverall wayes of executing that power in ſeverall formes of Government. Hereupon the <hi>Fuller An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi> and M. <hi>Bridge</hi> every where takes it for granted by me, that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, Ariſtocracry and Democracy, are equally the inventions of man, which followes not, as was explained above, <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. concerning the originall of the governing power, and the firſt beginning of Monarchy.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, M. <hi>Bridge</hi> concludes, that my proving of the governing power to be of God, but the qualifications of it &amp; the deſignation of the perſon to be of man, gaineth nothing againſt reſiſtance, or depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of a Prince that doth not diſcharge his truſt; <hi>for ſtil the peoplemay ſay, we may alter the government, and depoſe the Perſon, becauſe he was of our deſigning, Pag.</hi> 55. Nothing ſo, for if they reſiſt they uſurp a power that God ha's not given them, and invade the power that God ha's given Him; if they depoſe Him, they quite take away that pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er which God, and not they, placed in Him, for although they ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and deſgned the Perſon, yet is He the Miniſter of God, &amp; from God he ha's His Power and Commiſſion; as if Citizens ſhould take upon them to turn the Major, that ha's his power and Commiſſion from the King, out of office, becauſe they choſe him. For altering the government, unleſſe they be altogether free (as upon the utter failing of the Royall Line) they cannot doe it, no nor alter any Lawes or qualifications of the governing power, for they were not made by them alone, but alſo, and cheifly, by the conſent and authority of the Prince.</p>
               <p>Vpon that place, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82. <hi>I have ſaid yee are Gods,</hi> alleadged in the former Treatiſe, <hi>the Fuller Anſwerer</hi> replyes, <hi>all Rulers are Gods
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:155829:38"/>alike, that word of God comes to them All alike, to</hi> Pilate <hi>as well as</hi> Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar, <hi>pag.</hi> 24. This text was brought to prove the governing power was derived from God, becauſe Rulers were ſo called, as His Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerents, as having their Commiſſion from Him, and in his ſtead over the people, this was urged to take off the derivation of that power from the people. He Anſwers, <hi>Inferiour Magiſtrates are Gods too;</hi> that's nothing to the purpoſe, but <hi>Gods alike,</hi> that's plainly falſe; for that word and power comes firſt to the Supream, and from Him to them that are <hi>ſent</hi> by Him, <hi>from Caeſar to Pilate.</hi> Inferiour Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates are as Gods to the people under them, but the <hi>Supream</hi> as a God to thoſe Gods; <hi>Aaron</hi> was ſo to the people, but <hi>Moſes</hi> was as God to <hi>Aaron,</hi> Exod. 4.16.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XI. <hi>A Confutation of what is replyed upon the fourth Section in the former Treatiſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HIs fourth Section</hi> (ſaith the Fuller Anſwerer) <hi>is ſpent againſt the Peoples reaſſuming the power be truſted to the King, which no man maintaines; what need they reaſſume that, which in the firſt conſtitution of Government they reſerved? pag.</hi> 24. This man ha's often told us, the power of Arms is ordinarily intruſted to the King, &amp; that by the people in the firſt Conſtitution of government to uſe it for the ſafety of the State. VVell, He does not uſe it ſo, as they conceive; they therefore diſpoſe of it, taking the Sword into their own hands, what is this but a reaſſuming, or (which is worſe and more unreaſonable) an uſing of an higher power reſerved and inherent in themſelves; which is to place the very Supremacie in the people, as ha's been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſhewen above.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>Bridge</hi> beſtowes more labour upon this Section; But firſt He complaines, <hi>The D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> charges us, that we hold the people may reaſſume the power entruſted to the Prince, making the World beleive we contend for the depoſing of Kings, pag.</hi> 24. What ſome of you have contended for all this while, the Lord knowes, that knowes your Hearts, yet this we know, the ſame principles will carry you ſo farre. But there is a difference between depoſing the Prince, and reaſſuming the power; for though you have not depoſed the King, yet have you ſeized the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:155829:38"/>
                  <hi>Militia;</hi> and Armes of the Kingdome, have commanded obedience from all His people, have left Him nothing ye could take from Him, and what is this but, as much as in youlyeth, to <hi>reaſſume the power?</hi> if there be any impropriety in the ſpeech, it is in calling that a <hi>reaſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming,</hi> which indeed is rather a taking away or diſpoyling Him of that, you never gave Him.</p>
               <p>But if you doe not reaſſume the power, what meanes the difference you make of things diſpoſed by truſt, from things diſpoſed by dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe they may be recalled, theſe may not; ſo you ſay, <hi>Pag.</hi> 25. and in applying it, you tell us the King ha's His Power by truſt from the people, and ſhould have proceeded to confeſſe, they may recall <hi>(i. e.)</hi> reaſſume it, you muſt hold it, if you hold to your principles.</p>
               <p>But let me tell you, that God entruſts the Prince with the power, and with the people, and therefore the people cannot reaſſume it, And when they elect one to bear that power, they doe commit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to his truſt, not giving ſo much as receiving a benefit; and ſuch elected Kings (as was ſaid in the former Treatiſe) are the Lords An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed and his Miniſters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then cannot Princes, whoſe coming to the Crowne is meerly Pactio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, be depoſed, for they are alſo the Lords Annointed and his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, but the Doctor granted, that the argument (ſpeaking of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture of the Princes power) has force in Governmente meerly Elective and Pactionall, Pag.</hi> 26. The Doctor by way of ſuppoſition paſſed it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in theſe words (although ſuch argument may ſeeme to have ſome force in ſtates meerly Pactionall) to the undenyable clearing of this State from the danger of ſuch forfeiture. But if M. <hi>Bridge</hi> will have me deliver my opinion abſolutely, the reaſons above mentioned will not ſuffer me to thinke, the people may depoſe any King they have choſen, upon what conditions ſoever they admitted him; and if they ſhould chuſe &amp; admit one upon ſuch condition of forfeiture it were <hi>turpis Conditio,</hi> moſt unreaſonable, the very Seminary of Jealouſy and ſedition; neither profitable for King nor people, a plain encroachment of the peorle upon the governing power, which was at firſt derived from God not through their hands, and ſhould alwayes be left in the Governour ſufficient to rule them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Doctor alſo confeſſeth, it is probable that Kings at firſt were by election here as elſewhere, yet will he not have the King claime by it, pag.</hi> 27. It is like they were ſo, as generally among the Heathen they
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:155829:39"/>began by election; what then? muſt our King now claime by the firſt Kings in this Land? and Conſcience be put to drive into the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure fabulous times before <hi>Caeſar</hi> or <hi>Brute</hi> his entrance, for that firſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection? We are upon the Engliſh government, which followed the <hi>Saxons,</hi> or rather upon the <hi>Norman</hi> which followed the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt; and as I ſaid in that place, how can Conſcience be ſatisfied, that the argument drawn from the ſuppoſed firſt Election to prove the peoples aſſuming this power, can have any force in this govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which began not ſo, but as we ſee by the entrance of the <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and <hi>Normans: Thus it is with our Prince, although he ſucceeded the Conqueror, yet doth he alſo take in the voluntary and free conſent of the Commonwealth unto His Crowne, pag.</hi> 28. That was not the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the firſt ſuppoſed election, but an after Conſent following the Conqueſt, as the Prince and the People could agree, which agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was not likely to leave them a power of reſiſtance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now we ſee the Doctors mind plainly that he contends for an Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary government, for he ſaith, pag.</hi> 11. <hi>the Emperors ruied abſolutely and arbitrarily, and here he ſaith, how came they of Subjects to be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Manarchs, but by force of Armes, the way that the Saxons and Normans made themſelves Maſters of this people?</hi> The Doctor did not contend for an arbitrary government, but did often (becauſe he knew he ſhould meet with thoſe that would made bad conſtruction of his words) expreſly declare the contrary; His intent was to anſwer the Reply there made (that thoſe Emperors might not be reſiſted becauſe they were abſolute) by ſhewing they made themſelves ſo by Armes; and if the people could not upon any former right re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſt in that Empire, no more can they doe in this, upon pretence of right by a firſt election, for here alſo the Government began in Armes. None of my Adverſaries have bitten at the edge and ſtrength of this anſwer, but only catched at the ſhadow of thoſe two words <hi>Conqueſt</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary.</hi> More was ſpoken above of Conqueſt, Sect. 6. and this I may adde, We ſee in the titles of many of our Kings before the Acts of Parliament made in their times, a reference to the Conqueſt, as <hi>Edward the third after the Conqueſt,</hi> which does relate not only to the <hi>Edward</hi> before the Conqueſt, but alſo to the Conqueſt it ſelfe, as to a beginning of claime and government, or elſe the number ſhould have none on, and our <hi>Edward</hi> the third ſhould have been numbred the fourth. So <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeaventh, and <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, after the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:155829:39"/>queſt, which relates to no ſuch name before, but only to the Conqueſt as a beginning of Claime and Government.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then the Doctor comes to the matter of Covenant, to which we ſay, Every breach of Covenant makes not a forfeiture, but we eſteem a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of a Covenant, which we ſee in Kings deſigned by God,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.3. <hi>and that this bindes as well the King to the People, as the People to the King, pag.</hi> 29. That Covenant was not there a Condition on which thoſe Kings were admitted to the Crown, no more is it in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but a confirmation and ſtrengthning of their naturall duties by promiſes and Oaths. That every breach the Prince makes in that Covenant ſhould forfeit his power, you cannot ſay indeed for ſhame, but you canenlarge the breach as you pleaſe til you have made it wide enough for Armies of ſeduced people to enter in upon Him. And we cannot but obſerve, how you prepare for it in thoſe words, <hi>the King as well bound to the people,</hi> that is, they ſtand equally accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptable to each other; for you immediately inferre, <hi>Therefore it is as well unlawfull for a King by force to oppreſſe His Subjects &amp; to take up Arms againſt them, as for Subjects to take up Arms againſt him.</hi> Both are unlawfull and unjuſt, but not equally; for doe not the mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all duties of the fifth Commandement run betwixt ſuperior and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior? and is it as heinous for the father to ſtrike the ſonne, as the ſon to lift up his hand againſt the Father? If a King oppreſſe His Subjects, it is an abuſing of that power which is in him, if people take Armes it's an uſurping of power that belongs not to them, which is of more dangerous conſequence; if the people doe what is unlawfull, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate bears not the ſword in vain, God has appointed him to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them; if the Supream Magiſtrate doe unlawfully, he is not to be puniſhed by the people (for that were to overthrow the order God has ſet) but is reſerved for a Divine judgement.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the Covenant twixt King and People though it be not expreſſed, that the ſtate of the Kingdome may take Armes and provide for its ſafety, in eaſe the King will not diſcharge, yet muſt it in all reaſon be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, that ſafety being the end of that truſt, and ratio Legis is Lex; as in Marriage it is not verbally expreſſed, that the party committing A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery ſhall he divorced, yet that Covenant carries the force of ſuch a Condition,</hi> pag. 31. That the King ought to diſcharge is Law, and the end or reaſon of it is the ſafety of the ſtate, but that, in caſe he does not, or not according to the opinion of the people, they by Armes
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:155829:40"/>ſhould reſiſt &amp; provide for it, is neit her Law nor Reaſon of any Law, but an unreaſonable condition, were any King admitted under it, and no rea onable means of ſafety, but the way of confuſion and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as experience has alwayes ſhewn.</p>
               <p>That Adultery is the breach of the Mariage Covenant and cauſe of Divorce, both in the inſtitution of Marriage, <hi>They two ſhall be one fleſh,</hi> doth in reaſon imply, and the Law of God doth expreſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare; and the like implication of reaſon and declaration of Law muſt appear, before we can ſee any warrant for Subjects to reſiſt and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for their own ſafety: for as of the parties married, ſo of a Prince and the people entruſted to him by God, it may be ſaid; <hi>whom God hath enjoyned let no man put aſunder;</hi> and <hi>let not the woman uſurp au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over the man,</hi> nor Subjects over their Prince.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XII. <hi>A Confutation of what was replied upon the</hi> 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>Sect: of the former Treatiſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VPon that which was ſaid, They ſharpenmany weapons for this reſiſtance at the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> forge, borrow arguments from the Papiſts, M. <hi>Bridge</hi> replyes, <hi>There is much difference betweene them and us in this particular.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>The Papiſts contend for the Lawfulneſſe of depoſing Kings, wee not.</hi> Difference there muſt needs be betweene you in this particular, for they Challenge ſuch a power for the Pope, you for the people. But you doe not contend for the power of depoſing, or as you told us above, the people from their power of reſiſtance need not make that inference; here is great ſecurity for the Prince. We ſee your party making uſe of thoſe Examples, which the Papiſts bring for the depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Kings, as that of <hi>Saul, Vzziah, Athalia,</hi> and one of your fellow Anſwerers has endeavoured to prove ſuch a power of depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing (with whom we ſhall meet at the end of this Section;) and we know your principles wil carry the people ſo far if they wil follow them, if, as you teach them, they have juſtly taken Armes in order to their own ſafety, ſo they ſhall thinke in order to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>fety they cannot lay them downe, or any longer truſt their ſafety with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Prince.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:155829:40"/>II. <hi>The Papiſts plead for power of depoſing a Prince in caſe he turn Heretick, we hold a Prince may change his Religion, and yet the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects thereby not excuſed from their Allegiance.</hi> You will give him leave to change Religion himſelfe, ſo will the Papiſts, if all His Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects may have free liberty of their Religion; but in caſe he alſo ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avour to force that contrary Religion upon his Subjects (for that muſt be ſuppoſed) how then will your Allegiance hold? When you chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the power of Armes in order to your own and the States ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, will you think that the preſervation onely of your goods, Eſtates and out ward liberty is concerned in it, and not of your Religion too? How have you wrought the people into Armes againſt their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne but by this name <hi>Religion?</hi> and that, not becauſe He is turn'd Heretique and changed his Religion, or has impoſed a Contrary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion upon his Subjects, (that you could not tell them) but only by making them beleive He favours Popery, and there is feare He will change Religion; which is as weak and low pretence as any Ieſuit can deſcend to for drawing People into Armes againſt their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne.</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>The Papiſts hold it lawfull to kill a Prince, and that a private man inveſted with the Popes Authority may do it; We abhore it.</hi> That is their new forge under ground, ſet up of late by Ieſuits; I did not mean you ſharpned your weapons there, but at the old forge, where the Popes power of acquitting people of their Allegiance, and commanding them into Armes has been beaten out ſome hundreds of years. And however you ſay you abhor this Doctrine of killing Kings, that is, of Butchering them by privat hands, yet I feare, and tremble to think, if your Soveraigne had falne in Battell by the edge of your ſword or ſhot of your Artillery, yee would have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted your ſelves, and found him guilty of his own death, in that he would not, being deſired, forbeare to go down himſelfe into Battel againſt his Enemyes. Some of your Fellowes, M. <hi>Bridge,</hi> are much wronged, if they did not after the buſineſſe of <hi>Brainceford,</hi> play the Popes in abſolving the Souldiers, there taken, from the Oath, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they had again bound themſelves from bearing Armes againſt his <hi>Majeſty;</hi> and I can witneſſe how the beſt of your party in <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> had plited their faith for conſerving of the Pea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of the Country, and how they were diſpenſed with and commanded into Armes.</p>
               <p>Let us proceed. The <hi>Fuller Anſwerer</hi> alſo complaines, <hi>The fift Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:155829:41"/>is a plain begging of three Queſtions the Reſolver would have us maintain, Pag.</hi> 25. To pardon your abuſe of ſpeech, we know what you mean, and muſt tell you, we need not put upon you more then you undertake to maintain, which is more then you can prove, more then former Ages have been Conſcious of, enough to make your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, if you have any, heare ill in after times. But let us ſee what you ſay in vindication of your ſelves. <hi>We ſay not that every State hath theſe meancs of ſafety by reſiſtance unleſſe reſerved by them.</hi> Anſwer, Yet is the ſafety of every State as deare and heare to it ſelfe, as This; and for any thing you have ſhewn for it, any State may pretend ſuch a Reſervation, as well as This; for you have not proved ſuch a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, and the generall argument, your Party uſeth, is from ſelfe preſervation, which is common to all.</p>
               <p>Then to the Argument of the Churches ſafety, (under pretence of which the Pope challenges a power upon the failing of the Civill Magiſtate, as the people now upon the refuſall of their Prince) you ſay <hi>The Church is not a State by it ſelfe,</hi> ſo alſo M. <hi>Burrowes</hi> and M. <hi>Bridge.</hi> It is not indeed the whole State, comprehending the Civill State too, yet is the good Eſtate thereof, of as great conſequence as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Concernment of the body Politique. <hi>But the Church is not of its own Conſtitution but of Chriſts.</hi> What then? therefore it muſt be preſerved by the laws inſtituted by Chriſt; true, ſo muſt the Civill State by its eſtabliſhed lawes, we deſire no more; yet will you not give Him leave to be as carefull for the good Eſtate of His Church, in providing meanes of preſervation for it, in caſe the Civill Magiſtrate faile in his truſt, as you are to provide or reſerve this power of reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance upon the Kings refuſall? But he did not provide ſuch forceable meanes as are challenged by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> under that pretence; and theſe meanes of a reſerved power for reſiſtance are as unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble on your part: if both of you ſhould be put to prove your Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, He for his Excommunicating or depoſing of Kings in order to the Churches ſafety, and you for your reſerved power of reſiſtance in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the States preſervation, Conſcience would find as little ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in the one as in the other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As for the matter of the Church, we turn</hi> (ſaith M. <hi>Bridge,</hi> pag. 33.) <hi>the Doctors argument upon himſelfe, thus. If the Church cannot be preſerved where the officer is an Heretick, unleſſe it has power to reject him, neither can a Kingdome; when the officer is unfaithfull, unleſſe it
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:155829:41"/>has power to reject him, neither can a Kingdome, when the Officer is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull, unleſſe it has power either to depoſe Him, or to looke to it ſelfe.</hi> It was not my argument; I did but ſhew how the Papiſts uſe the like argument for the Churches ſafety, as you doe for the States; and if you back again wil gather ſtrength for your aſſertion from their reaſons, be as like as you will one to the other, I cannot helpe it, but I am for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for you (at leaſt for the Religion you profeſſe) that you are put to ſuch ſhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts. <hi>But the Church hath Excommunication granted to it by Chriſt for its own preſervation from Evills and Errors; and the Body Naturall hath power to deliver it ſelfe from its burden, therefore the Common wealth alſo cannot preſerve it ſelf, unleſſe it have power to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it ſelfe from its burden, ibid.</hi> Then has this Church a Power of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication ſtill; ſo it ſhould be indeed, and the power cannot be taken away by any mortal authority; but ſince the Act, which tooke away the High Commiſſion, and (as the party, you plead for, would have it interpreted) all Eccleſiaſticall Cenſure too, where doth the Exerciſe of that power reſt? upon whom now is the Argument turned?</p>
               <p>The Body Naturall has power to disburden it ſelf, ſo has the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth too, but wil you have the naturall body disburden it ſelf of the Head, or worke without it, and ſay <hi>I have no neede of thee?</hi> Or will you uſe letting of blood for the disburdning of the Natural body, when ſweating or gentle purges may doe it? So in the Body Politick, when a calme Reformation may purge out noxious humors, will you put the ſword into the rough hand of the people, which in ſtead of opening a veine will cut the Arteries and Sinewes of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth? Ye are too deſperate Phyſitians, and that is plainly ſeene by the Conſumption and languiſhing Eſtate of this Kingdom.</p>
               <p>It was urged in the former Treatiſe, as a reaſon againſt theſe meanes of ſafety by this power of reſiſtance. (If the repreſentative body of the people upon the Kings ſailing in His truſt, may take this power, then may the multitude by the like rule, upon the failing of their repreſentatives in the diſcharge of the truſt they were choſen for, take the power to themſelves, for it is claimed by them) the <hi>Fuller Anſwerer</hi> replies, <hi>They cannot doe it, for the people have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorved any power to themſelves from themſelves in Parliament,</hi> pag. 25. But it will be as hard for him to make them believe they have power no otherwiſe, as to make it appeare to us, there was any ſuch power
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:155829:42"/>reſerved at all; for when the people come to be ſpoiled in their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates and Liberties, they will think it moſt unreaſonable, that they ſhould entruſt themſelves, and all they have, to ſuch Arbitrary diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of their own Repreſentatives; eſpecially having been taught by this rule ſo eaſily to diſclaime the Truſt of their Soveraigne.</p>
               <p>He that wrote the book called <hi>Plain Engliſh,</hi> ſaith expreſly, that if the Repreſentative body cannot or will not diſcharge their truſt to the ſatisfaction of reaſon in the people, they may reſume (if ever yet they parted with a power to their manifeſt undoing) and uſe their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ſo far as conduceth to their owne ſafety; and M. <hi>Bridge</hi> (though here he brings reaſons againſt the peoples recalling their Truſt given to their repreſentative body, yet) by his argument of ſelfe preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation at the beginning of his book, has taught them to ſay, It is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall for them to provide for themſelves, and the act of Truſt given to their Repreſentative body is but by <hi>poſitive</hi> Law, and cannot deſtroy the <hi>Naturall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But forgetting what he ſaid of the Naturall Law of ſelfe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, he gives us reaſons why the people ſhould not take the power in ſuch a caſe. 1. <hi>Becauſe they cannot be ſo ready to think the Parliament</hi> (that is, the two Houſes) <hi>neglect their truſt,</hi> pag. 36. not think ſo? but if by Ordinances thence iſſuing, they be ſpoiled of their property and liberty (which is ſuppoſed in the Caſe) they will quickly feele it is ſo. 2. <hi>Becauſe there is not that actuall deſigning and election af the Prince to the preſent affairs of the Commonweal, as there is of the Parliament men choſen for theſe particular buſineſſes.</hi> This is bold, and ſets aſide both King and houſe of Lords, putting all upon the <hi>Sentence</hi> of thoſe that are <hi>choſen by the people for the preſent affaires of the Kingdom,</hi> thoſe are his words; and unto their ſentence the people bind themſelves to ſtand as parties diſagreeing to doe the ſentence of an <hi>Vmpire</hi> or <hi>Arbitrator,</hi> that is his ſimilitude. What can be ſaid more to the diſſolving of the temper of three Eſtates in Parliament, and to the overthrow of this Government? 3. <hi>Becauſe if the people, upon ſuch ſurmiſes, ſhould call in their truſt and their power, they would leave themſelves naked of all authority, and be private men.</hi> pag. 37. Naked of all authority? to doe what? to take up Arms? that muſt be your meaning; but what authority had they before the King cals them together? were they any other then private men? or does he by call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them give them authority to take Arms againſt him? And if the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:155829:42"/>people ſhould recall their truſt, why ſhould they think themſelves in that condition more private men, then they were when at firſt (as you ſuppoſe) they elected a King? did they then being private men give (as you maintain) all power of Government, and will they conceive they cannot now uſe any? will they not as eaſily conclude they may free themſelves from their Truſt given to thoſe Parliament men choſen by them, as renounce, according to your leſſons, their Truſt given to their Prince? in all reaſon they will hold their Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives more accountable to them, then their Prince can be; who is entruſted for them immediately by God and themſelves.</p>
               <p>To this we may adde what he replies to the ſame purpoſe, pag. 42. <hi>The people doe all acknowledge that we are to be governed by Lawes,</hi> And they feel the want of it, and doe earneſtly deſire they may once again ſee this Kingdome ſo happy; <hi>Now the Parliament</hi> (as the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor ſaith) <hi>is the Iudge what is Law.</hi> He never ſaid ſo, unleſſe you mean the three Eſtates of Parliament; <hi>How then can the People think the Parliament doth any thing contrary to Low, when they are the Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of it?</hi> This is to make them Arbitrary; and all their commands Lawes, and to lead the people after them by an implicit faith; But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of the power of declaring Law, and of theſe Arbitrary com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, Sect. 6. &amp; 7.</p>
               <p>Finally, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Bridge</hi> endeavours to ſhew how they can anſwer the Oath of Supremacie, and the Proteſtation, by taking of Arms. <hi>If the Popiſh party ſhould prevail, who knowes not that they will force the King to another Supremacie, or quickly make an hand of Him,</hi> Pag. 44. But who knowes not that the King (by Gods bleſſing) may prevail in the maintenance of His Crowne and Right (for which he is now forced to fight) without any prevailing of the Popiſh party? And who knowes not, if that party of Browniſts and Anabaptiſts (which are now ſo prevalent in the Arms taken up againſt the King) ſhould get the upper hand, what would become of the Kings Supremacy and this Government?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the Oath of Supremacie we Sweare Him our Soveraigne to be Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream, in oppoſition to the Pope, or any other particular perſon. How doth our Doctrine or Practice infringe this, ibid.</hi> Is this all you can ſay for your Soveraignes ſupremacie? the Declaration of Parliament (as was ſhewn, Sect. 4.) teaches you another Doctrine, that He is Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream not ſo much in oppoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to particular Perſons, as in relation to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:155829:43"/>the whole <hi>Body Politick</hi> of which he is the <hi>Head,</hi> and accordingly you ſhould regulate your practice and obedience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In our Proteſtation we proteſt to defend the Kings Perſon, and hom can we ſay with a good Conſcience we do it, if we do not take up Arms in this time of Popiſh inſurrection? ibid.</hi> you proteſt alſo to defend his Honour and Rights, which your Armes invade. And if the comming in of ſome Papiſts, in the duty of Allegiance, to His aid againſt your violences may be called a popiſh inſurrection, (as you have the Art to make all things ſeem odious on the Kings part) it was cauſed by your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing up Arms firſt, which the next Age will truly call an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or can we (if we take not Arms) in Conſcience ſay, we defend the Priviledge of Parliament in bringing in Delinquents to their Tryall, or the liberty of the Subject, or the truth of Religion? I preſume every good man that makes conſcience of his wayes, will not be backward to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance this publique deſigne.</hi> You cannot in conſcience ſay, but you have had the ſecurity of all thoſe particulars offered and promiſed &amp; might have had them better aſſured without your taking Armes, if you had not ſome farther reach in your <hi>Publick deſign.</hi> However you can overrule your own, and your Peoples conſcience, yet all good men, that ſeriouſly conſider your wayes, cannot but conceive, the priviledges of Paraliment, Liberty of the Subject, and truth of Religion have ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red moſt by this your pretended defence of them.</p>
               <p>And now it is high time I ſay ſomething (there need not much) to the Anſwerer that would not be known by his name, but would be noted by his Margin painted with Greek and Latin. He begins with Scripture, but ſtaies not long upon it, ſpeaking indeed leſſe from that, then any of the other Anſwerers to whom I have already replyed. He inſiſts chiefly upon the grounds of Reaſon borrowed from <hi>Aniſtotle,</hi> out of whom he would prove ſeverall concluſions; thoſe, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern us, are touching elective Kingdoms, touching a power in the State to bring Kings to an account, and to depoſe a Tyrant.</p>
               <p>We reply to what he has brought out of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> touching thoſe particulars; The Philoſophers reaſons may be good and uſefull in the founding of a Government, but muſt they therefore obtain in this that is founded? If <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> like of Kingdoms that goe by choice, and approve the power which the <hi>Ephori</hi> had over their Kings in <hi>Sparta,</hi> would this man have it ſo here? Let him ſpeak his Treaſon plainly in
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:155829:43"/>his own, not <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> words, and ſay, He would have a new Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Kings here made by choyce, and ſome <hi>Ephori</hi> ſet over them; ſurely he thought, as many moe did, of a new erection, and had fitted himſelfe to give advice for it out of <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> But however that Philiſopher gives us many fine hints of Politicall prudence, if this man were put to it, to draw up that frame of that Government, which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſeemes to approve, and by piece-meal to deliver, he would find the task very difficult, and we the Government very ſtrange, ſuch as I believe, never was nor will be, deſerving almoſt as well to goe into the Proverb, as his maſter <hi>Plato's</hi> did; as for example, He would have Government goe by choyce, and that choyce to follow excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, now ſeeing excellency, as he notes in 3. <hi>Pol.</hi> is in Riches, or Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or Nobility, or Virtue, we cannot ſee now he provides for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting of thoſe which excell in Riches, Power, or Nobility, that facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may be prevented, and yet they, that excell in virtue, to carry the Government and be willingly obeyed of all, as he would have it in that book; but where and when will it be ſo unleſſe in <hi>Plato's</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth?</p>
               <p>Well; <hi>Ariſtotle's</hi> reaſon may be good, and yet my reaſons, in the 5. Sect. of the former Treatiſe againſt this power of reſiſtance now aſſumed, ſtand firm too; why? becauſe if that power be uſed to bring this Government into ſuch a Mould, as this man phanſies out of <hi>Ariſtole,</hi> can we expect any thing but a ſucceſſion of Givill war? for will it not alwaies be more juſt for the Prince to endeavour the recovery of his Rights and power, where with he is inveſted by law, then it was for Subjects to force him from them? and this is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who ſpeaking of Kings in Barbarous Nations that have a power very neare to Tyranny, thoſe Kingdomes, ſaith he, <hi>have their ſecurity, becauſe the Government is eſtabliſhed by law and the Cuſtom of the Nation. l.</hi> 3. <hi>pol. c.</hi> 14. Will this man then have <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotl's</hi> reaſons, belonging to ſuch Governments as he deſcribed, take place here againſt the Regall power eſtabliſhed by law and the Cuſtom of the Nation? which eſtabliſhment might give us <hi>Security</hi> too, but for ſuch unquiet ſpirits as this man pleads for.</p>
               <p>One ſtep farther; this Anſwerer has alſo a long plea againſt, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, for the forceable bringing them to account and taking them away, upon which, after he has ſpent many pages, he layes the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion thus, It is lawfull for the Kingdom to depoſe a Tyrant, <hi>Pag.</hi>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:155829:44"/>25. but many of his proofes ſeem to allow, it may be don by aſſaſſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; I will not ſay it is his opinion, but he tells us of the praiſe of <hi>Caſſius</hi> and <hi>Brutus,</hi> that they were <hi>Romanorum Vltimi,</hi> and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtyles ſome, in reſiſtance now againſt the King, <hi>Anglorum Vltimos:</hi> he ſpeakes of the taking away of <hi>Caligua, Nero, Domitian,</hi> of the ſentence of <hi>Plotinus, Evil Kings rule by the Cowardlines of their Subjects,</hi> of which more below; ſo that the people had need to uſe more diſcretion in refuſing ſuch inſtances, then this man did in alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them; but if it muſt be done by depoſing, his fellow Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are againſt it: and for the two Parliaments which he cites, the <hi>Obſervatour</hi> tells us, <hi>No King was ever depoſed by a free Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> let this man make the application.</p>
               <p>He tells me he cannot find what I ſpoke out of <hi>Tertullian</hi> his Apol. yet cites me words within two lines of it. It runs thus in the Author, <hi>Si hoſtes, non tantum vindices occultos agere vellemus, deeſſet nobis vis numerorum &amp; Copiarum? Veſtra omnia implevimus, urbes, inſulas, Caſtella, Caſtra; Cui bello non idonei, non prompti fuiſſemus, etiam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares copiis, ſi ſecundum iſtam diſciplinam non magis occidiliceret, quàm occidere?</hi> Let the Anſwerer Conſture theſe words, and he ſhall eaſily perceive they will render the ſenſe that I gave of them, <hi>The Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans had number and force ſufficient to reſiſt; but they had not warrant;</hi> And if he had looked a little before theſe words, he might have ſeen <hi>Tertullian</hi> affirming, the Chriſtians had none ſuch as <hi>Caſſius</hi> among them.</p>
               <p>Then out of his great reading, but ſmall judgement (for he ſeems to turn his books by their <hi>Indices</hi> onely) he tells us, <hi>He believes the primitive Divines held not ſuch Tenets as are of late ſtarted up concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Kings, for if they did, ſurely the Parliament ſhould have heard of it, Pag.</hi> 22. I beleive they did not indeed hold ſuch, as are newly ſtarted up by thoſe that the Houſes have been willing to heare; for my part, it was not my purpoſe (though the performance had not been difficult) to tell the Parliament what the primitive Divines held, but only to let the people know, what Scripture and reaſon taught them to hold and reſt upon.</p>
               <p>But you give us ſome inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces out of antiquity. 1. <hi>Theoderet cites</hi> Plo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus <hi>his ſaying, Evil men raign by reaſon of the Cowardlines of their ſubjects, we muſt not ſo think of providence as to think our ſelves nothing. Anſ.</hi> If <hi>Plotinus</hi> had ſpoken to your ſenſe for the Depoſing of Tyrants,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:155829:44"/>the Authority had reſted barely on <hi>Plotinus;</hi> for <hi>Theoderet</hi> cites him not to any purpoſe concerning Kings, but only to ſhew that <hi>Plotinus</hi> acknowledged Providence. Nor is your ſenſe the meaning of <hi>Plotinus,</hi> for his drift is to ſhew that Providence expects our endeavours (not to the depoſing or killing of Tyrantrs, as you deſperatly inſinuate, and therefore tranſlate the word <hi>Cowardlines,</hi> which here ſignifies ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, effeminacy, luxury, but) to the attaining of an happy and quiet life; unto which purpoſe he there ſhewes, how ſome men do bear the puniſhment <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of their ſloath and luxury; how others though evill, yet being laborious do reap more fruit of their tillage; and accordingly how evill men rule through the negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and ſloathfulneſſe of others, that is, they being ſedulous doe gain the Dominion, or being in it, they turne evill for the puniſhment of the ſloath and vitiouſneſſe of their Subjects, for it followes immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (which you have left out) this is juſt; juſt? how? that they ſhould be ſo puniſhed; and no reaſon their happineſſe ſhould be procured by providence or good Governours, when they will doe nothing towards it themſelves; this is the full and only meaning of <hi>Plotinus. Ennead.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>cir: med.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Nicephorus</hi> you ſay, tells us, <hi>of the Godly zeale of a Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who took down</hi> Diocleſians <hi>Proclamation, and tore it in pieces:</hi> I could alſo tell you out of Scripture of <hi>Peters</hi> zeale who did ſtrike with the ſword in defence of his Maſter; but was rebuked for it; for the zeale may be good and commendable when the action is not ſo, but an exceſſe, and not to be drawn into a Rule or example.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, That <hi>Nicephorus</hi> tells us, <hi>The Chriſtians under the King of</hi> Perſia <hi>fled to</hi> Rome <hi>for ſuccor, and how</hi> Atticus <hi>then Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>obtained aid for them—and they were denyed to the</hi> Perſian <hi>King de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding his fugitive Subjects</hi>—we acknowledge ſuch a ſtory in <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cephorus,</hi> though no ſuch matter when <hi>Atticus</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> unleſſe you ſhould mean new <hi>Rome,</hi> that is <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> it ſeems <hi>Nicephorus</hi> his manner of Calling thoſe of that Eaſtern Empire by the name of <hi>Romans</hi> deceived you; but what does the true part of your ſtory prove? that Subjects may fly from their perſecuting King? or that one Prince may protect the Subjects of another Prince, when they are come into his Dominions for releife? be it ſo, neither of them will help your cauſe. But enough of theſe impertinences.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:155829:45"/>
               <head>SECT. XIII. <hi>An Anſwer to what was replyed upon the two laſt Sections of the former Treatiſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT was there ſaid. The defence of Religion, and the Subjects Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty can be no other then pretences of this War — and, It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern's them that will reſiſt upon the Principles, now taught, to render their Prince odious to his people—To theſe and the like ſayings Mr. <hi>Bridge</hi> Replyes, <hi>Theſe are ſad charges, bold and ſcandalous aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to charge a Parliament in the face of the world with Hypocriſie; He declamed againſt uncharitableneſſe in others, where is now the Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this man?</hi> Theſe were not Charges upon a Parliament, but upon the chiefe Contrivers of, and Actors in this Reſiſtance, as Mr <hi>Bridge</hi> might have obſerved in the former Treatiſe; upon theſe indeed they will lye ſad and heavy, when he that knowes the heart ſhall diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Hypocriſie, and all thoſe generous, and honeſt, and noble ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, to whoſe eares the true information of things abroad is not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to come, ſhall ſee it (yea, and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Bridge</hi> too, if his heart be right) to their amazement. Nor does Charity bind the Conſcience to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, or to judge againſt ſenſe; or from condemning one part, when it muſt Iudge between two, as at this time between the King and Subjects in Armes againſt Him; which rules of Charity were laid down and applyed towards the end of the former Treatiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whoſees not how tender the Parliament hath beene of the Kings Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour? therefore they charge all upon His Counſellors, as</hi> David <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>id up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe about</hi> Saul, 1 Sam. c. 26. v. 19. <hi>If the Lord hath ſtirred the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> up againſt me let him accept an aſſering; but if they be the Children of men, curſed be they before the Lord, for they have driven me out this day.</hi> And who ſees not how tender His Majeſty hath been of the reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Parliament charging the fault upon them that give the Counſell, and are the contrivers of all that is done againſt Him. Or who ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not how <hi>Davids</hi> words agree more properly to the King that ha's been driven out and hunted up and downe, then to His adverſaries that have had their abode at pleaſure, and Raigned without Him? but if they will needs ſpeake the word, let them learn this leſſon from them, If ſuch as have unlawfully engaged a King, cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:155829:45"/>be brought to Juſtice then by Subjects taking Armes and fighting againſt their King, it muſt not be done that way, but by referring the matter to God, as <hi>David</hi> did here.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The King is no more bound by vertue of His Oath to maintaine the Government of the Church, as by Law eſtabliſhed, then any other Law of the Kingdome, which if the King and Parliament thinke fit to repeale, They may without breach of the Kings Oath.</hi> Suppoſe they ſhould think fit to doe it, is it no more to take away a Government, which had the conſent of the Catholike Church, and has been received and continued in this Land ever ſince the planting of the Chriſtian Faith here, then to repeal any Law made but yeſterday in compariſon, and in <hi>materia particulari,</hi> of no ſuch concernment? A fundamentall of the Government of the State may not be ſtirred, nor may the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of ſome men be touched, and may the government of the Church be ſo eaſily torn up by the root and foundation? the Eſtates and Immunities of ſo many free Subjects taken away? But the King doth not think fit to do it, ſhall he then by Armes be forced from that, which He is both by Oath and Judgement bound to maintain?</p>
               <p>Upon thoſe words of the former Treatiſe (the Government of the Church by Biſhops is ſimply the beſt; the aboliſhing whereof is one of thoſe many inconveniences, which this Land is now threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with, and which the King hath reaſon by power of Arms to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert) Mr. <hi>Bridge</hi> enters upon a looſe diſcourſe againſt Epiſcopall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. I refor him for his better inſtruction to a book intituled, <hi>Epiſcopacy aſſerted,</hi> lately publiſhed and learnedly written. Then he breaks out. <hi>Now the Dr. ſhewes himſelfe, be had rather the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome be embrewed in a bloody Warre, then Epiſcopacy ſhould downe; Iudge yee, O all Engliſhmen, whether it bee better for you, to have this order taken away, then for the whole Kingdome to lye embrewed in their owne gore?</hi> Nay Mr. <hi>Bridge,</hi> you and your party in Armes ſhew your ſelves hereby what ſpirit yee are of, who will have this Land em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broiled in a bloody Warre, rather then Epiſcopacy, and ſome other things by Law juſtly eſtabliſhed, ſhall not down; for that is the caſe, and ſo propoſed in the former Treatiſe: and then judge all yee En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh men, whether it be better for you to embrew this Kingdome in its own Gore, then to hold the ancient and primitive Government of the Church; and hear, O Heavens, and judge upon whom the guilt will lye; upon the King that will continue that Government, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:155829:46"/>to Law and oath, or upon them that by Armes would force Him from it?</p>
               <p>To that of <hi>Sauls</hi> ſpeare reſtored, Maſter <hi>Bridge</hi> replies; <hi>Though re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored before demanded, yet not before</hi> Saul <hi>had humbled himſelfe to</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, <hi>ſaying, I have ſinned, J will no more doe thee harm, becauſe my ſoule was precious in thy ſight this day.</hi>—We know what you looke for; If you bluſh not yet to have expected it, His <hi>Majeſty</hi> has not been aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to doe it with a great condeſcention; He has even ſupplicated for Peace, He has redreſſed former miſcarriages of Government with new additionalls of Grace, He has promiſed and proteſted for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; Oh that He could ſay, <hi>My Soule has been precious in your eyes this day, this whole yeere;</hi> or that He could finde anſwerable humility in the hearts of Subjects, whoſe Ambition has cauſed His troubles and our miſeries.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Doctor defends the Kings entertainment of Papiſts by</hi> Davids <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; but he muſt prove that</hi> Ziba, <hi>or thoſe that reſorted to</hi> David <hi>in his diſtreſſe were of another Religion, and by Law to be diſarmed.</hi> What needs that? for the Doctor intended onely by thoſe examples to ſhew, that a Prince in His neceſſary defence may entertaine ſuch men, as otherwiſe He would not make uſe of, and may give ſome countenance to ſuch as have relieved Him in diſtreſſe, though otherwiſe as ill deſerving His Grace as a diſſembling <hi>Ziba.</hi> And though, by Law, Papiſts are not to have Armes at their diſpoſing, yet are they not quit of the duty and ſervice of Subjects, they may by juſt authority beare Armes to uſe them according to the direction of that authority; and if a Liſt of the Army againſt his <hi>Majeſty</hi> were examined, there would be found, if not a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiderable number of Papiſts; yet of ſuch as they, that imploy them, would have cauſe to be aſhamed of, ſuch as by Law are to abjure the Land, as men not to be held in with any government.</p>
               <p>Upon the former particulars the <hi>Fuller Anſwerer</hi> is more bitter and malicious, interpreting every thing, that had ſharpneſſe in it, as ſpoken of the Parliament. It was ſaid, That in ſuch a caſe the State would be unreaſonably expoſed to the danger, that every prevailing Faction might bring upon it; This is, according to this mans inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, to call the Parliament, <hi>a prevailing Faction.</hi> It was ſaid, That the people are made to believe by their <hi>good teachers,</hi> that the King was ſo and ſo affected, to whom no more need be ſaid then the <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angell</hi> did to he <hi>Arch-accuſer, The Lord rebuke thee,</hi> alſo that their
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:155829:46"/>preachings were the doctrines of this giddy age, and that many wicked Pamphlets, and bookes written by Enemies to Peace, were <hi>ſuffered</hi> to iſſue forth into every corner of this Land, This is according to this mans apprehenſion, <hi>to call the</hi> Parliament <hi>Declarations wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ked Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, and ſcandalous imputations of this giddy ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and to liken them to the Devill the Arch-accuſer.</hi> I had need ſay again to this man, <hi>the Lord rebuke thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, it was ſaid. If the Papiſt will ſhew himſelfe a good Subject, it is juſt and reaſonable that the King, when He is put to it, admit his helpe, and the more ſhame for them, that profeſſe the Proteſtant reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to force him to it. This is, according to this mans ſenſe, <hi>to call the Papiſts good Subjects, better then the Parliament, how will Romering of this?</hi> The Papiſts have no cauſe to applaud themſelves for any thing ſpoken by me, but this I can ſay, and ſay it upon experience, that they take occaſion to be confirmed and hardened in their way, by the principles and practice of the adverſe party: for how will <hi>Rome</hi> ring of this, That Proteſtants ſhould take Armes againſt their King profeſſing the ſame religion? that a concealed <hi>Tradition</hi> of a reſerved power of reſiſtance ſhould ſo farre prevaile, and the people be ſo finely led on by an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mplicit faith to build upon it, that by vertue thereof the Oathes of Supremacy and Allegiance ſhould be ſo eaſily diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed with? that the Jeſuites themſelves ſhould be cleane out done in the cunning of Lies and Forgeries to uphold a cauſe, that pretends religion?</p>
               <p>This Anſwerer after a fit of railing concludes with Prayer. <hi>I ſhall onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dde this ſhort prayer, and with my very ſoule I ſpeake it, God bleſſe the King and ſend us peace, and if it muſt not be till one ſide have prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, I pray God it may be that ſide that loves the King beſt.</hi> Truth would not let me bitherto accord with this Anſwerer, but Charity now bids me joyne with him, and to adde unto his prayer; That it would pleaſe God to forgive that fide, which under pretence of love to the King, has ſo deeply wounded him in his Perſon and Kingly power, alſo that our peace may be reſtored, not through an abſolute prevailing of either ſide by Armes, but through a loyall ſubmiſſion of that ſide, which has done the wrong to His Majeſty and His People, by this Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe reſiſtance. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have done with this man; Let us ſee how Mr. <hi>Burrows</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes the buſineſſe, <hi>pag.</hi> 140. to the two laſt Sections which concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:155829:47"/>matter of fact, he briefly thus anſwers, <hi>The Doctor puts the caſe thus Whether Conſcience can be perſwaded that the King is ſuch, and ſo minded, as that there may be ſufficient cauſe to take up Armes againſt Him? In this he is as miſerably miſtaken as in all his other grounds from Scripture and Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſon; for we take up no Armes againſt the King, and whatſoever the Kings minde be, there is ſufficient cauſe to take Armes, to defend our ſelves againſt others that ſeek our ruine.</hi> Is it ſo that the Law is in your hand, and it concerns you not, <hi>What ever the Kings minde be?</hi> He is bound by Oath to protect you againſt <hi>thoſe that ſeek your ruine,</hi> and accordingly has the power of the ſword, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending of Armes; will you not then know whether it be his minde to defend you, but take the ſword into your own hand? ſurely herein you are miſerably miſtaken, if you thinke this is not to take Armes againſt the King, and againſt that power which God and the Law en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſts him with, for your protection. Or have you not read how Armes taken up by ſome in the latter end of the Queens time, to remove evill Counſellors, ſuch as they pretended ſought their ruine, were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged a leavying of warre againſt the Queen? it will not helpe you, to ſay Your Arms are taken up by authority of Parliament; thoſe were not, for that's not the point, you may ſee by this, your Armes are againſt the King, and his power and authority, if without it, under what pretence ſoever you may take them up.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the King doe but deny to aſſiſt in delivering us from ſuch dangers, and in delivering up Delinquents, there is cauſe enough to ſatisfie our Conſciences in taking of Armes.</hi> It ſeems now it concernes you to know, what the Kings minde is, though not cauſe ſufficient here to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ie your Conſciences, for you cannot ſay he denied this, till you put your ſelves out of His protection, and were your own protectors in Armes; Nay after you appeared in this poſture, what was denied you from <hi>Nottingham,</hi> that might give you cauſe to proceed in Armes till you brought them to give the King battell? you take away His Armes and power againſt His will, you uſe them in battell to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent endangering of His Perſon, and yet you take not Armes againſt him, and you can ſatisfie your Conſcience of the lawfulneſſe of it.</p>
               <p>See now whether you can ſet ſuch a Conſcience before Gods tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and there lay the plea as you doe, pag. 142. <hi>Lord thou who art the ſearcher of hearts knoweſt we aimed at no hurt to our King, we deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:155829:47"/>to live in Peace, to deliver our Kingdome and Parliament from the rage of ungodly men, to preſerve what thy Majeſty, what the Law of Nature, and of this Land hath made our own.</hi> Dare you juſtifie your ſelves thus at his Tribunall? you may bluſh to ſpeak it before man, that knows not your hearts, but ſees, how you have actually inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Kings Right and Power, and imminently endangered His Perſon, if the mercy of the Lord had not preſerved Him; how you break through the Lawes of God and Nature, not to preſerve what is your own, but to gain the Lord knows what? <hi>Thou telleſt us, that it is not the part of a Chriſtian, but of an Infidel, not to provide for his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</hi> Dare you thus entitle Him to your blood-ſhed and rapines, whereby you provide for your ſelves? has he taught you to provide for the family of the Common-wealth by binding the maſter of the family, and ſmiting your fellow-ſervants? as thoſe did, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.49. <hi>For the ſubſtance of what we have done, it hath been in thy name, that we may be faithfull to our King, Kingdome and Parliament, Pardon we beſeech thee the failings.</hi> Let your ends which you pretend, be never ſo ſpecious, if the means you uſe be not Lawfull and Warrantable, as they are not, for the very ſubſtance of them, either by the Law of God or Man, your plea will not hold, but your account will be heavy for all the blood ſhed and miſeries this Land has groaned under, which might have been prevented if Reaſon would have ſatisfied you: Now the Lord that is at hand, grant you moderation, and then we doubt not, but (with his bleſſing) we ſhall have Peace in good time, to the reſtoring of his truth, the Kings Honour and Rights, the due Priviledges of Parliament, and the Subjects Liberty.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Pag. 2. med, your, <hi>for</hi> their. p. 9. l. 13. your <hi>for</hi> their. p. 49. l. 11. <hi>for</hi> 5. <hi>r.</hi> 15. p. 69. l. 9. natuall <hi>r.</hi> mutuall.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:155829:48"/>
            <head>The Contents of the ſeverall SECTIONS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Sect. I. <hi>The Caſe, and the Queſtion upon it ſtated.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. II. <hi>The frame of this Government as it is phanſyed in the</hi> Fuller Anſwer</item>
               <item>Sect. III. <hi>Of the Originall of Governing power; of Monarchy, and of the beginnings of Government in this Land.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. IV. <hi>Of the Coordination of three Eſtates in Parliament, and of the Supremacy of Power.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. V. <hi>Of the Supply which is phanſyed upon the former Coor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. VI. <hi>Of the finall reſolution of this States Indgement, and of the power of declaring Law.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. VII. <hi>The finall reſolution is not arbitrary in the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but only in the three Eſtates.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. VIII. <hi>A confutation of what is replied by the Anſwerers upon the firſt Section of the former Treatiſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. IX. <hi>A Confutation of what was replied upon the ſecond Sect. of the former Treatiſe, touching places of Scripture pretended for, or alledged againſt reſiſtance.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. X. <hi>A Confutation of what was replied upon the third Sect. of the former Treatiſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. XI. <hi>A Confutation of what was replied upon the fourth Sect. of the former Treatiſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. XII. <hi>A Confutation of what was replied upon the fift Sect. of the former Treatiſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. XIII. <hi>An Anſwer to what was replied upon the two laſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the former Treatiſe.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:155829:48"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
